<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, LUXOR, May 15, 1867.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/101">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</name>
               <date when="1867-05-15">15 May 1867</date>
               <rs type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/360502">Luxor</rs>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff
                  Gordon</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Dearest <name type="person" ref="#alick">Alick</name>, </p>
         <p> All the Christendom of Upper Egypt is in a state of excitement, owing to the arrival of
            the Patriarch of <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>, who is now in Luxor. My
            neighbour, Mikaeel, entertains him, and <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> has
            been busily decorating his house and arranging the illumination of his garden, and
            to-day is gone to cook the confectionery, he being looked upon as the person best
            acquainted with the customs of the great. Last night the Patriarch sent for me, and I
            went to kiss his hand, but I won’t go again. It was a very droll caricature of the
            thunders of the Vatican. Poor Mikaeel had planned that I was to dine with the Patriarch,
            and had borrowed my silver spoons, etc., etc., in that belief. But the representative of
            St. Mark is furious against the American missionaries who have converted some twenty
            Copts at Koos, and he could not bring himself to be decently civil to a Protestant. I
            found a coarse-looking man seated on a raised divan smoking his chibouk, on his right
            were some priests on a low divan; I went up and kissed his hand and was about to sit by
            the priests, but he roughly ordered a cawass to put a wooden chair _off the carpet_ to
            his left, at a distance from him, and told me to sit there. I looked round to see
            whether any of my neighbours were present, and I saw the consternation in their faces
            so, not wishing to annoy them, I did as if I did not perceive the affront, and sat down
            and talked for half an hour to the priests, and then took leave. I was informed that the
            Catholics were _naas mesakeen_ (poor inoffensive people), and that the Muslims at least
            were of an old religion, but that the Protestants ate meat all the year round, ‘like
            dogs’—‘or Muslims,’ put in <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name>, who stood behind
            my chair and did not relish the mention of dogs and the ‘English religion’ in one
            sentence. As I went the Patriarch called for dinner, it seems he had told Mikaeel he
            would not eat with me. It is evidently ‘a judgment’ of a most signal nature that I
            should be snubbed for the offences of missionaries, but it has caused some ill blood;
            the Kadee and Sheykh Yussuf and the rest, who all intended to do the civil to the
            Patriarch, now won’t go near him on account of his rudeness to me. He has come up in a
            steamer, at the Pasha’s expense, with a guard of cawasses, and, of course, is loud in
            praise of the Government, though he failed in getting the Moudir to send all the
            Protestants of Koos to the public works, or the army. </p>
         <p> From what he said before me about the Abyssinians, and still more, from what he said to
            others about the English prisoners up there, I am convinced that the place to put the
            screw on is the _Batrarchane_ (Patriarch’s palace) at <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>, and that the priests are at the bottom of that affair. {350} He
            boasted immensely of the obedience and piety of _El Habbesh_ (the Abyssinians). </p>
         <p> _Saturday_.—Yesterday I heard a little whispered grumbling about the money demanded by
            the ‘Father.’ One of my Copt neighbours was forced to sell me his whole provision of
            cooking butter to pay his quota. This a little damps the exultation caused by seeing him
            so honoured by the Effendina. One man who had heard that he had called the American
            missionaries ‘beggars,’ grumbled to me, ‘Ah yes, beggars, beggars, they didn’t beg of me
            for money.’ I really do think that there must be something in this dread of the
            Protestant movement. Evidently the Pasha is backing up the Patriarch who keeps his
            church well apart from all other Christians, and well under the thumb of the Turks. It
            was pretty to hear the priests talk so politely of Islam, and curse the Protestants so
            bitterly. We were very nearly having a row about a woman, who formerly turned Moslimeh
            to get rid of an old blind Copt husband who had been forced upon her, and was permitted
            to recant, I suppose in order to get rid of the Muslim husband in his turn. However he
            said, ‘I don’t care, she is the mother of my two children, and whether she is Muslim or
            Christian she is my wife, and I won’t divorce her, but I’ll send her to church as much
            as she likes.’ Thereupon the priests of course dropped the wrangle, much to the relief
            of Sheykh Yussuf, in whose house she had taken up her quarters after leaving the church,
            and who was afraid of being drawn into a dispute. </p>
         <p> My new little Darfour boy is very funny and very intelligent. I hope he will turn out
            well, he seems well disposed, though rather lazy. Mabrook quarrelled with a boy
            belonging to the quarter close to us about a bird, and both boys ran away. The Arab boy
            is missing still I suppose, but Mabrook was brought back by force, swelling with
            passion, and with his clothes most scripturally ‘rent.’ He had regularly ‘run amuck.’
            Sheykh Yussuf lectured him on his insolence to the people of the quarter, and I wound up
            by saying, ‘Oh my son! whither dost thou wish to go? I cannot let thee wander about like
            a beggar, with torn clothes and no money, that the police may take thee and put thee in
            the army; but say where thou desirest to go, and we will talk about it with discretion.’
            It was at once borne in upon him that he did not want to go anywhere, and he said, ‘I
            repent; I am but an ox, bring the courbash, beat me, and let me go to finish cooking the
            Sitt’s dinner.’ I remitted the beating, with a threat that if he bullied the neighbours
            again he would get it at the police, and not from <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name>’s very inefficient arm. In half an hour he was as merry as ever. It was
            a curious display of negro temper, and all about nothing at all. As he stood before me,
            he looked quite grandly tragic; and swore he only wanted to run outside and die; that
            was all. </p>
         <p> I wish you could have heard (and understood) my _soirées, au clair de la lune_, with
            Sheykh Yussuf and Sheykh Abdurrachman. How Abdurrachman and I wrangled, and how Yussuf
            laughed, and egged us on. Abdurrachman was wroth at my want of faith in physic
            generally, as well as in particular, and said I talked like an infidel, for had not God
            said, ‘I have made a medicine for every disease?’ I said, ‘Yes, but He does not say that
            He has told the doctors which it is; and meanwhile I say, _hekmet Allah_, (God will
            cure) which can’t be called an infidel sentiment.’ Then we got into alchemy, astrology,
            magic and the rest; and Yussuf vexed his friend by telling gravely stories palpably
            absurd. Abdurrachman intimated that he was laughing at _El-Ilm el-Muslimeen_ (the
            science of the Muslims), but Yussuf said, ‘What is the _Ilm el-Muslimeen_? God has
            revealed religion through His prophets, and we can learn nothing new on that point; but
            all other learning He has left to the intelligence of men, and the Prophet Mohammed
            said, “All learning is from God, even the learning of idolaters.” Why then should we
            Muslims shut out the light, and want to remain ever like children? The learning of the
            Franks is as lawful as any other.’ Abdurrachman was too sensible a man to be able to
            dispute this, but it vexed him. </p>
         <p> I am tired of telling all the _plackereien_ of our poor people, how three hundred and
            ten men were dragged off on Easter Monday with their bread and tools, how in four days
            they were all sent back from <name type="place" ref="#kenneh">Keneh</name>, because
            there were no orders about them, and made to _pay their boat hire_. Then in five days
            they were sent for again. Meanwhile the harvest was cut green, and the wheat is lying
            out unthreshed to be devoured by birds and rats, and the men’s bread was wasted and
            spoiled with the hauling in and out of boats. I am obliged to send camels twenty miles
            for charcoal, because the Abab’deh won’t bring it to market any more, the tax is too
            heavy. Butter too we have to buy secretly, none comes into the market. When I remember
            the lovely smiling landscape which I first beheld from my windows, swarming with beasts
            and men, and look at the dreary waste now, I feel the ‘foot of the Turk’ heavy indeed.
            Where there were fifty donkeys there is but one; camels, horses, all are gone; not only
            the horned cattle, even the dogs are more than decimated, and the hawks and vultures
            seem to me fewer; mankind has no food to spare for hangers-on. The donkeys are sold, the
            camels confiscated, and the dogs dead (the one sole advantage). Meat is cheap, as
            everyone must sell to pay taxes and no one has money to buy. I am implored to take sheep
            and poultry for what I will give.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>