<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Mrs. Austin, LUXOR, May 23, 1867.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/102">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</name>
               <date when="1867-05-23">23 May 1867</date>
               <rs type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/360502">Luxor</rs>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/59830344">Sarah Austin</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Dearest <foreign xml:lang="de"><name type="person" ref="#sarah_austin">Mutter</name></foreign>, </p>
         <p> I have only time for a few words by Giafar Pasha, who goes early to-morrow morning. My
            boat arrived all right and brought your tin box. The books and toys are very welcome.
            The latter threw little Darfour into ecstasies, and he got into disgrace for ‘playing
            with the Sitt’ instead of minding some business on hand. I fear I shall spoil him, he is
            so extremely engaging and such a baby. He is still changing his teeth, so cannot be more
            than eight; at first I did not like him, and feared he was sullen, but it was the usual
            _khoss_ (fear), the word that is always in one’s ears, and now that is gone, he is
            always coming hopping in to play with me. He is extremely intelligent and has a pretty
            baby nigger face. The Darfour people are, as you know, an independent and brave people,
            and by no means ‘savages.’ I can’t help thinking how pleased Rainie would be with the
            child. He asked me to give him the picture of the English Sultaneh out of the
            _Illustrated London News_, and has pasted it inside the lid of his box. </p>
         <p> I am better as usual, since the hot weather has begun, the last six days. I shall leave
            this in a week, I think, and Mustapha and Yussuf will go with me to <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>. Yussuf was quite enchanted with your note to him; his eyes
            glistened, and he took an envelope to keep it carefully. <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> said such a letter is like a _hegab_ (amulet) and Yussuf said, ‘Truly it
            is, and I could never have one with more _baraka_ (blessing) or more like the virtue
            which went out of Jesus, if ever I wore one at all; I will never part with it.’ </p>
         <p> We had a very pretty festival for the Sheykh, whose tomb you have a photograph of, and
            I spent a very pleasant evening with Sheykh Abd el-Mootooal, who used to scowl at me,
            but now we are ‘like brothers.’ I found him very clever, and better informed than any
            Arab I have met, who is quite apart from all Franks. I was astonished to find that he
            _abondait dans man sens_ in my dispute with Sheykh Abdurrachman, and said that it was
            the duty of Muslims to learn what they could from us, and not to stick to the old
            routine. </p>
         <p> On Sunday the Patriarch snubbed me, and would not eat with me, and on Monday a _Walee_
            (saint) picked out tit-bits for me with his own fingers, and went with me inside the
            tomb. The Patriarch has made a blunder with his progress. He has come ostentatiously as
            the _protegé_ and _pronem_ of the Pasha, and he has ‘eaten’ and beaten the fellaheen.
            The Copts of Luxor have had to pay fifty pounds for the honour of his presence, besides
            no end of sheep, poultry, butter, etc. If I were of a proselytising mind I could make
            converts of several whose pockets and backs are smarting, and the American missionaries
            will do it. Of course the Muslims sympathize with the converts to a religion which has
            no ‘idols,’ and no monks, and whose priests marry like other folk, so they are the less
            afraid. I hear there are now fifty Protestants at Koos, and the Patriarch was furious
            because he could not beat them. <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> cooked a
            grand dinner for him last night for our neighbour Mikaeel, and the eating was not over
            till two in the morning. Our Government should manage to put the screw on him about our
            Abyssinian prisoners. I dare not say who told me all he said, but he was a truthful man
            and a Christian. The Patriarch answered me sharply when I asked about the state of
            religion in Abyssinia that, ‘they were lovers of the faith, and his obedient children.’
            Whenever there is mischief among the Copts, the priests are at the bottom of it. If the
            Patriarch chose those people would be let go; and so it would be but he hates all
            Europeans bitterly. </p>
         <p> I should like to have the _Revue des Deux Mondes_ of all things, but I don’t know how
            it is to come here, or what the postage would cost. They send nothing but letters above
               <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name> by post, as all goes on men’s backs.
            ‘Inshallah! I am the bearer of good news,’ cries the postman, as he flings the letter
            over the wall. I am so glad of the chance of getting news to you quick by Giafar Pasha,
            who came here like a gentleman, alone, without a retinue; he is on his way from two
            years in the Soudan, where he was absolute Pasha. He is very much liked and respected,
            and seems a very sensible and agreeable man, quite unlike any Turkish big-wig I have
            seen. Great potentate as he is, he made Yussuf Mustapha and Abdallah sit down, and was
            extremely civil and simple in his manners.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>