<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Mrs. Austin, BOULAK, July 28, 1867.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/105">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</name>
               <date when="1867-07-28">28 July 1867</date>
               <rs type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/360630">Cairo</rs>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/59830344">Sarah Austin</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Dearest <foreign xml:lang="de"><name type="person" ref="#sarah_austin">Mutter</name></foreign>, </p>
         <p> I know I can write nothing more sure to please you than that I am a good deal better.
            It has been intensely hot, and the wind very worrying, but my cough has greatly abated
            and I do not feel so weak as I did. I am anchored here in the river at my old quarters,
            and have not yet been ashore owing to the hot wind and the dust, which of course are far
            less troublesome here on the river. I have seen but very few people and have but one
            neighbour, in a boat anchored near mine, a very bewitching Circassian, the former slave
            of a rich Pasha, now married to a respectable dragoman, and staying in his boat for a
            week or two. She is young and pretty, and very amiable, and we visit each other often
            and get on very well indeed. She is a very religious little lady, and was much relieved
            when I assured her it was not part of my daily devotions to curse the Prophet, and
            revile the noble Koran. </p>
         <p> I am extremely glad that the English have given a hearty welcome to the Ameer
            el-Moornemeen (Commander of the Faithful); it will have an excellent effect in all
            Mussulman countries. A queer little Indian from Delhi who had been converted to Islam,
            and spent four years at <name type="place" ref="#mecca">Mecca</name> acting as dragoman
            to his own countrymen, is now settled at Karnac. I sent for him, and he carne shaking in
            his shoes. I asked why he was afraid? ‘Oh, perhaps I was angry about something, and he
            was my _rayah_, and I might have him beaten.’ I cried out at him, ‘Ask pardon of God, O
            man. How could I beat thee any more than thou couldst beat me? Have we not laws? and art
            thou not my brother, and the _rayah_ of our Queen, as I am and no more?’ ‘Mashallah!’
            exclaimed the six or eight fellaheen who were waiting for physic, in prodigious
            admiration and wonder; ‘and did we not tell thee that the face of the Sitt brings good
            fortune and not calamity and stick?’ I found the little Indian had been a hospital
            servant in Calcutta, and was practising a little physic on his own account. So I gave
            him a few drugs especially for bad eyes, which he knew a good deal about, and we became
            very good friends; he was miserable when I left and would have liked me to have taken
            him as a volunteer servant. </p>
         <p> I have come to a curious honour. _Ich bin beim lebendigem Leibe besungen_. Several
            parties of real Arabs came with their sick on camels from the desert above <name type="place" ref="#edfou">Edfou</name>. I asked at last what brought them, and they
            told me that a _Shaer_ (bard or poet) had gone about singing my praises, as how the
            daughter of the English was a flower on the heads of the Arabs, and those who were sick
            should go and smell the perfume of the flower and rejoice in the brightness of the light
            (_nooreen_)—my name. Rather a highflown way of mentioning the ‘exhibition’ of a black
            dose. But we don’t feel that a man makes a fool of himself here when he is romantic in
            his talk even about an old woman. </p>
         <p> It is no use to talk of the state of things here; all classes are suffering terribly
            under the fearful taxation, the total ruin of the fellaheen, and the destruction of
            trade brought about by this much extolled Pasha. My grocer is half ruined by the
            ‘improvements’ made a _l’instar de Paris_—long military straight roads cut through the
            heart of <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>. The owners are expropriated, and
            there is an end of it. Only those who have half a house left are to be pitied, because
            they are forced to build a new front to the street on a Frankish model which renders it
            uninhabitable to them and unsaleable. </p>
         <p> The river men are excited about the crews gone to Paris, for fear they should be
            forcibly detained by the _Sultaneh Franzaweeh_, I assured them that they will all come
            home safe and happy, with a good backsheesh. Many of them think it a sort of degradation
            to be taken for the Parisians to stare at like an anteeka, a word which here means what
            our people call a ‘curiosity.’ </p>
         <p> I go on very well with my two boys. Mabrook washes very well and acts as _marmiton_.
            Darfour is housemaid and waiter in his very tiny way. He is only troublesome as being
            given to dirty his clothes in an incredibly short time. His account of the school system
            of Darfour is curious. How when the little boy has achieved excellence he is carried
            home in triumph to his father’s house, who makes a festival for the master and boys. I
            suppose you will be surprised to hear that the Darfour ‘niggers’ can nearly all read and
            write. Poor little Darfour apologised to me for his ignorance, he was stolen he said,
            when he had only just begun to go to school. I wish an English or French servant could
            hear the instructions given by an Alim here to serving men. How he would resent them!
            ‘When thou hast tired out thy back do not put thy hand behind it (do not shirk the
            burden). Remember that thou art not only to obey, but to please thy master, whose bread
            thou eatest;’ and much more of the like. In short, a standard of religious obedience and
            fidelity fit for the highest Catholic idea of the ‘religious life.’ Upon the few who
            seek instruction it does have an effect (I am sure that <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> looks on his service as a religious duty), but of course they are few;
            and those who don’t seek it themselves get none. It is curious how all children here are
            left utterly without any religious instruction. I don’t know whether it is in
            consequence of this that they grow up so very devout.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>