<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, BOULAK, September 7, 1867.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/109">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</name>
               <date when="1867-09-07">7 September 1867</date>
               <rs type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/360630">Cairo</rs>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff
                  Gordon</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Dearest <name type="person" ref="#alick">Alick</name>, </p>
         <p> Many thanks for your letter and for all the trouble you have taken. I wish you were
            better. </p>
         <p> There is such a group all stitching away at the big new sail; <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name>, the <name type="person" ref="#reis">Reis</name>, two or
            three volunteers, some old sailors of mine, and little Darfour. If I die I think you
            must have that tiny nigger over; he is such a merry little soul, I am sure you would
            love him, he is quite a civilized being and has a charming temper, and he seems very
            small to be left alone in the world. </p>
         <p> I hope <name type="person" ref="#maurice">Maurice</name> is not of the faction of the
            _ennuyés_ of this generation. I am more and more of <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name>’s opinion, who said, with a pleased sigh, as we sat on the deck under
            some lovely palm-trees in the bright moon-light, moored far from all human dwellings,
            ‘how sweet are the quiet places of the world.’ </p>
         <p> I wonder when Europe will drop the absurd delusion about Christians being persecuted by
            Muslims. It is absolutely the other way,—here at all events. The Christians know that
            they will always get backed by some Consul or other, and it is the Muslims who go to the
            wall invariably. The brute of a Patriarch is resolved to continue his persecution of the
            converts, and I was urged the other day by a Sheykh to go to the Sheykh ul-Islam himself
            and ask him to demand equal rights for all religions, which is the law, on behalf of
            these Coptic Protestants. Everywhere the Ulema have done what they could to protect
            them, even at <name type="place" ref="#siout">Siout</name>, where the American
            missionaries had caused them (the Ulemas) a good deal of annoyance on a former occasion.
            No one in Europe can conceive how much the Copts have the upper hand in the villages.
            They are backed by the Government, and they know that the Europeans will always side
            with them. </p>
         <p> _September_ 13.—<name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> is crazy with delight at
            the idea of <name type="person" ref="#maurice">Maurice</name>’s arrival, and <name type="person" ref="#reis">Reis</name> Mohammed is planning what men to take who can
            make fantasia, and not ask too much wages. Let me know what boat <name type="person" ref="#maurice">Maurice</name> comes by that I may send <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> to <name type="place" ref="#alexandria">Alexandria </name> to
            meet him. <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> begs me to give you and Sitti
            Rainie his best salaam, and his assurance that he will take great care of the young
            master and ‘keep him very tight.’ I think <name type="person" ref="#maurice">Maurice</name> will be diverted with small Darfour. Mabrook now really cooks very
            fairly under <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name>’s orders, but he is beyond
            belief uncouth, and utters the wildest howls now that his voice is grown big and strong
            like himself. Moreover he ‘won’t be spoken to,’ as our servants say; but he is honest,
            clean, and careful. I should not have thought any human creature could remain so
            completely a savage in a civilized community. I rather respect his savage _hauteur_,
            especially as it is combined with truth and honesty.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>