<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, BOULAK, June 14, 1868.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/117">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</name>
               <date when="1868-06-14">14 June 1868</date>
               <rs type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/360630">Cairo</rs>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff
                  Gordon</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Dearest <name type="person" ref="#alick">Alick</name>, </p>
         <p> The climate has been odious for Egypt—to shiver in cold winds of June on the Nile seems
            hard. <name type="person" ref="#maurice">Maurice</name> inherits my faculty for getting
            on with ‘d------d niggers’; all the crew kissed him on both cheeks and swore to come
            back again in the winter; and up the country he was hand and glove with all the
            fellaheen, eating a good deal of what he called ‘muck’ with great enjoyment, walking arm
            in arm with a crazy derweesh, fetching home a bride at night and swearing lustily by the
            Prophet. The good manners of the Arab _canaille_, have rubbed off the very disagreeable
            varnish which he got at Brussels. </p>
         <p> Dr. Patterson wants me to go to <name type="place" ref="#beyrout">Beyrout</name> or one
            of the Greek isles for a change. I am very feeble and short of breath—but I will try the
            experiment. Would you be shocked if a nigger taught <name type="person" ref="#maurice">Maurice</name>? One Hajjee Daboos I know to be a capital Arabic scholar and he
            speaks French like a Parisian, and Italian also, only he is a real nigger and so is the
            best music-master in <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>. _Que faire_? it’s not
            catching, as Lady Morley said, and I won’t present you with a young mulatto any more
            than with a young _brave Belge_. I may however find someone at <name type="place" ref="#beyrout">Beyrout</name>. <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name> is in
            such a state of beggary that all educated young men have fled. <name type="person" ref="#maurice">Maurice</name> has no sort of idea why a nigger should not be as good
            as anyone else, but thinks perhaps you might not approve. </p>
         <p> You would have stared to see old Achmet Agha Abd el-Sadig, a very good friend of ours
            at <name type="place" ref="#assouan">Assouan</name>, coaxing and patting the _weled_
            (boy) when he dined here the other day, and laughing immoderately at <name type="person" ref="#maurice">Maurice</name>’s nonsense. He is one of the M.P.’s for <name type="place" ref="#assouan">Assouan</name>, and a wealthy and much respected man in
            the Saeed. The Abyssinian affair is an awful disappointment to the Pasha; he had laid
            his calculations for something altogether different, and is furious. The Coptic clergy
            are ready to murder us. The Arabs are all in raptures. ‘God bless the English general,
            he has frightened our Pasha.’ </p>
         <p> Giafar Pasha backsheeshed me an _abbayeh_ of crimson silk and gold, also a basket of
            coffee. I was obliged to accept them as he sent his son with them, and to refuse would
            have been an insult, and as he is the one Turk I do think highly of I did not wish to
            affront him. It was at Luxor on his way to <name type="place" ref="#khartoum">Khartoum
            </name>. He also invited <name type="person" ref="#maurice">Maurice</name> to <name type="place" ref="#khartoum">Khartoum </name>, and proposed to send a party to fetch
            him from Korosko, on the Nile. Giafar is Viceroy of the Soudan, and a very quiet man,
            who does not ‘eat the people.’ </p>
         <p> My best love to <name type="person" ref="#janet">Janet</name>, I’ll write soon to her,
            but I am _lazy_ and <name type="person" ref="#maurice">Maurice</name> is worse. <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> nearly cried when <name type="person" ref="#maurice">Maurice</name> went to <name type="place" ref="#alexandria">Alexandria
            </name> for a week. ‘I seem to feel how dull we shall be without him when he goes away
            for good,’ said he, and Darfour expresses his intention of going with <name type="person" ref="#maurice">Maurice</name>. ‘Thou must give me to the young man
            backsheesh,’ as he puts it, ‘because I have plenty of sense and shall tell him what to
            do.’ That is the little rascal’s sauce. Terence’s slaves are true to the life here.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>