<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, ALEXANDRIA, May 12, 1863.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/12">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</name>
               <rs type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/361058">Alexandria</rs>
               <date when="1863-05-12">12 May 1863</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff
                  Gordon</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Dearest <name type="person" ref="#alick">Alick</name>,</p>

         <p>I only got your letter an hour ago, and the mail goes out at four. I enclose to you the
            letter I had written to my mother, so I need not repeat about my plans. Continue to
            write here, a letter comes as soon and safer. My general health is so much stronger and
            better—especially before I had this last severe attack—that I still hope, though it is a
            severe trial of patience not to throw it up and come home for good. It would be
            delightful to have you at <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name> now I have pots
            and pans and all needful for a house, but a carpet and a few mattresses, if you could
            camp with me <hi rendition="italic"><foreign xml:base="fr">à l’Arabe</foreign></hi>.</p>

         <p>How you would revel in old <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Masr el-Kahira</name>, peep
            up at lattice windows, gape like a <hi rendition="italic"><foreign xml:base="fr">gasheem</foreign></hi> (green one) in the <foreign xml:lang="ar">bazaar</foreign>, go wild over the mosques, laugh at portly Turks and dignified Sheykhs
            on their white donkeys, drink sherbet in the streets, ride wildly about on a donkey,
            peer under black veils at beautiful eyes and feel generally intoxicated! I am quite a
            good cicerone now of the glorious old city. <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name>
            is in raptures at the idea that the <hi rendition="italic"><foreign xml:base="fr">Sidi
                  el Kebir</foreign></hi> (the Great Master) might come, and still more if he
            brought the ‘little master.’ He plans meeting you on the steamboat and bringing you to
            me, that I may kiss your hand first of all. <hi rendition="italic"><foreign xml:base="fr">Mashallah</foreign></hi>! How our hearts would be dilated!</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>