<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, ALEXANDRIA, October 26, 1863.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/16">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</name>
               <rs type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/361058">Alexandria</rs>
               <date when="1863-10-26">26 October 1863</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff
                  Gordon</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Dearest <name type="person" ref="#alick">Alick</name>,</p>

         <p>I went to two <foreign xml:lang="ar">hareem</foreign>s the other day with a little boy
            of <name type="person" ref="#mustapha_aga">Mustapha Aga</name>’s, and was much pleased.
            A very pleasant Turkish lady put out all her splendid bedding and dresses for me, and
            was most amiable. At another a superb Arab with most <hi rendition="italic"><foreign xml:lang="fr">grande dame</foreign></hi> manners, dressed in white cotton and with
            unpainted face, received me statelily. Her house would drive you wild, such antique
            enamelled tiles covering the panels of the walls, all divided by carved woods, and such
            carved screens and galleries, all very old and rather dilapidated, but superb, and the
            lady worthy of the house. A bold-eyed slave girl with a baby put herself forward for
            admiration, and was ordered to bring coffee with such cool though polite imperiousness.
            One of our great ladies can’t half crush a rival in comparison, she does it too
            coarsely. The quiet scorn of the pale-faced, black-haired Arab was beyond any English
            powers. Then it was fun to open the lattice and make me look out on the square, and to
            wonder what the neighbours would say at the sight of my face and European hat. She asked
            about my children and blessed them repeatedly, and took my hand very kindly in doing so,
            for fear I should think her envious and fear her eye—she had none.</p>

         <p><date>Tuesday</date>.—The post goes out to-morrow, and I have such a cold I must stay in
            bed and cannot write much. I go on Thursday and shall go to <name type="person" ref="#brigg">Briggs</name>’ house. Pray write to me at <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>. <name type="person" ref="#sally">Sally</name> and I are
            both unwell and anxious to get up the river. I can’t write more.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>