<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Mrs. Ross, CAIRO, December 1, 1863.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/20">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</name>
               <rs type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/360630">Cairo</rs>
               <date when="1863-12-01">1 December 1863</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person">Mrs. Ross</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST JANET,</p>

         <p>I should much like to go with Thayer if his times and seasons will suit mine; but I
            cannot wait indefinitely, still less come down the river before the end of April. But
            most likely the Pasha will give him a boat. It is getting cold here and I feel my throat
            sore to-day. I went to see Hassan yesterday, he is much better, but very weak and pale.
            It is such a nice family—old father, mother, and sister, all well-bred and pleasing like
            Hassan himself. He almost shrieked at hearing of your fall, and is most anxious to see
            you when you come here. Zeyneb, after behaving very well for three weeks, has turned
            quietly sullen and displays great religious intolerance. It would seem that the Berberi
            men have put it into her head that we are inferior beings, and she pretends not to be
            able to eat because she thinks everything is pig. <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name>’s eating the food does not convince her. As she evidently does not like
            us I will offer her to Mrs. <name type="person" ref="#hekekian_bey">Hekekian Bey</name>,
            and if she does not do there, in a household of black Mussulman slaves, they must pass
            her on to a Turkish house. She is very clever and I am sorry, but to keep a sullen face
            about me is more than I can endure, as I have shown her every possible kindness. I think
            she despises <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> for his affection towards me.
            How much easier it is to instil the bad part of religion than the good; it is really a
            curious phenomenon in so young a child. She waits capitally at table, and can do most
            things, but she won’t move if the fancy takes her except when ordered, and spends her
            time on the terrace. One thing is that the life is dull for a child, and I think she
            will be happier in a larger, more bustling house. I don’t know whether, after the
            fearful example of Mrs. B., I can venture to travel up the Nile with such a _séducteur_
            as our dear Mr. Thayer. What do you think? Will gray hairs on my side and _mutual_ bad
            lungs guarantee our international virtue; or will someone ask the Pater when he means to
            divorce me? Would it be considered that Yankeedoodle had ‘stuck a feather in his cap’ by
            leading a British matron and grandmother astray?</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>