<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, Wednesday, January 20, 1864.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/26">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</name>
               <date when="1864-01-20">20 January 1864</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff
                  Gordon</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>I received your welcome letters of December 15 and 25 on Monday, to my great joy, but
            was much grieved to hear of Thomas’s death, and still more so to hear from <name type="person" ref="#janet">Janet</name> that Thackeray and Mrs. Alison were dead. She
            died the morning I left <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>, so her last act
            almost was to send sweetmeats to the boat after me on the evening before. Poor dear soul
            her sweetness and patience were very touching. We have had a week of piercing winds, and
            yesterday I stayed in bed, to the great surprise of Mustapha’s little girl who came to
            see me. To-day was beautiful again, and I mounted old Mustapha’s cob pony and jogged
            over his farm with him, and lunched on delicious sour cream and _fateereh_ at a
            neighbouring village, to the great delight of the _fellaheen_. It was more Biblical than
            ever; the people were all relations of Mustapha’s, and to see Sidi <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name>, the head of the household, and the ‘young men coming in from
            the field,’ and the ‘flocks and herds and camels and asses,’ was like a beautiful dream.
            All these people are of high blood, and a sort of ‘roll of Battle’ is kept here for the
            genealogies of the noble Arabs who came in with Amr—the first Arab conqueror and
            lieutenant of <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name>. Not one of these brown men,
            who do not own a second shirt, would give his brown daughter to the greatest Turkish
            Pasha. This country _noblesse_ is more interesting to me by far than the town people,
            though <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name>, who is quite a Cockney, and piques
            himself on being ‘delicate,’ turns up his nose at their beggarly pride, as Londoners
            used to do at bare-legged Highlanders. The air of perfect equality—except as to the
            respect due to the head of the clan—with which the villagers treated Mustapha, and which
            he fully returned, made it all seem so very gentlemanly. They are not so dazzled by a
            little show, and far more manly than the Cairenes. I am on visiting terms with all the
            ‘county families’ resident in Luxor already. The Názir (magistrate) is a very nice
            person, and my Sheykh Yussuf, who is of the highest blood (being descended from
            Abu-l-Hajjaj himself), is quite charming. There is an intelligent little German here as
            Austrian Consul, who draws nicely. I went into his house, and was startled by hearing a
            pretty Arab boy, his servant, inquire, ‘_Soll ich den Kaffee bringen_?’ What next? They
            are all mad to learn languages, and Mustapha begs me and <name type="person" ref="#sally">Sally</name> to teach his little girl Zeyneb English. </p>
         <p> _Friday_, 22_nd_.—Yesterday I rode over to Karnac, with Mustapha’s _sais_ running by my
            side. Glorious hot sun and delicious air. To hear the _sais_ chatter away, his tongue
            running as fast as his feet, made me deeply envious of his lungs. Mustapha joined me,
            and pressed me to go to visit the Sheykh’s tomb for the benefit of my health, as he and
            Sheykh Yussuf wished to say a _Fathah_ for me; but I must not drink wine at dinner. I
            made a little difficulty on the score of difference of religion, but Sheykh Yussuf, who
            came up, said that he presumed I worshipped God, and not stones, and that sincere
            prayers were good anywhere. Clearly the bigotry would have been on my side if I had
            refused any longer. So in the evening I went with Mustapha. It was a very curious sight,
            the little dome illuminated with as much oil as the mosque could afford, and the tombs
            of Abu-l-Hajjaj and his three sons. A magnificent old man, like Father Abraham himself,
            dressed in white, sat on a carpet at the foot of the tomb; he was the head of the family
            of Abu-l-Hajjaj. He made me sit by, and was extremely polite. Then came the Názir, the
            Kadee, a Turk travelling on Government business, and a few other gentlemen, who all sat
            down round us after kissing the hand of the old Sheykh. Everyone talked; in fact it was
            a _soirée_ for the entertainment of the dead Sheykh. A party of men sat at the further
            end of the place, with their faces to the Kibleh, and played on a _taraboukeh_ (sort of
            small drum stretched on earthenware which gives a peculiar sound), a tambourine without
            bells, and little tinkling cymbals fitting on thumb and fingers (crotales), and chanted
            songs in honour of Mohammed and verses from the Psalms of David. Every now and then one
            of our party left off talking, and prayed a little or counted his beads. The old Sheykh
            sent for coffee, and gave me the first cup—a wonderful concession. At last the Názir
            proposed a _Fathah_ for me, which the whole group round me repeated aloud, and then each
            said to me, ‘Our Lord God bless and give thee health and peace, to thee and thy family,
            and take thee back safe to thy master and thy children,’ one adding _Ameen_ and giving
            the salaam with the hand. I returned it, and said, ‘Our Lord reward thee and all the
            people of kindness to strangers,’ which was considered a very proper answer. After that
            we went away, and the worthy Názir walked home with me to take a pipe and a glass of
            sherbet, and enjoy a talk about his wife and eight children, who are all in
            Foum-el-Bachr’, except two boys at school in <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>. Government appointments are so precarious that it is not worth while
            to move them up here, as the expense would be too heavy on a salary of £15 a month, with
            the chance of recall any day. In <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name> or Lower
            Egypt it would be quite impossible for a Christian to enter a Sheykh’s tomb at all—above
            all on his birthday festival and on the night of Friday. </p>
         <p> _Friday_, _January_ 29.—I have been too unwell to write all this week, but will finish
            this to-day to send off by Lady Herbert’s boat. The last week has been very cold here,
            the thermometer at 59° and 60°, with a nipping wind and bright sun. I was obliged to
            keep my bed for three or four days, as of course a _palazzo_ without doors or windows to
            speak of was very trying, though far better than a boat. Yesterday and to-day are much
            better, not really much warmer, but a different air. </p>
         <p> The _moolid_ (festival) of the Sheykh terminated last Saturday with a procession, in
            which the new cover of his tomb, and the ancient sacred boat, were carried on men’s
            shoulders. It all seemed to have walked out of the royal tombs, only dusty and shabby
            instead of gorgeous. These festivals of the dead are such as <name type="person" ref="#herodotus">Herodotus</name> alludes to as held in honour of ‘Him whose name he
            dares not mention—Him who sleeps in <name type="place" ref="#philae">Philae</name>,’
            only the name is changed and the mummy is absent. </p>
         <p> For a fortnight everyone who had a horse and could ride came and ‘made fantasia’ every
            afternoon for two hours before sunset; and very pretty it was. The people here show
            their good blood in their riding. On the last three days all strangers were entertained
            with bread and cooked meat at the expense of the Luxor people; every house killed a
            sheep and baked bread. As I could not do that for want of servants enough, I sent 100
            piastres (12s) to the servants of Abu-l-Hajjaj at the mosque to pay for the oil burnt at
            the tomb, etc. I was not well and in bed, but I hear that my gift gave immense
            satisfaction, and that I was again well prayed for. The Coptic Bishop came to see me,
            but he is a tipsy old monk and an impudent beggar. He sent for tea as he was ill, so I
            went to see him, and perceived that his disorder was arrakee. He has a very nice black
            slave, a Christian (Abyssinian, I think), who is a friend of <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name>’s, and who sent <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> a
            handsome dinner all ready cooked; among other things a chicken stuffed with green wheat
            was excellent. <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> constantly gets dinners sent
            him, a lot of bread, some dates and cooked fowls or pigeons, and _fateereh_ with honey,
            all tied up hot in a cloth. I gave an old fellow a pill and dose some days ago, but his
            _dura ilia_ took no notice, and he came for more, and got castor-oil. I have not seen
            him since, but his employer, _fellah_ <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name>, sent
            me a lot of delicious butter in return. I think it shows great intelligence in these
            people, how none of them will any longer consult an Arab _hakeem_ if they can get a
            European to physic them. They now ask directly whether the Government doctors have been
            to Europe to learn _Hekmeh_, and if not they don’t trust them—for poor ‘savages’ and
            ‘heathens’ _ce n’est pas si bête_. I had to interrupt my lessons from illness, but
            Sheykh Yussuf came again last night. I have mastered _Abba shedda o mus beteen_—_ibbi
            shedda o heftedeen_, etc. Oh dear, what must poor Arab children suffer in learning ABC!
            It is a terrible alphabet, and the _shekel_ (points) are _désespérants_; but now I stick
            for want of a dictionary. </p>
         <p> Mr. Arrowsmith kindly gave me Miss Martineau’s book, which I have begun. It is true as
            far as it goes, but there is the usual defect—the people are not real people, only part
            of the scenery to her, as to most Europeans. You may conceive how much we are
            naturalized when I tell you that I have received a serious offer of marriage for <name type="person" ref="#sally">Sally</name>. Mustapha A’gha has requested me to ‘give her to him’ for
            his eldest son Seyyid, a nice lad of nineteen or twenty at most. As Mustapha is the
            richest and most considerable person here, it shows that the Arabs draw no unfavourable
            conclusions as to our morals from the freedom of our manners. He said of course she
            would keep her own religion and her own customs. Seyyid is still in <name type="place" ref="#alexandria">Alexandria </name>, so it will be time to refuse when he returns. I
            said she was too old, but they think that no objection at all. She will have to say that
            her father would not allow it, for of course a handsome offer deserves a civil refusal.
               <name type="person" ref="#sally">Sally</name>’s proposals would be quite an ethnological study;
            Mustapha asked what I should require as dowry for her. Fancy <name type="person" ref="#sally">Sally</name> as <foreign xml:lang="ar">Hareem</foreign> of the Sheykh-el-Beled of
            Luxor! </p>
         <p> I am so charmed with my house that I begin seriously to contemplate staying here all
            the time. <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name> is so dear now, and so many dead
            cattle are buried there, that I think I should do better in this place. There is a huge
            hall, so large and cold now as to be uninhabitable, which in summer would be glorious.
            My dear old captain of steamer XII. would bring me up coffee and candles, and if I ‘sap’
            and learn to talk to people, I shall have plenty of company. </p>
         <p> The cattle disease has not extended above <name type="place" ref="#minieh">Minieh</name> to any degree, and here there has not been a case. _Alhamdulillah_!
            Food is very good here, rather less than half <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name> prices even now; in summer it will be half that. Mustapha urges me to
            stay, and proposes a picnic of a few days over in the tombs with his <foreign xml:lang="ar">Hareem</foreign> as a diversion. I have got a photo, for a stereoscope,
            which I send you, of my two beloved, lovely palm-trees on the river-bank just above and
            looking over <name type="place" ref="#philae">Philae</name>. </p>
         <p> Hitherto my right side has been the bad one, but now one side is uneasy and the other
            impossible to lie on. It does not make one sleep pleasantly, and the loss of my good,
            sound sleep tries me, and so I don’t seem well. We shall see what hot weather will do;
            if that fails I will give up the contest, and come home to see as much as I shall have
            time for of you and my chicks.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>