<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Mrs. Austin, Sunday, February 7, 1864</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/27">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</name>
               <date when="1864-02-07">7 February 1864</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/59830344">Sarah Austin</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Dearest <foreign xml:lang="de"><name type="person" ref="#sarah_austin">Mutter</name></foreign>, </p>
         <p> We have had our winter pretty sharp for three weeks, and everybody has had violent
            colds and coughs—the Arabs, I mean. </p>
         <p> I have been a good deal ailing, but have escaped any violent cold altogether, and now
            the thermometer is up to 64°, and it feels very pleasant. In the sun it is always very
            hot, but that does not prevent the air from being keen, and chapping lips and noses, and
            even hands; it is curious how a temperature, which would be summer in England, makes one
            shiver at <name type="place" ref="#thebes">Thebes</name>—_Alhamdulillah_! it is over
            now. </p>
         <p> My poor Sheykh Yussuf is in great distress about his brother, also a young Sheykh
            (_i.e._, one learned in theology and competent to preach in the mosque). Sheykh Mohammed
            is come home from studying in ‘El-Azhar’ at <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>—I fear to die. I went with Sheykh Yussuf, at his desire, to see if I could
            help him, and found him gasping for breath and very, very ill. I gave him a little
            soothing medicine, and put mustard plasters on him, and as it relieved him, I went again
            and repeated them. All the family and a lot of neighbours crowded in to look on. There
            he lay in a dark little den with bare mud walls, worse off, to our ideas, than any
            pauper; but these people do not feel the want of comforts, and one learns to think it
            quite natural to sit with perfect gentlemen in places inferior to our cattle-sheds. I
            pulled some blankets up against the wall, and put my arm behind Sheykh Mohammed’s back
            to make him rest while the poultices were on him, whereupon he laid his green turban on
            my shoulder, and presently held up his delicate brown face for a kiss like an
            affectionate child. As I kissed him, a very pious old moollah said _Bismillah_ (In the
            name of God) with an approving nod, and Sheykh Mohammed’s old father, a splendid old man
            in a green turban, thanked me with effusion, and prayed that my children might always
            find help and kindness. I suppose if I confessed to kissing a ‘dirty Arab’ in a ‘hovel’
            the English travellers would execrate me; but it shows how much there is in ‘Mussulman
            bigotry, unconquerable hatred, etc.,’ for this family are Seyyids (descendents of the
            Prophet) and very pious. Sheykh Yussuf does not even smoke, and he preaches on Fridays.
            You would love these Saeedees, they are such thorough gentlemen. I rode over to the
            village a few days ago to see a farmer named <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name>. Of course I had to eat, and the people were enchanted at my going alone,
            as they are used to see the English armed and guarded. Sidi <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name>, however, insisted on accompanying me home, which is the
            civil thing here. He piled a whole stack of green fodder on his little nimble donkey,
            and hoisted himself atop of it without saddle or bridle (the fodder was for Mustapha
            A’gha), and we trotted home across the beautiful green barley-fields, to the amazement
            of some European young men out shooting. We did look a curious pair, certainly, with my
            English saddle and bridle, habit, hat and feather, on horseback, and Sidi <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name>’s brown shirt, brown legs and white turban,
            guiding his donkey with his chibouque. We were laughing very merrily, too, over my
            blundering Arabic. </p>
         <p> Young Heathcote and Strutt called here, but were hurrying on up the river. I shall see
            more of them when they come down. Young Strutt is so like his mother I knew him in the
            street. I would like to give him a fantasia, but it is not proper for a woman to send
            for the dancing-girls, and as I am the friend of the Maōhn (police magistrate), the
            Kadee, and the respectable people here, I cannot do what is indecent in their eyes. It
            is quite enough that they approve my unveiled face, and my associating with men; that is
            ‘my custom,’ and they think no harm of it. </p>
         <p> To-morrow or next day Ramadan begins at the first sight of the new moon. It is a great
            nuisance, because everybody is cross. <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> did
            not keep it last year, but this year he will, and if he spoils my dinners, who can blame
            him? There was a wedding close by here last night, and about ten o’clock all the women
            passed under my windows with crys of joy ‘ez-zaghareet’ down to the river. I find, on
            inquiry, that in Upper Egypt, as soon as the bridegroom has ‘taken the face’ of his
            bride, the women take her down to ‘see the Nile.’ They have not yet forgotten that the
            old god is the giver of increase, it seems. </p>
         <p> I have been reading Miss Martineau’s book; the descriptions are excellent, but she
            evidently knew and cared nothing about the people, and had the feeling of most English
            people here, that the difference of manners is a sort of impassable gulf, the truth
            being that their feelings and passions are just like our own. It is curious that all the
            old books of travels that I have read mention the natives of strange countries in a far
            more natural tone, and with far more attempt to discriminate character, than modern
            ones, _e.g._, Niebuhr’s Travels here and in Arabia, Cook’s Voyages, and many others.
            _Have_ we grown so _very_ civilized since a hundred years that outlandish people seem
            like mere puppets, and not like real human beings? Miss M.’s bigotry against Copts and
            Greeks is droll enough, compared to her very proper reverence for ‘Him who sleeps in
               <name type="place" ref="#philae">Philae</name>,’ and her attack upon <foreign xml:lang="ar">hareem</foreign>s outrageous; she implies that they are brothels. I
            must admit that I have not seen a Turkish <foreign xml:lang="ar">hareem</foreign>, and
            she apparently saw no other, and yet she fancies the morals of Turkey to be superior to
            those of Egypt. It is not possible for a woman to explain all the limitations to which
            ordinary people do subject themselves. Great men I know nothing of; but women can and
            do, without blame, sue their husbands-in-law for the full ‘payment of debt,’ and demand
            a divorce if they please in default. Very often a man marries a second wife out of duty
            to provide for a brother’s widow and children, or the like. Of course licentious men act
            loosely as elsewhere. _Kulloolum Beni Adam_ (we are all sons of Adam), as Sheykh Yussuf
            says constantly, ‘bad-bad and good-good’; and modern travellers show strange ignorance
            in talking of foreign natives _in the lump_, as they nearly all do. </p>
         <p> _Monday_.—I have just heard that poor Sheykh Mohammed died yesterday, and was, as
            usual, buried at once. I had not been well for a few days, and Sheykh Yussuf took care
            that I should not know of his brother’s death. He went to Mustapha A’gha, and told him
            not to tell anyone in my house till I was better, because he knew ‘what was in my
            stomach towards his family,’ and feared I should be made worse by the news. And how
            often I have been advised not to meddle with sick Arabs, because they are sure to
            suspect a Christian of poisoning those who die! I do grieve for the graceful, handsome
            young creature and his old father. <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> was vexed
            at not knowing of his death, because he would have liked to help to carry him to the
            grave. </p>
         <p> I have at last learned the alphabet in Arabic, and can write it quite tidily, but now I
            am in a fix for want of a dictionary, and have written to <name type="person" ref="#hekekian_bey">Hekekian Bey</name> to buy me one in <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>. Sheykh Yussuf knows not a word of English, and <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> can’t read or write, and has no notion of
            grammar or of _word for word_ interpretation, and it is very slow work. When I walk
            through the court of the mosque I give the customary coppers to the little boys who are
            spelling away loudly under the arcade, _Abba sheddeh o nusbeyteen_, _Ibbi sheddeh o
            heftedeen_, etc., with a keen sympathy with their difficulties and well-smudged tin
            slates. An additional evil is that the Arabic books printed in England, and at English
            presses here, require a 40-horse power microscope to distinguish a letter. The ciphering
            is like ours, but with other figures, and I felt very stupid when I discovered how I had
            reckoned Arab fashion from right to left all my life and never observed the fact.
            However, they ‘cast down’ a column of figures from top to bottom. </p>
         <p> I am just called away by some poor men who want me to speak to the English travellers
            about shooting their pigeons. It is very thoughtless, but it is in great measure the
            fault of the servants and dragomans who think they must not venture to tell their
            masters that pigeons are private property. I have a great mind to put a notice on the
            wall of my house about it. Here, where there are never less than eight or ten boats
            lying for full three months, the loss to the _fellaheen_ is serious, and our Consul
            Mustapha A’gha is afraid to say anything. I have given my neighbours permission to call
            the pigeons mine, as they roost in flocks on my roof, and to go out and say that the
            Sitt objects to her poultry being shot, especially as I have had them shot off my
            balcony as they sat there. </p>
         <p> I got a note from M. Mounier yesterday, inviting me to go and stay at El-Moutaneh,
            Halim Pasha’s great estate, near Edfoo, and offering to send his dahabieh for me. I
            certainly will go as soon as the weather is decidedly hot. It is now very warm and
            pleasant. If I find <name type="place" ref="#thebes">Thebes</name> too hot as summer
            advances I must drop down and return to <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>, or
            try <name type="place" ref="#suez">Suez </name>, which I hear is excellent in
            summer—bracing desert air. But it is very tempting to stay here—a splendid cool house,
            food extremely cheap; about £1 a week for three of us for fish, bread, butter, meat,
            milk, eggs and vegetables; all grocery, of course, I brought with me; no trouble, rest
            and civil neighbours. I feel very disinclined to move unless I am baked out, and it
            takes a good deal to bake me. The only fear is the Khamaseen wind. I do not feel very
            well. I don’t ail anything in particular; blood-spitting frequent, but very slight; much
            less cough; but I am so weak and good for nothing. I seldom feel able to go out or do
            more than sit in the balcony on one side or other of the house. I have no donkey here,
            the hired ones are so very bad and so dear; but I have written Mounier to try and get me
            one at El-Moutaneh and send it down in one of Halim Pasha’s corn-boats. There is no
            comfort like a donkey always ready. If I have to send for Mustapha’s horse, I feel lazy
            and fancy it is too much trouble unless I can go just when I want. </p>
         <p> I have received a letter from <name type="place" ref="#alexandria">Alexandria </name>
            of January 8. What dreadful weather! We felt the ghost of it here in our three weeks of
            cold. Sometimes I feel as if I must go back to you all _coûte qui coûte_, but I know it
            would be no use to try it in the summer. I long for more news of you and my chicks.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>