<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, LUXOR, February 12, 1864.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/29">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</name>
               <rs type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/360502">Luxor</rs>
               <date when="1864-02-12">12 February 1864</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff
                  Gordon</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Dearest <name type="person" ref="#alick">Alick</name>, </p>
         <p> We are in Ramadan now, and <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> really enjoys a
            good opportunity of ‘making his soul.’ He fasts and washes vigorously, prays his five
            times a day, goes to mosque on Fridays, and is quite merry over it, and ready to cook
            infidels’ dinners with exemplary good-humour. It is a great merit in Muslims that they
            are not at all grumpy over their piety. The weather has set in since five or six days
            quite like paradise. I sit on my lofty balcony and drink the sweet northerly breeze, and
            look at the glorious mountain opposite, and think if only you and the chicks were here
            it would be ‘the best o’ life.’ The beauty of Egypt grows on one, and I think it far
            more lovely this year than I did last. My great friend the Maōhn (he is _not_ the Nazir,
            who is a fat little pig-eyed, jolly Turk) lives in a house which also has a superb view
            in another direction, and I often go and sit ‘on the bench’—_i.e._, the _mastabah_ in
            front of his house—and do what little talk I can and see the people come with their
            grievances. I don’t understand much of what goes on, as the _patois_ is broad and
            doubles the difficulty, or I would send you a Theban police report; but the Maōhn is
            very pleasant in his manner to them, and they don’t seem frightened. We have appointed a
            very small boy our _bowàb_, or porter—or, rather, he has appointed himself—and his
            assumption of dignity is quite delicious. He has provided himself with a huge staff, and
            he behaves like the most tremendous janissary. He is about Rainie’s size, as sharp as a
            needle, and possesses the remains of a brown shirt and a ragged kitchen duster as
            turban. I am very fond of little Achmet, and like to see him doing _tableaux vivants_
            from Murillo with a plate of broken victuals. The children of this place have become so
            insufferable about _backsheesh_ that I have complained to the Maōhn, and he will
            assemble a committee of parents and enforce better manners. It is only here and just
            where the English go. When I ride into the little villages I never hear the word, but am
            always offered milk to drink. I have taken it two or three times and not offered to pay,
            and the people always seem quite pleased. </p>
         <p> Yesterday Sheykh Yussuf came again, the first time since his brother’s death; he was
            evidently deeply affected, but spoke in the usual way, ‘It is the will of God, we must
            all die,’ etc. I wish you could see Sheykh Yussuf. I think he is the sweetest creature
            in look and manner I ever beheld—so refined and so simple, and with the animal grace of
            a gazelle. A high-bred Arab is as graceful as an Indian, but quite without the feline
            _Geschmeidigkeit_ or the look of dissimulation; the eye is as clear and frank as a
            child’s. Mr. Ruchl, the Austrian Consul here, who knows Egypt and Arabia well, tells me
            that he thinks many of them quite as good as they look, and said of Sheykh Yussuf, _Er
            ist so gemüthlich_. There is a German here deciphering hieroglyphics, Herr Dümmichen, a
            very agreeable man, but he has gone across the river to live at el-Kurneh. He has been
            through Ethiopia in search of temples and inscriptions. I am to go over and visit him,
            and see some of the tombs again in his company, which I shall enjoy, as a good
            interpreter is sadly wanted in those mysterious regions. </p>
         <p> My chest is wonderfully better these last six or seven days. It is quite clear that
            downright heat is what does me good. Moreover, I have just heard from M. Mounier that a
            good donkey is _en route_ in a boat from El-Moutaneh—he will cost me between £4 and £5
            and will enable me to be about far more than I can by merely borrowing Mustapha’s horse,
            about which I have scruples as he lends it to other lady travellers. Little Achmet will
            be my sais as well as my door-keeper, I suppose. I wish you would speak to Layard in
            behalf of Mustapha A’gha. He has acted as English Consul here for something like thirty
            years, and he really is the slave of the travellers. He gives them dinners, mounts them,
            and does all the disagreeable business of wrangling with the reis and dragomans for
            them, makes himself a postmaster, takes care of their letters and sends them out to the
            boats, and does all manner of services for them, and lends his house for the infidels to
            pray in on Sundays when a clergyman is here. For this he has no remuneration at all,
            except such presents as the English see fit to make him, and I have seen enough to know
            that they are neither large nor always gracefully given. The old fellow at <name type="place" ref="#kenneh">Keneh</name> who has nothing to do gets regular pay, and I
            think Mustapha ought to have something; he is now old and rather infirm, and has to keep
            a clerk to help him; and at least, his expenses should be covered. Please say this to
            Layard from me as my message to him. Don’t forget it, please, for Mustapha is a really
            kind friend to me at all times and in all ways. </p>
         <p> _February_ 14th.—Yesterday we had a dust-storm off the desert. It made my head heavy
            and made me feel languid, but did not affect my chest at all. To-day is a soft gray day;
            there was a little thunder this morning and a few, very few, drops of rain—hardly enough
            for even <name type="person" ref="#herodotus">Herodotus</name> to consider portentous.
            My donkey came down last night, and I tried him to-day, and he is very satisfactory
            though alarmingly small, as the real Egyptian donkey always is; the big ones are from
            the Hejaz. But it is wonderful how the little creatures run along under one as easy as
            possible, and they have no will of their own. I rode mine out to Karnac and back, and he
            did not seem to think me at all heavy. When they are overworked and overgalloped they
            become bad on the legs and easily fall, and all those for hire are quite stumped up,
            poor beasts—they are so willing and docile that everyone overdrives them.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>