<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Mrs. Austin. FESHN, Monday, November 30, 1862.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/3">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</name>
               <rs type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/361329">Al Fashn</rs>
               <date when="1862-11-30">30 November 1862</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/59830344">Sarah Austin</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Dearest <foreign xml:lang="de">
               <name type="person" ref="#sarah_austin">Mutter</name>
            </foreign>,</p>
         <p>I have now been enjoying this most delightful way of life for ten days, and am certainly
            much better. I begin to eat and sleep again, and cough less. My crew are a great
            amusement to me. They are mostly men from near the <name type="place" ref="#first_cataract">first Cataract</name> above <name type="place" ref="#assouan">Assouan</name>, sleek-skinned, gentle, patient, merry black fellows. The little
            black <name type="person" ref="#reis">Reis</name> is the very picture of good-nature and
            full of fun, ‘chaffing’ the girls as we pass the villages, and always smiling. The
            steersman is of lighter complexion, also very cheery, but decidedly pious. He prays five
            times a day and utters ejaculations to the apostle Rusool continually. He hurt his ankle
            on one leg and his instep on the other with a rusty nail, and they festered. I dressed
            them with poultices, and then with lint and strapping, with perfect success, to the
            great admiration of all hands, and he announced how much better he felt, ‘<foreign xml:lang="ar">Alhamdulillah, kieth-el-hairack khateer ya Sitti</foreign>’ (Praise be
            to God and thanks without end O Lady), and everyone echoed, ‘<foreign xml:lang="ar">kieth-el-hairack khateer</foreign>.’ The most important person is the ‘<foreign xml:lang="ar">weled</foreign>’—boy—<name type="person" ref="#achmet">Achmet</name>.
            The most merry, clever, omnipresent little rascal, with an ugly little pug face, a shape
            like an antique Cupid, liberally displayed, and a skin of dark brown velvet. His voice,
            shrill and clear, is always heard foremost; he cooks for the crew, he jumps overboard
            with the rope and gives advice on all occasions, grinds the coffee with the end of a
            stick in a mortar, which he holds between his feet, and uses the same large stick to
            walk proudly before me, brandishing it if I go ashore for a minute, and ordering
            everybody out of the way. ‘<foreign xml:lang="ar">Ya Achmet</foreign>!’ resounds all day
            whenever anybody wants anything, and the ‘<foreign xml:lang="ar">weled</foreign>’ is
            always ready and able. My favourite is <name type="person" ref="#osman">Osman</name>, a
            tall, long-limbed black who seems to have stepped out of a hieroglyphical drawing,
            shirt, skull-cap and all. He has only those two garments, and how anyone contrives to
            look so inconceivably ‘neat and respectable’ (as <name type="person" ref="#sally">Sally</name> truly remarked) in that costume is a mystery. He is always at work,
            always cheerful, but rather silent—in short, the able seaman and steady, respectable
            ‘hand’ <hi rendition="italic">
               <foreign xml:lang="fr">par excellence</foreign>
            </hi>. Then we have <name type="person" ref="#zankalonee">El Zankalonee</name> from near
               <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>, an old fellow of white complexion and a
            valuable person, an inexhaustible teller of stories at night and always <foreign xml:lang="fr">en train</foreign>, full of jokes and remarkable for a dry humour much
            relished by the crew. I wish I understood the stories, which sound delightful, all about
            Sultans and Efreets, with effective ‘points,’ at which all hands exclaim ‘<foreign xml:lang="ar">Mashallah</foreign>!’ or ‘Ah!’ (as long as you can drawl it). The
            jokes, perhaps, I may as well be ignorant of. There is a certain <name type="person" ref="#shereef">Shereef</name> who does nothing but laugh and work and be obliging;
            helps <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> with one hand and <name type="person" ref="#sally">Sally</name> with the other, and looks like a great innocent black
            child. The rest of the dozen are of various colours, sizes and ages, some quite old, but
            all very quiet and well-behaved. </p>
         <p>We have had either dead calm or contrary wind all the time and the men have worked very
            hard at the tow-rope. On <date>Friday</date> I proclaimed a halt in the afternoon at a
            village at prayer-time for the pious Muslims to go to the mosque; this gave great
            satisfaction, though only five went, <name type="person" ref="#reis">Reis</name>,
            steersman, <name type="person" ref="#zankalonee">Zankalonee</name> and two old men. The
            up-river men never pray at all, and <name type="person" ref="#osman">Osman</name>
            occupied himself by buying salt out of another boat and stowing it away to take up to
            his family, as it is terribly dear high up the river. At <name type="place" ref="#benisouef">Benisouef</name> we halted to buy meat and bread, it is <hi rendition="italic">
               <foreign xml:lang="fr">comme qui dirait</foreign>
            </hi> an assize town, there is one butcher who kills one sheep a day. I walked about the
            streets escorted by <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> in front and two sailors
            with huge staves behind, and created a sensation accordingly. It is a dull little
            country town with a wretched palace of <name type="person" ref="#said_pasha">Said
               Pasha</name>. On <date>Sunday</date> we halted at <name type="place" ref="#bibbeh">Bibbeh</name>, where I caught sight of a large Coptic church and sallied forth to
            see whether they would let me in. The road lay past the house of the headman of the
            village, and there ‘in the gate’ sat a patriarch, surrounded by his servants and his
            cattle. Over the gateway were crosses and queer constellations of dots, more like
            Mithraic symbols than anything Christian, but <name type="person" ref="#girgis">Girgis</name> was a Copt, though the chosen head of the Muslim village. He rose as I
            came up, stepped out and salaamed, then took my hand and said I must go into his house
            before I saw the church and enter the <foreign xml:lang="ar">hareem</foreign>. His old
            mother, who looked a hundred, and his pretty wife, were very friendly; but, as I had to
            leave <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> at the door, our talk soon came to an
            end, and <name type="person" ref="#girgis">Girgis</name> took me out into the divan,
            without the sacred precincts of the <foreign xml:lang="ar">hareem</foreign>. Of course
            we had pipes and coffee, and he pressed me to stay some days, to eat with him every day
            and to accept all his house contained. I took the milk he offered, and asked him to
            visit me in the boat, saying I must return before sunset when it gets cold, as I was
            ill. The house was a curious specimen of a wealthy man’s house—I could not describe it
            if I tried, but I felt I was acting a passage of the Old Testament. We went to the
            church, which outside looked like nine beehives in a box. Inside, the nine domes resting
            on square pillars were very handsome. <name type="person" ref="#girgis">Girgis</name>
            was putting it into thorough repair at his own expense, and it will cost a good deal, I
            think, to repair and renew the fine old wood panelling of such minute and intricate
            workmanship. The church is divided by three screens; one in front of the eastern three
            domes is impervious and conceals the holy of holies. He opened the horseshoe door for me
            to look in, but explained that no <foreign xml:lang="ar">Hareem</foreign> might cross
            the threshold. All was in confusion owing to the repairs which were actively going on
            without the slightest regard to <date>Sunday</date>; but he took up a large bundle,
            kissed it, and showed it me. What it contained I cannot guess, and I scrupled to inquire
            through a Muslim interpreter. To the right of this sanctum is the tomb of a Muslim
            saint! enclosed under the adjoining dome. Here we went in and <name type="person" ref="#girgis">Girgis</name> kissed the tomb on one side while <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> salaamed it on the other—a pleasant sight. They were much
            more particular about our shoes than in the mosques. <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> wanted to tie handkerchiefs over my boots like at <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>, but the priest objected and made me take them off and
            march about in the brick and mortar rubbish in my stockings. I wished to hear the
            service, but it was not till sunset, and, as far as I could make out, not different on
               <date>Sunday</date> to other days. The <foreign xml:lang="ar">Hareems</foreign> are
            behind the screen furthest removed from the holy screen, behind a third screen where
            also was the font, locked up and shaped like a Muslim tomb in little. (<foreign xml:lang="ar">Hareem</foreign> is used here just like the German <hi rendition="italic">
               <foreign xml:lang="de">Frauenzimmer</foreign>
            </hi>, to mean a respectable woman. <name type="person" ref="#girgis">Girgis</name>
            spoke of me to <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> as ‘<foreign xml:lang="ar">Hareem</foreign>.’) The Copts have but one wife, but they shut her up much closer
            than the Arabs. The children were sweetly pretty, so unlike the Arab brats, and the men
            very good-looking. They did not seem to acknowledge me at all as a <hi rendition="italic">
               <foreign xml:lang="fr">co-religionnaire</foreign>
            </hi>, and asked whether we of the English religion did not marry our brothers and
            sisters.</p>
         <p>The priest then asked me to drink coffee at his house close by, and there I ‘sat in the
               gate’—<hi rendition="italic">i.e.</hi>, in a large sort of den raised 2 feet from the
            ground and matted, to the left of the gate. A crowd of Copts collected and squatted
            about, and we were joined by the mason who was repairing the church, a fine, burly,
            rough-bearded old Mussulman, who told how the Sheykh buried in the church of <name type="place" ref="#bibbeh">Bibbeh</name> had appeared to him three nights running at
               <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name> and ordered him to leave his work and go
            to <name type="place" ref="#bibbeh">Bibbeh</name> and mend his church, and how he came
            and offered to do so without pay if the Copts would find the materials. He spoke with
            evident pride, as one who had received a Divine command, and the Copts all confirmed the
            story and everyone was highly gratified by the miracle. I asked <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> if he thought it was all true, and he had no doubt of it. The
            mason he knew to be a respectable man in full work, and <name type="person" ref="#girgis">Girgis</name> added that he had tried to get a man to come for years
            for the purpose without success. It is not often that a dead saint contrives to be
            equally agreeable to Christians and Mussulmans, and here was the staunch old ‘true
            believer’ working away in the sanctuary which they would not allow an English
            fellow-Christian to enter.</p>
         <p> Whilst we sat hearing all these wonders, the sheep and cattle pushed in between us,
            coming home at eve. The venerable old priest looked so like <name type="person" ref="#abraham">Father Abraham</name>, and the whole scene was <hi rendition="italic">so</hi> pastoral and Biblical that I felt quite as if my wish was fulfilled to live
            a little a few thousands of years ago. They wanted me to stay many days, and then <name type="person" ref="#girgis">Girgis</name> said I must stop at <name type="place" ref="#feshn">Feshn</name> where he had a fine house and garden, and he would go on
            horseback and meet me there, and would give me a whole troop of Fellaheen to pull the
            boat up quick. <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name>’s eyes twinkled with fun as
            he translated this, and said he knew the Sitt would cry out, as she always did about the
            Fellaheen, as if she were hurt herself. He told <name type="person" ref="#girgis">Girgis</name> that the English customs did not allow people to work without pay,
            which evidently seemed very absurd to the whole party.</p>
         <p>
            <name type="place" ref="#gebel_sheykh_embarak">GEBEL SHEYK EMBARAK</name>, <hi rendition="italic">
               <date>Thursday</date>
            </hi>.</p>
         <p> I stopped last night at <name type="place" ref="#feshn">Feshn</name>, but finding this
            morning that my Coptic friends were not expected till the afternoon, I would not spend
            the whole day, and came on still against wind and stream. If I could speak Arabic I
            should have enjoyed a few days with <name type="person" ref="#girgis">Girgis</name> and
            his family immensely, to learn their <hi rendition="italic">
               <foreign xml:lang="de">Ansichten</foreign>
            </hi> a little; but <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name>’s English is too
            imperfect to get beyond elementary subjects. The thing that strikes me most is the
            tolerant spirit that I see everywhere. They say ‘Ah! it is your custom,’ and express no
            sort of condemnation, and Muslims and Christians appear perfectly good friends, as my
            story of <name type="place" ref="#bibbeh">Bibbeh</name> goes to prove. I have yet to see
            the much-talked-of fanaticism, at present I have not met with a symptom of it. There
            were thirteen Copt families at <name type="place" ref="#bibbeh">Bibbeh</name> and a
            considerable Muslim population, who had elected <name type="person" ref="#girgis">Girgis</name> their headman and kissed his hand very heartily as our procession
            moved through the streets. <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> said he was a
            very good man and much liked.</p>
         <p>The villages look like slight elevations in the mud banks cut into square shapes. The
            best houses have neither paint, whitewash, plaster, bricks nor windows, nor any visible
            roofs. They don’t give one the notion of human dwellings at all at first, but soon the
            eye gets used to the absence of all that constitutes a house in Europe, the impression
            of wretchedness wears off, and one sees how picturesque they are, with palm-trees and
            tall pigeon-houses, and here and there the dome over a saint’s tomb. The men at work on
            the river-banks are exactly the same colour as the Nile mud, with just the warmer hue of
            the blood circulating beneath the skin. <name type="person" ref="#prometheus">Prometheus</name> has just formed them out of the universal material at hand, and
            the sun breathed life into them. Poor fellows—even the boatmen, ragged crew as they
            are—say ‘Ah, Fellaheen!’ with a contemptuous pity when they see me watch the villagers
            at work.</p>
         <p>The other day four huge barges passed us towed by a steamer and crammed with hundreds of
            the poor souls torn from their homes to work at the Isthmus of <name type="place" ref="#suez">Suez</name>, or some palace of the Pasha’s, for a nominal piastre a day,
            and find their own bread and water and cloak. One of my crew, <name type="person" ref="#andrasool">Andrasool</name>, a black savage whose function is always to jump
            overboard whenever the rope gets entangled or anything is wanted, recognised some
            relations of his from a village close to Assouan. There was much shouting and poor <name type="person" ref="#andrasool">Andrasool</name> looked very mournful all day. It may
            be his turn next. Some of the crew disloyally remarked that they were sure the men there
            wished they were working for a Sitti Ingleez, as <name type="person" ref="#andrasool">Andrasool</name> told them he was. Think too what splendid pay it must be that the
            boat-owner can give out of £25 a month to twelve men, after taking his own profits, the
            interest of money being enormous.</p>
         <p>When I call my crew black, don’t think of negroes. They are elegantly-shaped Arabs and
            all gentlemen in manners, and the black is transparent, with amber <hi rendition="italic">reflets</hi> under it in the sunshine; a negro looks <hi rendition="italic">blue</hi> beside them. I have learned a great deal that is curious
            from <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name>’s confidences, who tells me his family
            affairs and talks about the women of his family, which he would not to a man. He refused
            to speak to his brother, a very grand dragoman, who was with the Prince of Wales, and
            who came up to us in the hotel at <name type="place" ref="Cairo">Cairo</name> and
            addressed <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name>, who turned his back on him. I
            asked the reason, and <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> told me how his
            brother had a wife, ‘An old wife, been with him long time, very good wife.’ She had had
            three children—all dead. All at once the dragoman, who is much older than <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name>, declared he would divorce her and marry a
            young woman. Omar said, ‘No, don’t do that; keep her in your house as head of your home,
            and take one of your two black slave girls as your Hareem.’ But the other insisted, and
            married a young Turkish wife; whereupon <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> took
            his poor old sister-in-law to live with him and his own young wife, and cut his grand
            brother dead. See how characteristic!—the urging his brother to take the young slave
            girl ‘as his Hareem,’ like a respectable man—that would have been all right; but what he
            did was ‘not good.’ I’ll trouble you (as Mrs. Grote used to say) to settle these
            questions to everyone’s satisfaction. I own <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name>
            seemed to me to take a view against which I had nothing to say. His account of his other
            brother, a confectioner’s household with two wives, was very curious. He and they, with
            his wife and sister-in-law, all live together, and one of the brother’s wives has six
            children—three sleep with their own mother and three with their <hi rendition="italic">other</hi> mother—and all is quite harmonious.</p>
         <p><name type="place" ref="#siout">SIOUT</name>, <hi rendition="italic">December</hi>
            10.</p>
         <p>I could not send a letter from <name type="place" ref="#minieh">Minieh</name>, where we
            stopped, and I visited a sugar manufactory and a gentlemanly Turk, who superintended the
            district, the Moudir. I heard a boy singing a <hi rendition="italic">Zikr</hi> (the
            ninety-nine attributes of God) to a set of dervishes in a mosque, and I think I never
            heard anything more beautiful and affecting. Ordinary Arab singing is harsh and nasal,
            but it can be wonderfully moving. Since we left <name type="place" ref="#minieh">Minieh</name> we have suffered dreadfully from the cold; the chickens died of it,
            and the Arabs look blue and pinched. Of course it is <hi rendition="italic">my
               weather</hi> and there never was such cold and such incessant contrary winds known.
            To-day was better, and <name type="person" ref="#wassef">Wassef</name>, a Copt here,
            lent me his superb donkey to go up to the tomb in the mountain. The tomb is a mere
            cavern, so defaced, but the view of beautiful <name type="place" ref="#siout">Siout</name> standing in the midst of a loop of the Nile was ravishing. A green
            deeper and brighter than England, graceful minarets in crowds, a picturesque bridge,
            gardens, palm-trees, then the river beyond it, the barren yellow cliffs as a frame all
            around that. At our feet a woman was being carried to the grave, and the boys’ voices
            rang out the Koran full and clear as the long procession—first white turbans and then
            black veils and robes—wound along. It is all a dream to me. You can’t think what an odd
            effect it is to take up an English book and read it and then look up and hear the men
            cry, ‘Yah Mohammad.’ ‘Bless thee, Bottom, how art thou translated;’ it is the reverse of
            all one’s former life when one sat in England and read of the East. ‘<hi rendition="italic">Und nun sitz ich mitten drein</hi>’ in the real, true Arabian
            Nights, and don’t know whether ‘I be I as I suppose I be’ or not.</p>
         <p>Tell <name type="person" ref="#alick">Alick</name> the news, for I have not written to
            any but you. I do so long for my Rainie. The little Copt girls are like her, only pale;
            but they don’t let you admire them for fear of the evil-eye.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>