<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Mrs. Ross, LUXOR, April 7, 1864.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/37">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</name>
               <rs type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/360502">Luxor</rs>
               <date when="1864-04-07">7 April 1864</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person">Mrs. Ross</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST JANET, </p>
         <p> I have continued very fairly well. We had great heat ten days ago; now it is quite
            cool. Harvesting is going on, and never did I see in any dream so lovely a sight as the
            whole process. An acquaintance of mine, one Abdurachman, is Boaz, and as I sat with him
            on the threshing-floor and ate roasted corn, I felt quite puzzled as to whether I were
            really alive or only existing in imagination in the Book of Ruth. It is such a _kief_
            that one enjoys under the palm-trees, with such a scene. The harvest is magnificent
            here; I never saw such crops. There is no cattle disease, but a good deal of sickness
            among the people; I have to practise very extensively, and often feel very anxious, as I
            cannot refuse to go to the poor souls and give them medicine, with sore misgivings all
            the while. Fancy that <name type="person" ref="#hekekian_bey">Hekekian Bey</name> can’t
            get me an Arabic dictionary in <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>. I must send
            to London, I suppose, which seems hardly worth while. I wish you could see my teacher,
            Sheykh Yussuf. I never before saw a pious person amiable and good like him. He is
            intensely devout, and not at all bigoted—a difficult combination; and, moreover, he is
            lovely to behold, and has the prettiest and merriest laugh possible. It is quite curious
            to see the mixture of a sort of learning with utter ignorance and great superstition,
            and such perfect high-breeding and beauty of character. It is exactly like associating
            with St. John. </p>
         <p> I want dreadfully to be able to draw, or to photograph. The group at the
            Sheykh-el-Ababdeh’s last night was ravishing, all but my ugly hat and self. The black
            ringlets and dirty white drapery and obsolete weapons—the graceful splendid Sheykh
            ‘black but beautiful’ like the Shulamite—I thought of Antar and Abou Zeyd. </p>
         <p> Give my salaam to Mme. Tastu and ask her whether I may stay on here, or if I go down
            stream during the heat whether I may return next winter, in which case I might leave
            some of my goods. Hekekian strongly advises me to remain here, and thinks the heat will
            be good. I will try; 88° seemed to agree with me wonderfully, my cough is much
            better.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>