<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Mrs. Austin, CAIRO, October 21, 1864.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/45">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</name>
               <date when="1864-10-21">21 October 1864</date>
               <rs type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/360630">Cairo</rs>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/59830344">Sarah Austin</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Dearest <foreign xml:lang="de"><name type="person" ref="#sarah_austin">Mutter</name></foreign>, </p>
         <p> I got your letter yesterday. I hope <name type="person" ref="#alick">Alick</name> got
            mine of two weeks ago before leaving, and told you I was better. I am still rather weak,
            however I ride my donkey and the weather has suddenly become gloriously dry and cool. I
            rather shiver with the thermometer at 79°—absurd is it not, but I got so used to real
            heat. </p>
         <p> I never wrote about my leaving Luxor or my journey, for our voyage was quite
            tempestuous after the three first days and I fell ill as soon as I was in my house here.
            I hired the boat for six purses (£18) which had taken Greeks up to <name type="place" ref="#assouan">Assouan</name> selling groceries and strong drinks, but the reis would
            not bring back their cargo of black slaves to dirty the boat and picked us up at Luxor.
            We sailed at daybreak having waited all one day because it was an unlucky day. </p>
         <p> As I sat in the boat people kept coming to ask whether I was coming back very anxiously
            and bringing fresh bread, eggs and things as presents, and all the quality came to take
            leave and hope, _Inshallah_, I should soon ‘come home to my village safe and bring the
            Master, please God, to see them,’ and then to say the _Fattah_ for a safe journey and my
            health. In the morning the balconies of my house were filled with such a group to see us
            sail—a party of wild Abab’deh with their long Arab guns and flowing hair, a Turk
            elegantly dressed, Mohammed in his decorous brown robes and snow-white turban, and
            several fellaheen. As the boat moved off the Abab’deh blazed away with their guns and
               <name type="person" ref="#osman">Osman</name> Effendi with a sort of blunderbuss, and
            as we dropped down the river there was a general firing; even Todoros (Theodore), the
            Coptic Mallim, popped off his American revolver. <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> keeping up a return with <name type="person" ref="#alick">Alick</name>’s
            old horse pistols which are much admired here on account of the excessive noise they
            make. </p>
         <p> Poor old Ismain, who always thought I was Mme. Belzoni and wanted to take me up to Abou
            Simbel to meet my husband, was in dire distress that he could not go with me to <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>. He declared he was still _shedeed_ (strong
            enough to take care of me and to fight). He is ninety-seven and only remembers fifty or
            sixty years ago and old wild times—a splendid old man, handsome and erect. I used to
            give him coffee and listen to his old stories which had won his heart. His grandson, the
            quiet, rather stately, Mohammed who is guard of the house I lived in, forgot all his
            Muslim dignity, broke down in the middle of his set speech and flung himself down and
            kissed and hugged my knees and cried. He had got some notion of impending ill-luck, I
            found, and was unhappy at our departure—and the backsheesh failed to console him. Sheykh
            Yussuf was to come with me, but a brother of his just wrote word that he was coming back
            from the Hejaz where he had been with the troops in which he is serving his time; I was
            very sorry to lose his company. Fancy how dreadfully irregular for one of the Ulema and
            a heretical woman to travel together. What would our bishops say to a parson who did
            such a thing? We had a lovely time on the river for three days, such moonlight nights,
            so soft and lovely; and we had a sailor who was as good as a professional singer, and
            who sang religious songs, which I observe excite people here far more than love songs.
            One which began ‘Remove my sins from before thy sight Oh God’ was really beautiful and
            touching, and I did not wonder at the tears which ran down <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name>’s face. A very pretty profane song was ‘Keep the wind from me
            Oh Lord, I fear it will hurt me’ (_wind_ means _love_, which is like the Simoom) ‘Alas!
            it has struck me and I am sick. Why do ye bring the physician? Oh physician put back thy
            medicine in the canister, for only he who has hurt can cure me.’ The masculine pronoun
            is always used instead of _she_ in poetry out of decorum—sometimes even in conversation. </p>
         <p> _October_ 23.—Yesterday I met a Saedee—a friend of the brother of the Sheykh of the
            wild Abab’deh, and as we stood handshaking and kissing our fingers in the road, some of
            the Anglo-Indian travellers passed and gazed with fierce disgust; the handsome Hassan,
            being black, was such a flagrant case of a ‘native.’ <name type="person" ref="#sarah_austin">Mutter</name> dear, it is heart-breaking
            to see what we are sending to India now. The mail days are dreaded, we never know when
            some outrage may not excite ‘Mussulman fanaticism.’ The English tradesmen here complain
            as much as anyone, and I, who as the Kadee of Luxor said am ‘not outside the family’ (of
            Ishmael, I presume), hear what the Arabs really think. There are also crowds ‘like lice’
            as one Mohammed said, of low Italians, French, etc., and I find my stalwart Hassan’s
            broad shoulders no superfluous _porte-respect_ in the Frangee quarter. Three times I
            have been followed and insolently stared at (_à mon age_)!! and once Hassan had to
            speak. Fancy how dreadful to Muslims! I hate the sight of a hat here now. </p>
         <p> I can’t write more now my eyes are weak still. <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> begs me to give you his best salaam and say, _Inshallah_, he will take
            great care of your daughter, which he most zealously and tenderly does..</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>