<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Mrs. Austin, LUXOR, January 2, 1865.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/47">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</name>
               <date when="1865-01-02">2 January 1865</date>
               <rs type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/360502">Luxor</rs>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/59830344">Sarah Austin</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Dearest <foreign xml:lang="de"><name type="person" ref="#sarah_austin">Mutter</name></foreign>, </p>
         <p> I posted a letter for you at <name type="place" ref="#girgeh">Girgeh</name>, as we
            passed <name type="place" ref="#siout">Siout</name> with a good wind, I hope you will
            get it. My crew worked as I never saw men work, they were paid to get to Luxor, and for
            eighteen days they never rested or slept day or night, and all the time were merry and
            pleasant. It shows what power of endurance these ‘lazy Arabs’ have when there is good
            money at the end of a job, instead of the favourite panacea of ‘stick.’ </p>
         <p> We arrived at midnight and next morning my boat had the air of being pillaged. A crowd
            of laughing, chattering fellows ran off to the house laden with loose articles snatched
            up at random, loaves of sugar, pots and pans, books, cushions, all helter-skelter. I
            feared breakages, but all was housed safe and sound. The small boys of an age licensed
            to penetrate into the cabin, went off with the oddest cargoes of dressing things and the
            like—of backsheesh not one word. _Alhamdulillah salaameh_! ‘Thank God thou art in
            peace,’ and _Ya Sitt, Ya Emeereh_, till my head went round. Old Ismaeen fairly hugged me
            and little Achmet hung close to my side. I went up to Mustapha’s house while the
            unpacking took place and breakfasted there, and found letters from all of you, from you
            to darling Rainie, Sheykh Yussuf was charmed with her big writing and said he thought
            the news in that was the best of all. </p>
         <p> The weather was intensely hot the first two days. Now it is heavenly, a fresh breeze
            and gorgeous sunshine. I brought two common Arab lanterns for the tomb of Abu-l-Hajjaj
            and his _moolid_ is now going on. <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> took them
            and lighted them up and told me he found several people who called on the rest to say
            the _Fathah_ for me. I was sitting out yesterday with the people on the sand looking at
            the men doing _fantasia_ on horseback for the Sheykh, and a clever dragoman of the party
            was relating about the death of a young English girl whom he had served, and so _de fil
            en aiguille_ we talked about the strangers buried here and how the bishop had extorted
            £100. I said, ‘_Maleysh_ (never mind) the people have been hospitable to me alive and
            they will not cease if I die, but give me a tomb among the Arabs.’ One old man said,
            ‘May I not see thy day, oh Lady, and indeed thou shouldest be buried as a daughter of
            the Arabs, but we should fear the anger of thy Consul and thy family, but thou knowest
            that wherever thou art buried thou wilt assuredly lie in a Muslim grave.’ ‘How so?’ said
            I. ‘Why, when a bad Muslim dies the angels take him out of his tomb and put in one of
            the good from among the Christians in his place.’ This is the popular expression of the
            doctrine that the good are sure of salvation. <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> chimed in at once, ‘Certainly there is no doubt of it, and I know a
            story that happened in the days of Mahommed Ali Pasha which proves it.’ We demanded the
            story and <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> began. ‘There was once a very rich
            man of the Muslims so stingy that he grudged everybody even so much as a “bit of the
            paper inside the date” (Koran). When he was dying he said to his wife, “Go out and buy
            me a lump of pressed dates,” and when she had brought it he bade her leave him alone.
            Thereupon he took all his gold out of his sash and spread it before him, and rolled it
            up two or three pieces at a time in the dates, and swallowed it piece after piece until
            only three were left, when his wife came in and saw what he was doing and snatched them
            from his hand. Presently after he fell back and died and was carried out to the burial
            place and laid in his tomb. When the Kadee’s men came to put the seal on his property
            and found no money they said, “Oh woman, how is this? we know thy husband was a rich man
            and behold we find no money for his children and slaves or for thee.” So the woman told
            what had happened, and the Kadee sent for three other of the Ulema, and they decided
            that after three days she should go herself to her husband’s tomb and open it, and take
            the money from his stomach; meanwhile a guard was put over the tomb to keep away
            robbers. After three days therefore the woman went, and the men opened the tomb and
            said, “Go in O woman and take thy money.” So the woman went down into the tomb alone.
            When there, instead of her husband’s body she saw a box (coffin) of the boxes of the
            Christians, and when she opened it she saw the body of a young girl, adorned with many
            ornaments of gold necklaces, and bracelets, and a diamond _Kurs_ on her head, and over
            all a veil of black muslin embroidered with gold. So the woman said within herself,
            “Behold I came for money and here it is, I will take it and conceal this business for
            fear of the Kadee.” So she wrapped the whole in her _melayeh_ (a blue checked cotton
            sheet worn as a cloak) and came out, and the men said “Hast thou done thy business?”’
            and she answered “Yes” and returned home. </p>
         <p> ‘In a few days she gave the veil she had taken from the dead girl to a broker to sell
            for her in the <foreign xml:lang="ar">bazaar</foreign>, and the broker went and showed
            it to the people and was offered one hundred piastres. Now there sat in one of the shops
            of the merchants a great Ma-allim (Coptic clerk) belonging to the Pasha, and he saw the
            veil and said, “How much asketh thou?” and the broker said “Oh thine honour the clerk
            whatever thou wilt.” “Take from me then five hundred piastres and bring the person that
            gave thee the veil to receive the money.” So the broker fetched the woman and the Copt,
            who was a great man, called the police and said, “Take this woman and fetch my ass and
            we will go before the Pasha,” and he rode in haste to the palace weeping and beating his
            breast, and went before the Pasha and said, “Behold this veil was buried a few days ago
            with my daughter who died unmarried, and I had none but her and I loved her like my eyes
            and would not take from her her ornaments, and this veil she worked herself and was very
            fond of it, and she was young and beautiful and just of the age to be married; and
            behold the Muslims go and rob the tombs of the Christians and if thou wilt suffer this
            we Christians will leave Egypt and go and live in some other country, O Effendina, for
            we cannot endure this abomination.” </p>
         <p> ‘Then the Pasha turned to the woman and said, “Woe to thee O woman, art thou a Muslimeh
            and doest such wickedness?” And the woman spoke and told all that had happened and how
            she sought money and finding gold had kept it. So the Pasha said, “Wait oh Ma-allim, and
            we will discover the truth of this matter,” and he sent for the three Ulema who had
            desired that the tomb should be opened at the end of three days and told them the case;
            and they said, “Open now the tomb of the Christian damsel.” And the Pasha sent his men
            to do so, and when they opened it behold it was full of fire, and within it lay the body
            of the wicked and avaricious Mussulman.’ Thus it was manifest to all that on the night
            of terror the angels of God had done this thing, and had laid the innocent girl of the
            Christians among those who have received direction, and the evil Muslim among the
            rejected. Admire how rapidly legends arise here. This story which everybody declared was
            quite true is placed no longer ago than in Mahommed Ali Pasha’s time. </p>
         <p> There are hardly any travellers this year, instead of a hundred and fifty or more
            boats, perhaps twenty. A son of one of the Rothschilds, a boy of fourteen, has just gone
            up like a royal prince in one of the Pasha’s steamers—all his expenses paid and crowds
            of attendants. ‘All that honour to the money of the Jew,’ said an old fellah to me with
            a tone of scorn which I could not but echo in my heart. He has turned out his dragoman—a
            respectable elderly man, very sick, and paid him his bare wages and the munificent sum
            of £5 to take him back to <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>. On board there
            was a doctor and plenty of servants, and yet he abandons the man here on Mustapha’s
            hands. I have brought Er-Rasheedee here (the sick man) as poor Mustapha is already
            overloaded with strangers. I am sorry the name of _Yahoodee_ (Jew) should be made to
            stink yet more in the nostrils of the Arabs. I am very well, indeed my cough is almost
            gone and I can walk quite briskly and enjoy it. I think, dear <name type="person" ref="#sarah_austin">Mutter</name>, I am really
            better. I never felt the cold so little as this winter since my illness, the chilly
            mornings and nights don’t seem to signify at all now, and the climate feels more
            delicious than ever. </p>
         <p> Mr. Herbert, the painter, went back to <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>
            from Farshoot below <name type="place" ref="#kenneh">Keneh</name>; so I have no
            ‘Frangee’ society at all. But Sheykh Yussuf and the Kadee drop in to tea very often and
            as they are agreeable men I am quite content with my company. </p>
         <p> Bye the bye I will tell you about the tenure of land in Egypt which people are always
            disputing about, as the Kadee laid it down for me. The _whole_ land belongs to the
            Sultan of Turkey, the Pasha being his vakeel (representative), nominally of course as we
            know. Thus there are no owners, only tenants paying from one hundred piastres tariff
            (£1) down to thirty piastres yearly per feddan (about an acre) according to the quality
            of the land, or the favour of the Pasha when granting it. This tenancy is hereditary to
            children only—not to collaterals or ascendants—and it may be sold, but in that case
            application must be made to the Government. If the owner or tenant dies childless the
            land reverts to the Sultan, _i.e._ to the Pasha, and _if the Pasha chooses to have any
            man’s land he can take it from him on payment—or without_. Don’t let any one tell you
            that I exaggerate; I have known it happen: I mean the _without_, and the man received
            feddan for feddan of desert, in return for his good land which he had tilled and
            watered. </p>
         <p> To-morrow night is the great night of Sheykh Abu-l-Hajjaj’s _moolid_ and I am desired
            to go to the mosque for the benefit of my health, and that my friends may say a prayer
            for my children. The kind hearty welcome I found here has been a real pleasure, and
            every one was pleased because I was glad to come home to my _beled_ (town), and they all
            thought it so nice of ‘my master’ to have come so far to see me because I was sick—all
            but one Turk, who clearly looked with pitying contempt on so much trouble taken about a
            sick old woman. </p>
         <p> I have left my letter for a long while. You will not wonder—for after some ten days’
            fever, my poor guest Mohammed Er-Rasheedee died to-day. Two Prussian doctors gave me
            help for the last four days, but left last night. He sank to sleep quietly at noon with
            his hand in mine, a good old Muslim sat at his head on one side and I on the other.
               <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> stood at his head and his black boy Khayr
            at his feet. We had laid his face to the Kibleh and I spoke to him to see if he knew
            anything and when he nodded the three Muslims chanted the _Islamee La Illáhá_, etc.,
            etc., while I closed his eyes. The ‘respectable men’ came in by degrees, took an
            inventory of his property which they delivered to me, and washed the body, and within an
            hour and a half we all went out to the burial place; I following among a troop of women
            who joined us to wail for ‘the brother who had died far from his place.’ The scene as we
            turned in between the broken colossi and the pylons of the temple to go to the mosque
            was over-powering. After the prayer in the mosque we went out to the graveyard, Muslims
            and Copts helping to carry the dead, and my Frankish hat in the midst of the veiled and
            wailing women; all so familiar and yet so strange. After the burial the Imám, Sheykh
            Abd-el-Waris, came and kissed me on the shoulders and the Shereef, a man of eighty, laid
            his hands on my shoulders and said, ‘Fear not my daughter, neither all the days of thy
            life nor at the hour of thy death, for God is with thee.’ I kissed the old man’s hand
            and turned to go, but numberless men came and said ‘A thousand thanks, O our sister, for
            what thou hast done for one among us,’ and a great deal more. Now the solemn chanting of
            the _Fikees_, and the clear voice of the boy reciting the Koran in the room where the
            man died are ringing through the house. They will pass the night in prayer, and
            to-morrow there will be the prayer of deliverance in the mosque. Poor Khayr has just
            crept in to have a quiet cry—poor boy. He is in the inventory and to-morrow I must
            deliver him up to _les autorités_ to be forwarded to <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name> with the rest of the property. He is very ugly with his black face wet
            and swollen, but he kisses my hand and calls me his mother quite ‘natural like’—you see
            colour is no barrier here. </p>
         <p> The weather is glorious this year, and in spite of some fatigue I am extremely well and
            strong, and have hardly any cough at all. I am so sorry that the young Rothschild was so
            hard to Er-Rasheedee and that his French doctor refused to come and see him. It makes
            bad blood naturally. However, the German doctors were most kind and helpful. </p>
         <p> The festival of Abu-l-Hajjaj was quite a fine sight, not splendid at all—_au
            contraire_—but spirit-stirring; the flags of the Sheykh borne by his family chanting,
            and the men tearing about in mimic fight on horseback with their spears. My acquaintance
            of last year, Abd-el-Moutovil, the fanatical Sheykh from Tunis was there. At first he
            scowled at me. Then someone told him how Rothschild had left Er-Rasheedee, and he held
            forth about the hatred of all the unbelievers to the Muslims, and ended by asking where
            the sick man was. A quaint little smile twinkled in Sheykh Yussuf’s soft eyes and he
            curled his silky moustache as he said demurely, ‘Your Honour must go and visit him at
            the house of the English Lady.’ I am bound to say that the Pharisee ‘executed himself
            handsomely, for in a few minutes he came up to me and took my hand and even hoped I
            would visit the tomb of Abu-l-Hajjaj with him!! </p>
         <p> Since I wrote last I have been rather poorly—more cough, and most wearing
            sleeplessness. A poor young Englishman died here at the house of the Austrian Consular
            agent. I was too ill to go to him, but a kind, dear young Englishwoman, a Mrs. Walker,
            who was here with her family in a boat, sat up with him three nights and nursed him like
            a sister. A young American lay sick at the same time in the house, he is now gone down
            to <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>, but I doubt whether he will reach it
            alive. The Englishman was buried on the first day of Ramadan where they bury strangers,
            on the site of a former Coptic church. Archdeacon Moore read the service; <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> and I spread my old flag over the bier, and
            Copts and Muslims helped to carry the poor stranger. It was a most impressive sight. The
            party of Europeans, all strangers to the dead but all deeply moved; the group of
            black-robed and turbaned Copts; the sailors from the boats; the gaily dressed dragomans;
            several brown-shirted fellaheen and the thick crowd of children—all the little Abab’deh
            stark naked and all behaving so well, the expression on their little faces touched me
            most of all. As Muslims, <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> and the boatmen
            laid him down in the grave, and while the English prayer was read the sun went down in a
            glorious flood of light over the distant bend of the Nile. ‘Had he a mother, he was
            young?’ said an Abab’deh woman to me with tears in her eyes and pressing my hand in
            sympathy for that far-off mother of such a different race. </p>
         <p> Passenger steamboats come now every fortnight, but I have had no letter for a month. I
            have no almanack and have lost count of European time—to-day is the 3 of Ramadan, that
            is all I know. The poor black slave was sent back from <name type="place" ref="#kenneh">Keneh</name>, God knows why—because he had no money and the Moudir could not ‘eat
            off him’ as he could off the money and property—he believes. He is a capital fellow, and
            in order to compensate me for what he eats he proposed to wash for me, and you would be
            amused to see Khayr with his coal-black face and filed teeth doing laundry-maid out in
            the yard. He fears the family will sell him and hopes he may fetch a good price for ‘his
            boy’—only on the other hand he would so like me to buy him—and so his mind is disturbed.
            Meanwhile the having all my clothes washed clean is a great luxury. </p>
         <p> The steamer is come and I must finish in haste. I have corrected the proofs. There is
            not much to alter, and though I regret several lost letters I can’t replace them. I
            tried, but it felt like a forgery. Do you cut out and correct, dearest <name type="person" ref="#sarah_austin">Mutter</name>, you will
            do it much better than I.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>