<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, LUXOR, February 7, 1867.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/51">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</name>
               <rs type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/360502">Luxor</rs>
               <date when="1865-02-07">7 February 1865</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff
                  Gordon</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Dearest <name type="person" ref="#alick">Alick</name>, </p>
         <p> I am enjoying a ‘great indulgence of talk’ with M. Prévost Paradol as heartily as any
            nigger. He is a delightful person. This evening he is coming with Arakel Bey, his
            Armenian companion, and I will invite a few Arabs to show him. I sent off the proofs
            yesterday per passenger steamer. I trust they will arrive safe. It is too disheartening
            about letters, so many are lost. I am dreadfully disappointed in my letters, I _really_
            don’t think them good—you know I don’t _blaguer_ about my own performances. I am very
            glad people like my Cape letters which I forget—but honestly I don’t think the Egyptian
            good. You know I don’t ‘pretend’ if I think I have done something well and I was
            generally content with my translations, but I feel these all to be poor and what <name type="person" ref="#maurice">Maurice</name> calls ‘dry’ when I know how curious and
            interesting and poetical the country really is. </p>
         <p> I paid Fadil Pasha a visit on his boat, and it was just like the middle ages. In order
            to amuse me he called up a horrid little black boy of about four to do tricks like a
            dancing dog, which ended in a performance of the Mussulman prayer. The little beast was
            dressed in a Stamboulee dress of scarlet cloth. </p>
         <p> All the Arab doctors come to see me now as they go up and down the river to give me
            help if I want it. Some are very pleasant men. Mourad Effendi speaks German exactly like
            a German. The old Sheykh-el-Beled of Erment who visits me whenever he comes here, and
            has the sweetest voice I ever heard, complained of the climate of <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>. ‘There is no sun there at all, it is no brighter or warmer
            than the moon.’ What do you think our sun must be now you know <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>. We have had a glorious winter, like the finest summer
            weather at home only so much finer. </p>
         <p>
            <name type="person" ref="#janet">Janet</name> wishes to go with me if I go to Soden, I
            must make enquiries about the climate. <name type="person" ref="#ross">Ross</name> fears
            it is too cold for an Egyptian like me. I should enjoy to have all the family _au grand
            complet_. I will leave Luxor in May and get to you towards the latter part of June, if
            that pleases you, _Inshallah_! </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>