<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Mrs. Austin, LUXOR, March 13, 1865.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/53">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</name>
               <date when="1865-03-13">13 March 1865</date>
               <rs type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/360502">Luxor</rs>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/59830344">Sarah Austin</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Dearest <foreign xml:lang="de"><name type="person" ref="#sarah_austin">Mutter</name></foreign>, </p>
         <p> I hope your mind has not been disturbed by any rumours of ‘battle, murder and sudden
            death’ up in our part of the world. A week ago we heard that a Prussian boat had been
            attacked, all on board murdered, and the boat burned; then that ten villages were in
            open revolt, and that Effendina (the Viceroy) himself had come up and ‘taken a broom and
            swept them clean’ _i.e._—exterminated the inhabitants. The truth now appears to be that
            a crazy darweesh has made a disturbance—but I will tell it as I heard it. He did as his
            father likewise did thirty years ago, made himself _Ism_ (name) by repeating one of the
            appellations of God, like _Ya Latif_ three thousand times every night for three years
            which rendered him invulnerable. He then made friends with a Jinn who taught him many
            more tricks—among others, that practised in England by the Davenports of slipping out of
            any bonds. He then deluded the people of the desert by giving himself out as _El-Mahdi_
            (he who is to come with the Lord Jesus and to slay Antichrist at the end of the world),
            and proclaimed a revolt against the Turks. Three villages below <name type="place" ref="#kenneh">Keneh</name>—Gau, Rayanaeh and Bedeh took part in the disturbance, and
            Fodl Pasha came up with steamboats, burnt the villages, shot about one hundred men and
            devastated the fields. At first we heard one thousand were shot, now it is one hundred.
            The women and children will be distributed among other villages. The darweesh some say
            is killed, others that he is gone off into the desert with a body of bedaween and a few
            of the fellaheen from the three ravaged villages. Gau is a large place—as large, I think
            as Luxor. The darweesh is a native of Salamieh, a village close by here, and yesterday
            his brother, a very quiet man, and his father’s father-in-law old Hajjee Sultan were
            carried off prisoners to <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>, or <name type="place" ref="#kenneh">Keneh</name>, we don’t know which. It seems that the boat
            robbed belonged to Greek traders, but no one was hurt, I believe, and no European boat
            has been molested. </p>
         <p> Baron Kevenbrinck was here yesterday with his wife, and they saw all the sacking of the
            villages and said no resistance was offered by the people whom the soldiers shot down as
            they ran, and they saw the sheep etc. being driven off by the soldiers. You need be in
            no alarm about me. The darweesh and his followers could not pounce on us as we are eight
            good miles from the desert, _i.e._ the mountain, so we must have timely notice, and we
            have arranged that if they appear in the neighbourhood the women and children of the
            outlying huts should come into my house which is a regular fortress, and also any
            travellers in boats, and we muster little short of seven hundred men able to fight
            including Karnac, moreover Fodl Pasha and the troops are at <name type="place" ref="#kenneh">Keneh</name> only forty miles off. </p>
         <p> Three English boats went down river to-day and one came up. The Kevenbrincks went up
            last night. I dined with them, she is very lively and pleasant. I nearly died of
            laughing to-day when little Achmet came for his lesson. He pronounced that he was sick
            of love for her. He played at cards with her yesterday afternoon and it seems lost his
            heart (he is twelve and quite a boyish boy, though a very clever one) and he said he was
            wishing to play a game for a kiss as the stake. He had put on a turban to-day, on the
            strength of his passion, to look like a man, and had neglected his dress otherwise
            because ‘when young men are sick of love they always do so.’ The fact is the Baroness
            was kind and amiable and tried to amuse him as she would have done to a white boy, hence
            Achmet’s susceptible heart was ‘on fire for her.’ He also asked me if I had any medicine
            to make him white, I suppose to look lovely in her eyes. He little knows how very pretty
            he is with his brown face—as he sits cross-legged on the carpet at my feet in his white
            turban and blue shirt reading aloud—he was quite a picture. I have grown very fond of
            the little fellow, he is so eager to learn and to improve and so remarkably clever. </p>
         <p> My little Achmet, who is donkey-boy and general little slave, the smallest slenderest
            quietest little creature, has implored me to take him with me to England. I wish Rainie
            could see him, she would be so ‘arprized’ at his dark brown little face, so _fein_, and
            with eyes like a dormouse. He is a true little Arab—can run all day in the heat, sleeps
            on the stones and eats anything—quick, gentle and noiseless and fiercely jealous. If I
            speak to any other boy he rushes at him and drives him away, and while black Khayr was
            in the house, he suffered martyrdom and the kitchen was a scene of incessant wrangle
            about the coffee. Khayr would bring me my coffee and Achmet resented the usurpation of
            his functions—of course quite hopelessly, as Khayr was a great stout black of eighteen
            and poor little Achmet not bigger than Rainie. I am really tempted to adopt the vigilant
            active little creature. </p>
         <p> _March_ 15.—Sheykh Yussuf returned from a visit to Salamieh last night. He tells me the
            darweesh Achmet et-Tayib is not dead, he believes that he is a mad fanatic and a
            communist. He wants to divide all property equally and to kill all the Ulema and destroy
            all theological teaching by learned men and to preach a sort of revelation or
            interpretation of the Koran of his own. ‘He would break up your pretty clock,’ said
            Yussuf, ‘and give every man a broken wheel out of it, and so with all things.’ </p>
         <p> One of the dragomans here had been urging me to go down but Yussuf laughed at any idea
            of danger, he says the people here have fought the bedaween before and will not be
            attacked by such a handful as are out in the mountain now; _du reste_ the
            Abu-l-Hajjajieh (family of Abu-l-Hajjaj) will ‘put their seal’ to it that I am their
            sister and answer for me with a man’s life. It would be foolish to go down into whatever
            disturbance there may be alone in a small country boat and where I am not known. The
            Pasha himself we hear is at <name type="place" ref="#girgeh">Girgeh</name> with
            steamboats and soldiers, and if the slightest fear should arise steamers will be sent up
            to fetch all the Europeans. What I grieve over is the poor villagers whose little
            property is all confiscated, guilty and innocent alike, and many shot as they ran away.
            Hajjee Ali tells me privately that he believes the discontent against the Government is
            very deep and universal and that there will be an outbreak—but not yet. The Pasha’s
            attempt to regulate the price of food by edicts has been very disastrous, and of course
            the present famine prices are laid to his charge—if a man will be omnipotent he must
            take the consequences when he fails. I don’t believe in an outbreak—I think the people
            are too thoroughly accustomed to suffer and to obey, besides they have no means of
            communication, and the steamboats can run up and down and destroy them _en détail_ in a
            country which is eight hundred miles long by from one to eight wide, and thinly peopled.
            Only <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name> could do anything, and everything is
            done to please the Cairenes at the expense of the fellaheen. </p>
         <p> The great heat has begun these last three days. My cough is better and I am grown
            fatter again. The Nile is so low that I fancy that six weeks or two months hence I shall
            have to go down in two little boats—even now the dahabiehs keep sticking fast
            continually. I have promised some neighbours to bring back a little seed corn for them,
            some of the best English wheat without beard. All the wheat here is bearded and they
            have an ambition for some of ours. I long to bring them wheelbarrows and spades and
            pickaxes. The great folks get steamploughs, but the labourers work with their bare hands
            and a rush basket _pour tout potage_, and it takes six to do the work of one who has got
            good tools.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>