<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Mrs. Austin, A FEW MILES BELOW GIRGEH, March 7, 1863.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/6">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</name>
               <rs type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/355026">Girga</rs>
               <date when="1863-03-07">7 March 1863</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/59830344">Sarah Austin</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Dearest <foreign xml:lang="de"><name type="person" ref="#sarah_austin">Mutter</name></foreign>,</p>

         <p>I was so glad to find from your letter (which Janet sent me to <name type="place" ref="#thebes">Thebes</name> by a steamer) that mine from <name type="place" ref="#siout">Siout</name> had reached you safely. First and foremost I am wonderfully
            better. In <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name> the winter has been terribly
            cold and damp, as the Coptic priest told me yesterday at <name type="place" ref="#girgeh">Girgeh</name>. So I don’t repent the expense of the boat for <hi rendition="italic"><foreign xml:lang="fr">j’en ai pour mon argent</foreign></hi>—I am
               <hi rendition="italic">all</hi> the money better and really think of getting well.
            Now that I know the ways of this country a little, which <name type="person" ref="#herodotus">Herodotus</name> truly says is like no other, I see that I might
            have gone and lived at <name type="place" ref="#thebes">Thebes</name> or at <name type="place" ref="#kenneh">Keneh</name> or <name type="place" ref="#assouan">Assouan</name> on next to nothing, but then how could I know it? The English have
            raised a mirage of false wants and extravagance which the servants of the country of
            course, some from interest and others from mere ignorance, do their best to keep up. As
            soon as I had succeeded in really persuading <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name>
            that I was not as rich as a Pasha and had no wish to be thought so, he immediately
            turned over a new leaf as to what must be had and said ‘Oh, if I could have thought an
            English lady would have eaten and lived and done the least like Arab people, I might
            have hired a house at <name type="place" ref="#kenneh">Keneh</name> for you, and we
            might have gone up in a clean passenger boat, but I thought no English could bear it.’
            At <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>, where we shall be, <foreign xml:lang="ar">Inshallaha</foreign>, on the <date>19th</date>, <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> will get a lodging and borrow a few mattresses and a table
            and chair and, as he says, ‘keep the money in our pockets instead of giving it to the
            hotel.’ I hope <name type="person" ref="#alick">Alick</name> got my letter from <name type="place" ref="#thebes">Thebes</name>, and that he told you that I had dined with
            ‘the blameless Ethiopians.’ I have seen all the temples in <name type="place" ref="#nubia">Nubia</name> and down as far as I have come, and nine of the tombs at
               <name type="place" ref="#thebes">Thebes</name>. Some are wonderfully beautiful—<name type="place" ref="#abou_simbel">Abou Simbel</name>, <name type="place" ref="#kalabshee">Kalabshee</name>, <name type="place" ref="#koum_ombo">Koom
               Ombo</name>—a little temple at <name type="place" ref="#el_kab">El Kab</name>,
            lovely—three tombs at <name type="place" ref="#thebes">Thebes</name> and most of all
               <name type="place" ref="#abydos">Abydos</name>; <name type="place" ref="#edfou">Edfou</name> and <name type="place" ref="#dendera">Dendera</name> are the most
            perfect, <name type="place" ref="#edfou">Edfou</name> quite perfect, but far less
            beautiful. But the most lovely object my eyes ever saw is the island of <name type="place" ref="#philae">Philæ</name>. It gives one quite the supernatural feeling
            of <name type="person" ref="#claude">Claude</name>’s best landscapes, only not the least
            like them—<hi rendition="italic"><foreign xml:lang="de">ganz anders</foreign></hi>. The
            Arabs say that <name type="person" ref="#ans_el_wogood">Ans el Wogood</name>, the most
            beautiful of men, built it for his most beautiful beloved, and there they lived in
            perfect beauty and happiness all alone. If the weather had not been so cold while I was
            there I should have lived in the temple, in a chamber sculptured with the mystery of
               <name type="person" ref="#osiris">Osiris</name>’ burial and resurrection. <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> cleaned it out and meant to move my things
            there for a few days, but it was too cold to sleep in a room without a door. The winds
            have been extraordinarily cold this year, and are so still. We have had very little of
            the fine warm weather, and really been pinched with cold most of the time. On the shore
            away from the river would be much better for invalids.</p>

         <p><name type="person" ref="mustapha_aga">Mustapha Aga</name>, the consular agent at <name type="place" ref="#thebes">Thebes</name>, has offered me a house of his, up among the
            tombs in the finest air, if ever I want it. He was very kind and hospitable indeed to
            all the English there. I went into his <foreign xml:lang="ar">hareem</foreign>, and
            liked his wife’s manners very much. It was charming to see that she henpecked her
            handsome old husband completely. They had fine children and his boy, about thirteen or
            so, rode and played Jereed one day when <name type="person" ref="#abdallah_pasha">Abdallah Pasha</name> had ordered the people of the neighbourhood to do it for
            General <name type="person" ref="#parker">Parker</name>. I never saw so beautiful a
            performance. The old General and I were quite excited, and he tried it to the great
            amusement of the Sheykh el Beled. Some young Englishmen were rather grand about it, but
            declined mounting the horses and trying a throw. The Sheykh and young Hassan and then
            old Mustapha wheeled round and round like beautiful hawks, and caught the palm-sticks
            thrown at them as they dashed round. It was superb, and the horses were good, though the
            saddles and bridles were rags and ends of rope, and the men mere tatterdemalions. A
            little below <name type="place" ref="#thebes">Thebes</name> I stopped, and walked inland
            to <name type="place" ref="#koos">Koos</name> to see a noble old mosque falling to ruin.
            No English had ever been there and we were surrounded by a crowd in the <foreign xml:lang="ar">bazaar</foreign>. Instantly five or six tall fellows with long sticks
            improvised themselves our body-guard and kept the people off, who <hi rendition="italic"><foreign xml:lang="fr">du reste</foreign></hi> were perfectly civil and only
            curious to see such strange ‘<foreign xml:lang="ar">Hareem</foreign>,’ and after seeing
            us well out of the town evaporated as quietly as they came without a word. I gave about
            ten-pence to buy oil, as it is Ramadan and the mosque ought to be lighted, and the old
            servant of the mosque kindly promised me full justice at the Day of Judgment, as I was
            one of those Nasranee of whom the Lord <name type="person" ref="#mohammed">Mohammed</name> said that they are not proud and wish well to the Muslimeen. The
            Pasha had confiscated all the lands belonging to the mosque, and allowed 300
            piastres—not £2 a month—for all expenses; of course the noble old building with its
            beautiful carving and arabesque mouldings must fall down. There was a smaller one beside
            it, where he declared that anciently forty girls lived unmarried and recited the
            Koran—Muslim nuns, in fact. I intend to ask the Alim, for whom I have a letter from
            Mustapha, about such an anomaly.</p>

         <p>Some way above <name type="place" ref="#bellianeh">Bellianeh</name>
            <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> asked eagerly leave to stop the boat as a
            great Sheyk had called to us, and we should inevitably have some disaster if we
            disobeyed. So we stopped and <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> said, ‘come and
            see the Sheyk, ma’am.’ I walked off and presently found about thirty people, including
            all my own men, sitting on the ground round St. Simon Stylites—without the column. A
            hideous old man like <name type="person" ref="#polyphemus">Polyphemus</name>, utterly
            naked, with the skin of a rhinoceros all cracked with the weather, sat there, and had
            sat day and night, summer and winter, motionless for twenty years. He never prays, he
            never washes, he does not keep Ramadan, and yet he is a saint. Of course I expected a
            good hearty curse from such a man, but he was delighted with my visit, asked me to sit
            down, ordered his servant to bring me sugar-cane, asked my name and tried to repeat it
            over and over again, and was quite talkative and full of jokes and compliments, and took
            no notice of anyone else. <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> and my crew smiled
            and nodded, and all congratulated me heartily. Such a distinction proves my own
            excellence (as the Sheyk knows all people’s thoughts), and is sure to be followed by
            good fortune. Finally <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> proposed to say the
               <foreign xml:lang="ar">Fathah</foreign> in which all joined except the Sheykh, who looked rather
            bored by the interruption, and desired us not to go so soon, unless I were in a hurry. A
            party of Bedaween came up on camels with presents for the holy man, but he took no
            notice of them, and went on questioning <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name>
            about me, and answering my questions. What struck me was the total absence of any
            sanctimonious air about the old fellow, he was quite worldly and jocose; I suppose he
            knew that his position was secure, and thought his dirt and nakedness proved his
            holiness enough. <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> then recited the Fathah
            again, and we rose and gave the servants a few foddahs—the saint takes no notice of this
            part of the proceeding—but he asked me to send him twice my hand full of rice for his
            dinner, an honour so great that there was a murmur of congratulation through the whole
            assembly. I asked <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> how a man could be a saint
            who neglected all the duties of a Muslim, and I found that he fully believed that Sheykh
            Seleem could be in two places at once, that while he sits there on the shore he is also
            at <name type="place" ref="#mecca">Mecca</name>, performing every sacred function and
            dressed all in green. ‘Many people have seen him there, ma’am, quite true.’</p>

         <p>From <name type="place" ref="#bellianeh">Bellianeh</name> we rode on pack-donkeys
            without bridles to <name type="place" ref="#abydos">Abydos</name>, six miles through the
            most beautiful crops ever seen. The absence of weeds and blight is wonderful, and the
            green of Egypt, where it is green, would make English green look black. Beautiful
            cattle, sheep and camels were eating the delicious clover, while their owners camped
            there in reed huts during the time the crops are growing. Such a lovely scene, all
            sweetness and plenty. We ate our bread and dates in <name type="person" ref="#osiris">Osiris</name>’ temple, and a woman offered us buffalo milk on our way home, which we
            drank warm out of the huge earthen pan it had been milked in. At <name type="place" ref="#girgeh">Girgeh</name> I found my former friend <name type="person" ref="#mishregi">Mishregi</name> absent, but his servants told some of his friends of
            my arrival, and about seven or eight big black turbans soon gathered in the boat. A
            darling little Coptic boy came with his father and wanted a ‘<hi rendition="italic"><foreign xml:lang="ar">kitaab</foreign></hi>’ (book) to write in, so I made one
            with paper and the cover of my old pocket-book, and gave him a pencil. I also bethought
            me of showing him ‘pickys’ in a book, which was so glorious a novelty that he wanted to
            go with me to my town, ‘Beled Ingleez,’ where more such books were to be found.</p>

         <p><name type="place" ref="#siout">Siout</name>, <date><hi rendition="italic">March</hi>
               9</date>.</p>

         <p>I found here letters from <name type="person" ref="#alick">Alick</name>, telling me of
            dear <name type="person" ref="#lord_lansdowne">Lord Lansdowne</name>’s death. Of course
            I know that his time was come, but the thought that I shall never see his face again,
            that all that kindness and affection is gone out of my life, is a great blow. No friend
            could leave such a blank to me as that old and faithful one, though the death of younger
            ones might be more tragic; but so many things seem gone with him into the grave. Many
            indeed will mourn that kind, wise, steadfast man—<hi rendition="italic"><foreign xml:lang="lat">Antiqua fides</foreign></hi>. No one nowadays will be so noble with
            such unconsciousness and simplicity. I have bought two Coptic turbans to make a black
            dress out of. I thought I should like to wear it for him—here, where ‘compliment’ is out
            of the question.</p>

         <p>I also found a letter from <name type="person" ref="#janet">Janet</name>, who has been
            very ill; the account was so bad that I have telegraphed to hear how she is, and shall
            go at once to <name type="place" ref="#alexandria">Alexandria</name> if she is not
            better. If she is I shall hold to my plan and see <name type="place" ref="#beni_hassan">Beni Hassan</name> and the Pyramids on my way to <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>. I found my kind friend the Copt <name type="person" ref="#wassef">Wassef</name> kinder than ever. He went off to telegraph to <name type="place" ref="#alexandria">Alexandria</name> for me, and showed so much feeling and real
            kindness that I was quite touched.</p>

         <p>I was grieved to hear that you had been ill again, dearest <name type="person" ref="#sarah_austin">Mutter</name>. The best is that I
            feel so much better that I think I may come home again without fear; I still have an
            irritable cough, but it has begun to have lucid intervals, and is far less frequent. I
            can walk four or five miles and my appetite is good. All this in spite of really cold
            weather in a boat where nothing shuts within two fingers’ breadths. I long to be again
            with my own people.</p>

         <p>Please send this to <name type="person" ref="#alick">Alick</name>, to whom I will write
            again from <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>