<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, NILE BOAT, URANIA, May, 1865.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/60">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</name>
               <date when="1865-05">May 1865</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff
                  Gordon</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Happy as I was in the prospect of seeing you all and miserable as poor Upper Egypt has
            become, I could not leave without a pang. Our Bairam was not gay. There was horse riding
            for Sheykh Gibreel (the cousin of Abu’l Haggag) and the scene was prettier than ever I
            saw. My old friend Yunis the Shereef insisted on showing me that at eighty-five he could
            still handle a horse and throw a Gereed ‘for Sheykh Gibreel and the Lady’ as he said.
            Then arrived the Mufettish of Zenia with his gay attendants and filled the little square
            in front of the Cadi’s castellated house where we were sitting. The young Sheykh of
            Salamieh rode beautifully and there was some excellent Neboot play (sort of very severe
            quarterstaff peculiar to the Fellaheen). </p>
         <p> Next day was the great dinner given by Mohammed and Mustapha outside Mohammed’s house
            opposite Sheykh Gibreel’s tomb—200 men ate at his gate. I went to see it and was of
            course asked to eat. ‘Can one like thee eat the Melocheea of the Fellaheen?’ So I joined
            a party of five round a little wooden tray, tucked up my sleeve and ate—dipping the
            bread into the Melocheea which is like very sloppy spinach but much nicer. Then came the
            master and his servants to deal the pieces of meat out of a great basket—sodden meat—and
            like Benjamin my piece was the largest, so I tore off a bit and handed it to each of my
            companions, who said ‘God take thee safe and happy to thy place and thy children and
            bring thee back to us in safety to eat the meat of the festival together once more.’ </p>
         <p> The moon rose clear and bright behind the one tall palm tree that overhangs the tomb of
            Sheykh Gibreel. He is a saint of homely tastes and will not have a dome over him or a
            cover for his tomb, which is only surrounded by a wall breast-high, enclosing a small
            square bit of ground with the rough tomb on one side. At each corner was set up a flag,
            and a few dim lanterns hung overhead. The 200 men eating were quite noiseless—and as
            they rose, one by one washed their hands and went, the crowd melted away like a vision.
            But before all were gone, came the Bulook, or sub-magistrate—a Turkish Jack in office
            with the manners of a Zouave turned parish beadle. He began to sneer at the _melocheea_
            of the fellaheen and swore he could not eat it if he sat before it 1,000 years.
            Hereupon, <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> began to ‘chaff’ him. ‘Eat, oh
            Bulook Pasha and if it swells thy belly the Lady will give thee of the physick of the
            English to clean thy stomach upwards and downwards of all thou hast eaten of the food of
            the fellaheen.’ The Bulook is notorious for his exactions—his ‘eating the people’—so
            there was a great laugh. Poor <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> was very ill
            next day—and every one thought the Bulook had given him the eye. </p>
         <p> Then came the Mufettish in state to pay his _devoirs_ to the Sheykh in the tomb. He
            came and talked to Mustapha and Yussuf and enumerated the people taken for the works,
            200 from Luxor, 400 from Carnac, 310 from Zenia, 320 from Byadyeh, and 380 from
            Salamieh—a good deal more than half the adult men to go for sixty days leaving their
            fields uncultivated and their <foreign xml:lang="ar">Hareem</foreign> and children
            hungry—for they have to take all the food for themselves. </p>
         <p> I rose sick at heart from the Mufettish’s harsh voice, and went down to listen to the
            Moonsheeds chanting at the tomb and the Zikheers’ strange sobbing, Allah, Allah. </p>
         <p> I leaned on the mud wall watching the slender figures swaying in the moonlight, when a
            tall, handsome fellah came up in his brown shirt, felt _libdeh_ (scull cap), with his
            blue cotton _melaya_ tied up and full of dried bread on his back. The type of the
            Egyptian. He stood close beside me and prayed for his wife and children. ‘Ask our God to
            pity them, O Sheykh, and to feed them while I am away. Thou knowest how my wife worked
            all night to bake all the wheat for me and that there is none left for her and the
            children.’ He then turned to me and took my hand and went on, ‘Thou knowest this lady,
            oh Sheykh Gibreel, take her happy and well to her place and bring her back to us—_el
            Fathah, yah Beshoosheh_!’ and we said it together. I could have laid my head on Sheykh
            Gibreel’s wall and howled. I thanked him as well as I could for caring about one like me
            while his own troubles were so heavy. I shall never forget that tall athletic figure and
            the gentle brown face, with the eleven days’ moon of Zulheggeh, and the shadow of the
            palm tree. That was my farewell. ‘The voice of the miserable is with thee, shall God not
            hear it?’ </p>
         <p> Next day <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> had a sharp attack of fever and
            was delirious—it lasted only two days but left him very weak and the anxiety and trouble
            was great—for my helping hands were as awkward as they were willing. </p>
         <p> In a few days arrived the boat Urania. She is very nice indeed. A small saloon, two
            good berths—bath and cabinet, and very large _kasneh_ (stern cabin). She is dirty, but
            will be extremely comfortable when cleaned and painted. On the 15th we sailed. Sheykh
            Yussuf went with me to <name type="place" ref="#kenneh">Keneh</name>, Mustapha and Seyd
            going by land—and one of Hajjee Sultan’s disciples and several Luxor men were deck
            passengers. The Shereef gave me the bread and jars of butter for his grandsons in Gama’l
            Azhar, and came to see me off. We sat on the deck outside as there was a crowd to say
            good-bye and had a lot of <foreign xml:lang="ar">Hareem</foreign> in the cabin. The old
            Shereef made me sit down on the carpet close to him and then said ‘we sit here like two
            lovers’—at eighty-five _even_ an Arab and a Shereef may be “_gaillard_”—so I cried, ‘Oh
            Shereef, what if <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> tells my master the secret
            thou hast let out—it is not well of thee.’ There was a great laugh which ended in the
            Shereef saying ‘no doubt thy master is of the best of the people, let us say the
            _Fathah_ for him,’ and he called on all the people ‘_El Fathah_ for the master of the
            lady!’ I hope it has benefited you to be prayed for at Luxor. </p>
         <p> I had written so far and passed <name type="place" ref="#minieh">Minieh</name> when I
            fell ill with pleurisy—I’ve lots more to tell of my journey but am too weak after two
            weeks in bed (and unable to lie down from suffocation)—but I am _much_ better now. A man
            from the Azhar is reading the Koran for me outside—while another is gone with candles to
            Seyeedele Zeynet ‘the fanatics!’</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>