<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, Monday, January 15, 1866.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/68">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</name>
               <date when="1866-01-15">15 January 1866</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff
                  Gordon</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Dearest <name type="person" ref="#alick">Alick</name>, </p>
         <p> I hear that Mr. and Miss North are to be here in a day or two. I hope you may have sent
            my saddle by them, for I want it sadly—mine is just possible for a donkey, but quite too
            broken for a horse. </p>
         <p> Two great Sheykhs of Bishareen and Abab’deh came here and picked me up out walking
            alone. We went and sat in a field, and they begged me to communicate to the Queen of
            England that they would join her troops if she would invade Egypt. One laid my hand on
            his hand and said ‘Thou hast 3,000 men in thy hand.’ The other rules 10,000. They say
            there are 30,000 Arabs (bedaween) ready to join the English, for they fear that the
            Viceroy will try to work and rob them like the fellaheen, and if so they will fight to
            the last, or else go off into Syria. I was rather frightened—for them, I mean, and told
            them that our Queen could do nothing till 600 Sheykhs and 400 Ameers had talked in
            public—all whose talk was printed and read at Stambool and <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>, and that they must not think of such a thing from our
            Queen, but if things became bad, it would be better for them to go off into Syria. I
            urged great caution upon them, and I need not repeat that to you, as the lives of
            thousands may be endangered. It might be interesting to be known in high places and in
            profound secret, as one of the indications of what is coming here. </p>
         <p> If the saddle comes, as I hope, I may very likely go up to <name type="place" ref="#assouan">Assouan</name>, and leave the boat and servants, and go into the
            desert for a few days to see the place of the Bishareen. They won’t take anyone else:
            but you may be quite easy about me ‘in the face’ of a Sheykh-el-Arab. Handsome Sheykh
            Hassan, whom you saw at <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>, will go with me.
            But if my saddle does not appear, I fear I should be too tired with riding a camel. </p>
         <p> The little district of Koos, including Luxor, has been mulcted of camels, food for them
            and drivers, to the amount of 6,000 purses—last week—£18,000, _fact_. I cast up the
            account, and it tallied with what I got from a sub _employé_, nor is the discontent any
            longer whispered. Everyone talks aloud—and well they may.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>