<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, OFF BOULAK, August 20, 1866.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/82">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</name>
               <date when="1866-08-20">20 August 1866</date>
               <rs type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/360630">Cairo</rs>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff
                  Gordon</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Dearest <name type="person" ref="#alick">Alick</name>, </p>
         <p> Since I wrote I have had a bad bilious attack, which has of course aggravated my cough.
            Everyone has had the same, and most far worse than I, but I was very wretched and most
            shamefully cross. <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> said, ‘That is not you but
            the sickness,’ when I found fault with everything, and it was very true. I am still
            seedy. Also I am beyond measure exasperated about my boat. I went up to the _Ata
            el-Khalig_ (cutting of the canal) to see the great sight of the ‘Bride of the Nile,’ a
            lovely spectacle; and on returning we all but sank. I got out into a boat of Zubeydeh’s
            with all my goods, and we hauled up my boat, and found her bottom rotten from stem to
            stern. So here I am in the midst of wood merchants, sawyers, etc., etc., rebuilding her
            bottom. My <name type="person" ref="#reis">Reis</name> said he had ‘carried her on his
            head all this time’ but ‘what could such a one as he say against the word of a Howagah,
            like <name type="person" ref="#ross">Ross</name>’s storekeeper?’ When the English cheat
            each other there remains nothing but to seek refuge with God. <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> buys the wood and superintends, together with the <name type="person" ref="#reis">Reis</name>, and the builders seem good workmen and
            fair-dealing. I pay day by day, and have a scribe to keep the accounts. If I get out of
            it for £150 I shall think <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> has done wonders,
            for every atom has to be new. I never saw anything so rotten afloat. If I had gone up
            the Cataract I should never have come down alive. It is a marvel we did not sink long
            ago. </p>
         <p> Mahbrook, Palgrave’s boy, has arrived, and turns out well. He is a stout lubberly boy,
            with infinite good humour, and not at all stupid, and laughs a good real nigger yahyah,
            which brings the fresh breezes and lilac mountains of the Cape before me when I hear it.
            When I tell him to do anything he does it with strenuous care, and then asks, _tayib_?
            (is it well) and if I say ‘Yes’ he goes off, as <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> says, ‘like a cannon in Ladyship’s face,’ in a guffaw of satisfaction.
            Achmet, who is half his size, orders him about and teaches him, with an air of extreme
            dignity and says pityingly to me, ‘You see, oh Lady, he is quite new, quite green.’
            Achmet, who had never seen a garment or any article of European life two years ago, is
            now a smart valet, with very distinct ideas of waiting at table, arranging my things
            etc. and cooks quite cleverly. Arab boys are amazing. I have promoted him to wages—one
            napoleon a month—so now he will keep his family. He is about a head taller than Rainie. </p>
         <p> I intend to write a paper on the various festivals and customs of Copts and Muslims;
            but I must wait to see Abu Seyfeyn, near Luxor, the great Christian Saint, where all go
            to be cured of possession—all mad people. The Viceroy wages steady war against all
            festivals and customs. The _Mahmal_ was burked this year, and the fair at <name type="place" ref="#tanta">Tanta</name>h forbidden. Then the Europeans spoil all; the
            Arabs no longer go to the _Ata el-Khalig_, and at the _Dóseh_, the Frangee carriages
            were like the Derby day. It is only up country that the real thing remains. </p>
         <p> To-morrow my poor black sheep will be killed over the new prow of the boat; his blood
            ‘straked’ upon her, and his flesh sodden and eaten by all the workmen, to keep off the
            evil eye; and on the day she goes into the water, some _Fikees_ will read the Koran in
            the cabin, and again there will be boiled mutton and bread. The Christian _Ma-allimeen_
            (skilled workmen) hold to the ceremony of the sheep quite as much as the others, and
            always do it over a new house, boat, mill, waterwheel etc. </p>
         <p> Did I tell you <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> has another girl—about two
            months ago? His wife and babies are to come up from <name type="place" ref="#alexandria">Alexandria </name> to see him, for he will not leave me for a day, on account of my
            constantly being so ailing and weak. I hope if I die away from you all, you will do
            something for <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> for my sake, I cannot conceive
            what I should do without his faithful and loving care. I don’t know why he is so
            devotedly fond of me, but he certainly does love me as he says ‘like his mother,’ and
            moreover as a very affectionate son loves his other. How pleasant it would be if you
            could come—but please don’t run any risks of fatigue or exposure to cold on your return.
            If you cannot come I shall go to Luxor early in October and send back the boat to let. I
            hear from Luxor that the people are all running away from the land, unable to pay triple
            taxes and eat bread: the ruin is universal. The poor Sheykhs el-Beled, who had the
            honour of dining with the Viceroy at <name type="place" ref="#minieh">Minieh</name> have
            each had a squeeze politely administered. One poor devil I know had to ‘make a present’
            of 50 purses. </p>
         <p> How is my darling Rainie? I do so long for her earnest eyes at times, and wonder if I
            shall ever be able to get back to you all again. I fear that break down at Soden sent me
            down a great terrace. I have never lost the pain and the cough for a day since. I have
            not been out for an age, or seen anyone. Would you know the wife of your bosom in a pair
            of pink trousers and a Turkish _tob_? Such is my costume as I write. The woman who came
            to sew could not make a gown, so she made me a pair of trousers instead. Farewell,
            dearest, I dare hardly say how your hint of possibly coming has made me wish it, and yet
            I dread to persuade you. The great heat is quite over with the high Nile, and the air on
            the river fresh and cool—cold at night even.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>