<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, March 7, 1867.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/98">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</name>
               <date when="1867-03-07">7 March 1867</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff
                  Gordon</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Dearest <name type="person" ref="#alick">Alick</name>, </p>
         <p> I have written a long yarn to <name type="person" ref="#sarah_austin">Mutter</name> and am rather tired, so I only write to say I am
            much better. The heat has set in, and, of course with it my health has mended, but I am
            a little shaky and afraid to tire myself. Moreover I want to nurse up and be stronger by
            next Thursday when <name type="person" ref="#janet">Janet</name> and <name type="person" ref="#ross">Ross</name> are expected. </p>
         <p> What a queer old fish your Dublin antiquary is, who wants to whitewash Miss
            Rhampsinitus, and to identify her with the beloved of Solomon (or Saleem); my brain spun
            round as I read it. Must I answer him, or will you? A dragoman gave me an old broken
            travelling arm-chair, and Yussuf sat in an arm-chair for the first time in his life.
            ‘May the soul of the man who made it find a seat in Paradise,’ was his exclamation,
            which strikes me as singularly appropriate on sitting in a very comfortable armchair.
            Yussuf was thankful for small mercies in this case. </p>
         <p> I am afraid <name type="person" ref="#janet">Janet</name> may be bored by all the
            people’s civility; they will insist on making great dinners and fantasias for her I am
            sure. I hope they will go on to <name type="place" ref="#assouan">Assouan</name> and
            take me with them; the change will do me good, and I should like to see as much of her
            as I can before she leaves Egypt for good. </p>
         <p> The state of business here is curious. The last regulations have stopped all money
            lending, and the prisons are full of Sheykh el-Beled whose villages can’t pay the taxes.
            Most respectable men have offered me to go partners with them now in their wheat, which
            will be cut in six weeks, if only I would pay their present taxes, I to take half the
            crop and half the taxes, with interest out of their half—some such trifle as 30 per
            cent, per month. Our prison is full of men, and we send them their dinner _à tour de
            rôle_. The other day a woman went with a big wooden bowl on her head, full of what she
            had cooked for them, accompanied by her husband. One Khaleel Effendi, a new vakeel here,
            was there, and said, ‘What dost thou ask here thou harlot?’ Her husband answered, ‘That
            is no harlot, oh Effendim, but my wife.’ Whereupon he was beaten till he fainted, and
            then there was a lamentation; they carried him down past my house, with a crowd of women
            all shrieking like mad creatures, especially his wife, who yelled and beat her head and
            threw dust over it, _more majorum_, as you see in the tombs. The humours of
            tax-gathering in this country are quite _impayable_ you perceive—and ought to be set
            forth on the escutcheon of the new Knight of the Bath whom the Queen hath delighted to
            honour. Cawass battant, Fellah rampant, and Fellaha pleurant would be the proper blazon.
            Distress in England is terrible, but, at least, it is not the result of extortion, as it
            is here, where everything from nature is so abundant and glorious, and yet mankind so
            miserable. It is not a little hunger, it is the cruel oppression which maddens the
            people now. They never complained before, but now whole villages are deserted. The boat
            goes to-morrow morning so I must say goodbye.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>