<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Mrs. Austin, LUXOR, April 12, 1867.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/97">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</name>
               <date when="1867-04-12">12 April 1867</date>
               <rs type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/360502">Luxor</rs>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/59830344">Sarah Austin</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Dearest <foreign xml:lang="de"><name type="person" ref="#sarah_austin">Mutter</name></foreign>, </p>
         <p> I have just received your letters, including the one for <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> which I read to him, and which he kissed and said he should
            keep as a _hegab_ (talisman). I have given him an order on Coutts’ correspondents for
            the money, in case I die. <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> proposes to wait
            till we get to <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name> and then to buy a little
            house, or a floor in one. I am to keep all the money till the house is found, so he will
            in no way be tempted to do anything foolish with it. I hope you approve? </p>
         <p>
            <name type="person" ref="#janet">Janet</name>’s visit was quite an _Eed_ (festival), as
            the people said. When I got up on the morning she was expected, I found the house decked
            with palm branches and lemon blossoms, and the holy flags of Abu-l-Hajjaj waving over my
            balcony. The mosque people had brought them, saying all the people were happy to-day,
            because it was a fortunate day for me. I suppose if I had had a mind to _testify_, I
            ought to have indignantly torn down the banners which bore the declaration, ‘There is no
            God but God, and Mohammed is His Prophet.’ But it appeared to me that if Imaams and
            Muezzins could send their banners to decorate a Christian house, the Christian might
            manage to endure the kindness. Then there was fantasia on horseback, and all the
            notables to meet the boat, and general welcome and jubilation. Next day I went on with
            Henry and <name type="person" ref="#janet">Janet</name> in the steamer, and had a very
            pleasant time to <name type="place" ref="#assouan">Assouan</name> and back, and they
            stayed another day here, and I hired a little dahabieh which they towed down to <name type="place" ref="#kenneh">Keneh</name> where they stayed a day; after which Sheykh
            Yussuf and I sailed back again to Luxor. As bad luck would have it we had hot weather
            just the week they were up here: since then it has been quite cool. </p>
         <p>
            <name type="person" ref="#janet">Janet</name> has left me her little black and tan
            terrier, a very nice little dog, but I can’t hope to rival <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> in his affections. He sleeps in <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name>’s bosom, and <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name>
            spoils and pets him all day, and boasts to the people how the dog drinks tea and coffee
            and eats dainty food, and the people say Mashallah! whereas I should have expected them
            to curse the dog’s father. The other day a scrupulous person drew back with an air of
            alarm from Bob’s approach, whereupon the dog stared at him, and forthwith plunged into
            Sheykh Yussuf’s lap, from which stronghold he ‘yapped’ defiance at whoever should object
            to him. I never laughed more heartily, and Yussuf went into _fou rire_. The mouth of the
            dog only is unclean, and Yussuf declares he is a very well-educated dog, and does not
            attempt to lick; he pets him accordingly, and gives him tea in his own saucer, only
            _not_ in the cup. </p>
         <p> I am to inherit another little blackie from <name type="person" ref="#ross">Ross</name>’s agency at <name type="place" ref="#kenneh">Keneh</name>: the funniest
            little chap. I cannot think why I go on expecting so-called savages to be different from
            other people. Mabrook’s simple talk about his village, and the animals and the victuals;
            and how the men of a neighbouring village stole him in order to sell him for a gun (the
            price of a gun is a boy), but were prevented by a razzia of Turks, etc. who killed the
            first aggressors and took all the children—all this he tells just as an English boy
            might tell of bird-nesting—delights me. He has the same general notion of right and
            wrong; and yet his tribe know neither bread nor any sort of clothes, nor cheese nor
            butter, nor even drink milk, nor the African beer; and it always rains there, and is
            always deadly cold at night, so that without a fire they would die. They have two
            products of civilization—guns and tobacco, for which they pay in boys and girls, whom
            they steal. I wonder where the country is, it is called Sowaghli, and the next people
            are Mueseh, on the sea-coast, and it is not so hot as Egypt. It must be in the southern
            hemisphere. The new _négrillon_ is from Darfoor. Won’t <name type="person" ref="#maurice">Maurice</name> be amused by his attendants, the Darfoor boy will trot
            after him, as he can shoot and clean guns, tiny as he is <name type="person" ref="#maurice">Maurice</name> seems to wish to come and I hope Alexander will let him
            spend the winter here, and I will take him up to the second Cataract; I really think he
            would enjoy it. </p>
         <p> My boat will not return I think for another six weeks. Mr. Eaton and Mr. Baird were
            such nice people! their dragoman, a Maltese, appeared to hate the Italians with
            ferocity. He said all decent people in Malta would ten times rather belong to the
            Mahommedans than to the Italians—after all blood tells. He was a very respectable young
            man, and being a dragoman and the son of a dragoman, he has seen the world, and
            particularly the Muslims. I suppose it is the Pope that makes the Italians so hateful to
            them. </p>
         <p> The post here is dreadful, I would not mind their reading one’s letters if they would
            only send them on. <name type="person" ref="#omar">Omar</name> begs we to say that he
            and his children will pray for you all his life, please God, not for the money only but
            still more for the good words and the trusting him. But he says, ‘I can’t say much
            _politikeh_, Please God she shall see, only I kiss her hand now.’ You will hear from
               <name type="person" ref="#janet">Janet</name> about her excursion. What I liked best
            was shooting the Cataract in a small boat; it was fine fantasia.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>