<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, CAIRO, June 16, 1865.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/61">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <date when="1865-06-16">16 June 1865</date>
               <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/360630">Cairo</settlement>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff Gordon</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK, </p>
         <p> I will go down to Alexandria in the boat and Omar will work at her. She wants a great
            deal of repairing I find, and his superintendence will save much money—besides he will
            do one man’s work as he is a much better carpenter than most here having learnt of the
            English workmen on the railroad—but the Reis says the boat must come out of the water as
            her bottom is unsound. She is a splendid sailer I hear and remarkably comfortable. The
            beds in the _kasneh_ would do for Jacob Omnium. So when you ‘honour our house’ you will
            be happy. The saloon is small, and the berths as usual. Also she is a very handsome
            shape—but she wants no end of repairs. So Omar is consoled at being left because he will
            ‘save our money’ a great deal by piecing sails, and cutting and contriving, and scraping
            and painting himself. Only he is afraid for me. However, _Allah Kereem_. </p>
         <p> I have a very good Reis I think. The usual tight little black fellow from near
            Assouan—very neat and active and good tempered—the same cross steersman that we had up
            to Bedreshayn—but he knows his work well. We had contrary gales the whole way. My men
            worked all they possibly could, and pulled the rope all day and rowed all night, day
            after day—but we were twenty-eight days getting down. </p>
         <p> I can’t write any more.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>