<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Mrs. Austin, OFF BOULAK, CAIRO, July 10, 1866.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/80">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <date when="1866-07-10">10 July 1866</date>
               <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/360630">Cairo</settlement>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/59830344">Sarah Austin</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST MUTTER, </p>
         <p> I am much better again. My cold went off without a violent illness and I was only weak
            and nervous. I am very comfortable here, anchored off <placeName ref="Boulak">Boulak</placeName>, with my Reis and one sailor who cleans and washes my clothes
            which Omar irons, as at Luxor, as he found the washerwomen here charged five francs a
            dozen for all small things and more for dresses. A bad _hashash_ boy turned Achmet’s
            head, who ran away for two days and spent a dollar in riotous living; he returned
            penitent, and got no fatted calf, but dry bread and a confiscation of his new clothes. </p>
         <p> The heat, when I left Luxor, was prodigious. I was detained three days by the death of
            Sheykh Yussuf’s poor little wife and baby (in childbirth) so I was forced to stay and
            eat the funeral feast, and be present at the _Khatmeh_ (reading of the Koran on the
            third night), or it would not have seemed kind. The Kadee gave me a very curious
            prayer-book, the Guide of the Faithful, written in Darfour! in beautiful characters, and
            with very singular decorations, and in splendid binding. It contains the names of all
            the prophets and of the hundred appellations of Mohammed, and is therefore a powerful
            _hegab_ or talisman. He requested me never to give it away and always to keep it with
            me. Such books cannot be bought with money at all. I also bought a most beautiful
            _hegab_ of cornelian set in enamel, the verse of the throne splendidly engraved, and
            dated 250 years ago. I sent over by Palgrave to Alick M. Brune’s lovely drawings of
            Luxor and Karnac, and to Maurice a gold coin which I received as a fee from an old
            Bedawee. </p>
         <p> It was so hot that I could not face the ride up to Keneh, when all my friends there
            came to fetch me, nor could I go to Siout. I never felt such heat. At Benisouef I went
            to see our Maōhn’s daughter married to another Maōhn there; it was a pleasant visit. The
            master of the house was out, and his mother and wife received me like one of the family;
            such a pretty woman and such darling children!—a pale, little slight girl of five, a
            sturdy boy of four, and a baby of one year old. The eager hospitality of the little
            creatures was quite touching. The little girl asked to have on her best frock, and then
            she stood before me and fanned me seriously and diligently, and asked every now and
            then, ‘Shall I make thee a sherbet?’ ‘Shall I bring thee a coffee?’ and then questions
            about grandpapa and grand mamma, and Abd el-Hameed and Abd el-Fattah; while the boy sat
            on his heels before me and asked questions about my family in his baby talk, and assured
            me it was a good day to him, and wanted me to stay three days, and to sleep with them.
            Their father came in and gave each an ashara (10 foddahs, ½ piastre) which, after
            consulting together, they tied in the corner of my handkerchief; ‘to spend on my
            journey.’ The little girl took such care of my hat and gloves and shoes, all very
            strange garments to her, but politeness was stronger than curiosity with the little
            things. I breakfasted with them all next day, and found much cookery going on for me. I
            took a doll for my little friend Ayoosheh, and some sugar-plums for Mohammed, but they
            laid them aside in order to devote themselves to the stranger, and all quietly, and with
            no sort of show-off or obtrusiveness. Even the baby seemed to have the instinct of
            hospitality, and was full of smiles. It was all of a piece with the good old lady, their
            grandmother at Luxor, who wanted to wash my clothes for me herself, because I said the
            black slave of Mohammed washed badly. Remember that to do ‘menial offices’ for a guest
            is an honour and pleasure, and not derogatory at all here. The ladies cook for you, and
            say, ‘I will cook my best for thee.’ The worst is that they stuff one so. Little
            Ayoosheh asked after my children, and said, ‘May God preserve them for thee! Tell thy
            little girl that Mohammed and I love her from afar off.’ Whereupon Mohammed declared
            that in a few years, please God, when he should be _balal_ (marriageable) he would marry
            her and live with me. When I went back to the boat the Effendi was ill with asthma, and
            I would not let him go with me in the heat (a polite man accompanies an honoured guest
            back to his house or boat, or tent). So the little boy volunteered, and we rode off on
            the Effendi’s donkey, which I had to bestride, with Mohammed on the hump of the saddle
            before me. He was delighted with the boat, of course, and romped and played about till
            we sailed, when his slave took him home. Those children gave me a happy day with their
            earnest, gracious hospitality. </p>
         <p> _July_ 14_th_.—Since I wrote this, I have had the boat topsy-turvy, with a carpenter
            and a _menegget_ (cushion-stuffer), and had not a corner even to write in. I am better,
            but still cough every morning. I am, however, much better, and have quite got over the
            nervous depression which made me feel unable and ashamed to write. My young carpenter—a
            Christian—half Syrian, half Copt, of the Greek rite, and altogether a Cairene—would have
            pleased you. He would not work on Sunday, but instead, came mounted on a splendid tall
            black donkey, and handsomely dressed, to pay me a visit, and go out with me for a ride.
            So he, I, and Omar went up to the Sittee (Lady) Zeyneb’s mosque, to inquire for Mustapha
            Bey Soubky, the Hakeem Pasha, whom I had known at Luxor. I was told by the porter of the
            mosque to seek him at the shop of a certain grocer, his particular friend, where he sits
            every evening. On going there we found the shop with its lid shut down (a shop is like a
            box laid on its side with the lid pulled up when open and dropped when shut; as big as a
            cobbler’s stall in Europe). The young grocer was being married, and Mustapha Bey was
            ill. So I went to his house in the quarter—such narrow streets!—and was shown up by a
            young eunuch into the hareem, and found my old friend very poorly, but spent a pleasant
            evening with him, his young wife—a Georgian slave whom he had married,—his daughter by a
            former wife—whom he had married when he was fourteen, and the female dwarf buffoon of
            the Valideh Pasha (Ismail’s mother) whose heart I won by rising to her, because she was
            so old and deformed. The other women laughed, but the little old dwarf liked it. She was
            a Circassian, and seemed clever. You see how the ‘Thousand and One Nights’ are quite
            true and real; how great Beys sit with grocers, and carpenters have no hesitation in
            offering civility to _naas omra_ (noble people). This is what makes Arab society quite
            unintelligible and impossible to most Europeans. </p>
         <p> My carpenter’s boy was the son of a _moonsheed_ (singer in the Mosque), and at night he
            used to sit and warble to us, with his little baby-voice, and little round, innocent
            face, the most violent love-songs. He was about eight years old, and sang with wonderful
            finish and precision, but no expression, until I asked him for a sacred song, which
            begins, ‘I cannot sleep for longing for thee, O Full Moon’ (the Prophet), and then the
            little chap warmed to his work, and the feeling came out. </p>
         <p> Palgrave has left in my charge a little black boy of his, now at Luxor, where he left
            him very ill, with Mustapha A’gha. The child told me he was a _nyan-nyan_ (cannibal),
            but he did not look ogreish. I have written to Mustapha to send him me by the first
            opportunity. Achmet has quite recovered his temper, and I do so much better without a
            maid that I shall remain so. The difference in expense is enormous, and the peace and
            quiet a still greater gain; no more grumbling and ‘exigencies’ and worry; Omar irons
            very fairly, and the sailor washes well enough, and I don’t want toilette—anyhow, I
            would rather wear a sack than try the experiment again. An uneducated, coarse-minded
            European is too disturbing an element in the family life of Easterns; the sort of filial
            relation, at once familiar and reverential of servants to a master they like, is odious
            to English and still more to French servants. If I fall in with an Arab or Abyssinian
            woman to suit me I will take her; but of course it is rare; a raw slave can do nothing,
            nor can a fellaha, and a <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> woman is bored to
            death up in the Saeed. As to care and attention, I want for nothing. Omar does
            everything well and with pride and pleasure, and is delighted at the saving of expense
            in wine, beer, meat, etc. etc. One feeds six or eight Arabs well with the money for one
            European. </p>
         <p> While the carpenter, his boy, and two _meneggets_ were here, a very moderate dish of
            vegetables, stewed with a pound of meat, was put before me, followed by a chicken or a
            pigeon for me alone. The stew was then set on the ground to all the men, and two loaves
            of a piastre each, to every one, a jar of water, and, _Alhamdulillah_, four men and two
            boys had dined handsomely. At breakfast a water-melon and another loaf-a-piece, and a
            cup of coffee all round; and I pass for a true Arab in hospitality. Of course no
            European can live so, and they despise the Arabs for doing it, while the Arab servant is
            not flattered at seeing the European get all sorts of costly luxuries which he thinks
            unnecessary; besides he has to stand on the defensive, in order not to be made a drudge
            by his European fellow-servant, and despised for being one; and so he leaves undone all
            sorts of things which he does with alacrity when it is for ‘the master’ only. What Omar
            does now seems wonderful, but he says he feels like the Sultan now he has only me to
            please. </p>
         <p> _July_ 15_th_.—Last night came the two _meneggets_ to pay a friendly visit, and sat and
            told stories; so I ordered coffee, and one took his sugar out of his pocket to put in
            his cup, which made me laugh inwardly. He told a fisherman, who stopped his boat
            alongside for a little conversation, the story of two fishermen, the one a Jew, the
            other a Muslim, who were partners in the time of the Arab Prophet (upon whom be blessing
            and peace!). The Jew, when he flung his nets called on the Prophet of the Jews, and
            hauled it up full of fish every time; then the Muslim called on our Master Mohammed
            etc., etc., and hauled up each time only stones, until the Jew said, ‘Depart, O man,
            thou bringest us misfortune; shall I continue to take half thy stones, and give thee
            half my fish? Not so.’ So the Muslim went to our Master Mohammed and said, ‘Behold, I
            mention thy name when I cast my net, and I catch only stones and calamity. How is this?’
            But the blessed Prophet said to him, ‘Because thy stomach is black inwardly, and thou
            thoughtest to sell thy fish at an unfair price, and to defraud thy partner and the
            people, while the Jew’s heart was clean towards thee and the people, and therefore God
            listened to him rather than to thee.’ I hope our fisherman was edified by this fine
            moral. I also had good stories from the chief diver of <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>, who came to examine the bottom of my boat, and told me, in a
            whisper, a long tale of his grandfather’s descent below the waters of the Nile, into the
            land of the people who lived there, and keep tame crocodiles to hunt fish for them. They
            gave him a sleeve-full of fishes’ scales, and told him never to return, and not to tell
            about them: and when he got home the scales had turned to money. But most wonderful of
            all was Haggi Hannah’s story of her own life, and the journey of Omar’s mother carrying
            her old mother in a basket on her head from Damietta to Alexandria, and dragging Omar
            then a very little boy, by the hand. The energy of many women here is amazing. </p>
         <p> The Nile is rising fast, and the _Bisheer_ is come (the messenger who precedes the
            Hajj, and brings letters). _Bisheer_ is ‘good tidings,’ to coin a word. Many hearts are
            lightened and many half-broken to-day. I shall go up to the Abassia to meet the Mahmal
            and see the Hajjees arrive. </p>
         <p> Next Friday I must take my boat out of the water, or at least heel her over, to repair
            the bad places made at Alexandria. It seems I once cured a Reis of the Pasha’s of
            dysentery at Minieh, and he has not forgotten it, though I had; so Reis Awad will give
            me a good place on the Pasha’s bank, and lend ropes and levers which will save a deal of
            expense and trouble. I shall move out all the things and myself into a boat of
            Zubeydeh’s for four or five days, and stay alongside to superintend my caulkers. </p>
         <p> Miss Berry _is_ dull no doubt, but few books seem dull to me now, I can tell you, and I
            was much delighted with such a _pièce de résistance_. Miss Eden I don’t wish for—that
            sort of theatre burlesque view of the customs of a strange country is inexpressibly
            tedious to one who is familiar with one akin to it. There is plenty of _real_ fun to be
            had here, but that sort is only funny to cockneys. I want to read Baker’s book very
            much. I am much pleased with Abd el-Kader’s book which Dozon sent me, and want the
            original dreadfully for Sheykh Yussuf, to show him that he and I are supported by such
            an authority as the great Ameer in our notions about the real unity of the Faith. The
            book is a curious mixture of good sense and credulity—quite ‘Arab of the Arabs.’ I will
            write a paper on the popular beliefs of Egypt; it will be curious, I think. By the way,
            I see in the papers and reviews speculations as to some imaginary Mohammedan conspiracy,
            because of the very great number of pilgrims last year from all parts to Mecca. _C’est
            chercher midi à quatorze heures_. Last year the day of Abraham’s sacrifice,—and
            therefore _the_ day of the pilgrimage—(the sermon on Mount Arafat) fell on a Friday, and
            when that happens there is always a rush, owing to the popular notion that the _Hajj
            el-Gumma_ (pilgrimage of the Friday) is seven times blessed, or even equivalent to
            making it seven times in ordinary years. As any beggar in the street could tell a man
            this, it may give you some notion of how absurdly people make theories out of nothing
            for want of a little commonsense. </p>
         <p> The _Moolid en-Nebbee_ (Festival of the Prophet) has just begun. I am to have a place
            in the great Derweesh’s tent to see the Doseh. </p>
         <p> The Nile is rising fast; we shall kill the poor little Luxor black lamb on the day of
            the opening of the canal, and have a _fantasia_ at night; only I grieve for my little
            white pussy, who sleeps every night on Ablook’s (the lamb’s) woolly neck, and loves him
            dearly. Pussy (‘Bish’ is Arabic for puss) was the gift of a Coptic boy at Luxor, and is
            wondrous funny, and as much more active and lissom than a European cat as an Arab is
            than an Englishman. She and Achmet and Ablook have fine games of romps. Omar has set his
            heart on an English signet ring with an oval stone to engrave his name on, here you know
            they sign papers with a signet, not with a pen. It must be _solid_ to stand hard work. </p>
         <p> Well, I must finish this endless letter. Here comes _such_ a bouquet from the Pasha’s
            garden (somebody’s sister’s son is servant to the chief eunuch and brings it to me), a
            great round of scarlet, surrounded with white and green and with tall reeds, on which
            are threaded single tube-rose flowers, rising out of it so as to figure a huge flower
            with white pistils. Arab gardeners beat French flower-girls in bouquets.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>