<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, CAIRO, December 2, 1863.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/21">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/360630">Cairo</settlement>
               <date when="1863-12-02">2 December 1863</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff Gordon</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p> DEAREST ALICK, </p>
         <p> It is beginning to be cold here, and I only await the results of my inquiries about
            possible houses at Thebes to hire a boat and depart. Yesterday I saw a camel go through
            the eye of a needle—_i.e._, the low arched door of an enclosure; he must kneel and bow
            his head to creep through—and thus the rich man must humble himself. See how a false
            translation spoils a good metaphor, and turns a familiar simile into a ferociously
            communist sentiment. I expect Henry and Janet here in four or five days when her ancle
            allows her to travel. If I get a house at Thebes, I will only hire a boat up and dismiss
            it, and trust to Allah for my return. There are rumours of troubles at Jeddah, and a
            sort of expectation of fighting somewhere next spring; even here people are buying arms
            to a great extent, I think the gunsmiths’ bazaar looks unusually lively. I do look
            forward to next November and your coming here; I know you would donkey-ride all day in a
            state of ecstasy. I never saw so good a servant as Omar and such a nice creature, so
            pleasant and good. When I hear and see what other people spend here in travelling and in
            living, and what bother they have, I say: ‘May God favour Omar and his descendants.’ </p>
         <p> I stayed in bed yesterday for a cold, and my next-door neighbour, a Coptic merchant,
            kept me awake all night by auditing his accounts with his clerk. How would you like to
            chant your rows of figures? He had just bought lots of cotton, and I had to get into my
            door on Monday over a camel’s back, the street being filled with bales. </p>
         <p> * * * * * </p>
         <p> [The house at Thebes of which my mother speaks in the following letter was built about
            1815, over the ancient temple of Khem, by Mr. Salt, English Consul-General in Egypt. He
            was an archæologist and a student of hieroglyphics, and when Belzoni landed at
            Alexandria was struck by his ability, and sent him up to Thebes to superintend the
            removal of the great bust of Memnon, now in the British Museum. Belzoni, I believe,
            lived for some time in Mr. Salt’s house, which afterwards became the property of the
            French Government, and was known as the _Maison de France_; it was pulled down in 1884
            when the great temple of Luxor was excavated by M. Maspero. My late friend Miss A. B.
            Edwards wrote a description of his work in the _Illustrated London News_, from which I
            give a few extracts: </p>
         <p> ‘Squatters settled upon the temple like a swarm of mason bees; and the extent of the
            mischief they perpetrated in the course of centuries may be gathered from the fact that
            they raised the level of the surrounding soil to such a height that the obelisks, the
            colossi, and the entrance pylon were buried to a depth of 40 feet, while inside the
            building the level of the native village was 50 feet above the original pavement. Seven
            months ago the first court contained not only the local mosque, but a labyrinthine maze
            of mud structures, numbering some thirty dwellings, and eighty strawsheds, besides
            yards, stables, and pigeon-towers, the whole being intersected by innumerable lanes and
            passages. Two large mansions—real mansions, spacious and, in Arab fashion,
            luxurious,—blocked the great Colonnade of Horembebi; while the second court, and all the
            open spaces and ruined parts of the upper end of the Temple, were encumbered by
            sheepfolds, goat-yards, poultry-yards, donkey-sheds, clusters of mud huts, refuse-heaps,
            and piles of broken pottery. Upon the roof of the portico there stood a large, rambling,
            ruinous old house, the property of the French Government, and known as the “Maison de
            France” . . . Within its walls the illustrious Champollion and his ally Rosellini lived
            and worked together in 1829, during part of their long sojourn at Thebes. Here the naval
            officers sent out by the French in 1831 to remove the obelisk which now stands in the
            Place de la Concorde took up their temporary quarters. And here, most interesting to
            English readers, Lady Duff Gordon lingered through some of her last winters, and wrote
            most of her delightful “Letters from Egypt.” A little balcony with a broken veranda and
            a bit of lattice-work parapet, juts out above some mud walls at the end of the building.
            Upon that balcony she was wont to sit in the cool of the evening, watching the boats
            upon the river and the magical effect of the after-glow upon the Libyan mountains
            opposite. All these buildings—“Maison de France,” stores, yards, etc. . . . are all
            swept away.’] </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>