<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, OFF BOULAK, September 21,
               1886.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/84">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <date when="1866-09-21">21 September 1866</date>
               <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/360630">Cairo</settlement>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff Gordon</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>I am better again now and go on very comfortably with my two little boys. Omar is from
            dawn till night at work at my boat, so I have only Mahbrook and Achmet, and you would
            wonder to see how well I am served. Achmet cooks a very good dinner, serves it and
            orders Mahbrook about. Sometimes I whistle and hear _hader_ (ready) from the water and
            in tumbles Achmet, with the water running ‘down his innocent nose’ and looking just like
            a little bronze triton of a Renaissance fountain, with a blue shirt and white skull-cap
            added. Mahbrook is a big lubberly lad of the laugh-and-grow-fat breed, clumsy, but not
            stupid, and very good and docile. You would delight in his guffaws, and the merry games
            and hearty laughter of my _ménage_ is very pleasant to me. Another boy swims over from
            Goodah’s boat (his Achmet), and then there are games at piracy, and much stealing of red
            pots from the potter’s boats. The joke is to snatch one under the owner’s very nose, and
            swim off brandishing it, whereupon the boatman uses eloquent language, and the boys
            out-hector him, and everybody is much amused. I only hope Palgrave won’t come back from
            Sookum Kaleh to fetch Mahbrook just as he has got clever—not at stealing jars, but in
            his work. He already washes my clothes very nicely indeed; his stout black arms are made
            for a washer-boy. Achmet looked forward with great eagerness to your coming. He is mad
            to go to England, and in his heart planned to ingratiate himself with you, and go as a
            ‘general servant.’ He is very little, if at all, bigger than a child of seven, but an
            Arab boy ‘_ne doute de rien_’ and does serve admirably. What would an English
            respectable cook say to seeing ‘two dishes and a sweet’ cooked over a little old wood on
            a few bricks, by a baby in a blue shirt? and very well cooked too, and followed by
            incomparable coffee. </p>
         <p> You will be pleased to hear that your capital story of the London cabman has its exact
            counterpart here. ‘Oh gracious God, what aileth thee, oh Achmet my brother, and why is
            thy bosom contracted that thou hast not once said to me d------n thy father, or son of a
            dog or pig, as thou art used to do.’ </p>
         <p> Can’t you save up your holidays and come for four months next winter with my Maurice?
            However perhaps you would be bored on the Nile. I don’t know. People either enjoy it
            rapturously or are bored, I believe. I am glad to hear from Janet that you are well. I
            am much better. The carpenter will finish in the boat to-day, then the painter begins
            and in a week, Inshallah, I shall get back into her.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>