<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, LUXOR, June 26, 1864.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/42">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/360502">Luxor</settlement>
               <date when="1864-06-26">26 June 1864</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff Gordon</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK, </p>
         <p> I have just paid a singular visit to a political _detenu_ or exile rather. Last night
            Mustapha came in with a man in great grief who said his boy was very ill on board a
            cangia just come from <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> and going to Assouan. The
            watchman on the river-bank had told him that there was an English Sitt ‘who would not
            turn her face from anyone in trouble’ and advised him to come to me for medicine, so he
            went to Mustapha and begged him to bring him to me, and to beg the cawass (policeman) in
            charge of El-Bedrawee (who was being sent to Fazoghlou in banishment) to wait a few
            hours. The cawass (may he not suffer for his humanity) consented. He described his boy’s
            symptoms and I gave him a dose of castor oil and said I would go to the boat in the
            morning. The poor fellow was a <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> merchant but
            living at Khartoum, he poured out his sorrow in true Eastern style. ‘Oh my boy, and I
            have none but he, and how shall I come before his mother, a Habbesheeyeh, oh Lady, and
            tell her “thy son is dead”?’ So I said, ‘_Allah kereem ya Seedee_, and _Inshallah
            tayib_,’ etc., etc., and went this morning early to the boat. It was a regular old Arab
            cangia lumbered up with corn, sacks of matting, a live sheep, etc., and there I found a
            sweet graceful boy of fifteen or so in a high fever. His father said he had visited a
            certain Pasha on the way and evidently meant that he had been poisoned or had the evil
            eye. I assured him it was only the epidemic and asked why he had not sent for the doctor
            at Keneh. The old story! He was afraid, ‘God knows what a government doctor might do to
            the boy.’ Then Omar came in and stood before El-Bedrawee and said, ‘Oh my master, why do
            we see thee thus? Mashallah, I once ate of thy bread when I was of the soldiers of Said
            Pasha, and I saw thy riches and thy greatness, and what has God decreed against thee?’
            So El-Bedrawee who is (or was) one of the wealthiest men of Lower Egypt and lived at
            Tantah, related how Effendina (Ismail Pasha) sent for him to go to <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> to the Citadel to transact some business, and how he
            rode his horse up to the Citadel and went in, and there the Pasha at once ordered a
            cawass to take him down to the Nile and on board a common cargo boat and to go with him
            and take him to Fazoghlou. Letters were given to the cawass to deliver to every Moudir
            on the way, and another despatched by hand to the Governor of Fazoghlou with orders
            concerning El-Bedrawee. He begged leave to see his son once more before starting, or any
            of his family. ‘No, he must go at once and see no one.’ But luckily a fellah, one of his
            relations had come after him to <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> and had £700 in
            his girdle; he followed El-Bedrawee to the Citadel and saw him being walked off by the
            cawass and followed him to the river and on board the boat and gave him the £700 which
            he had in his girdle. The various Moudirs had been civil to him, and friends in various
            places had given him clothes and food. He had not got a chain round his neck or fetters,
            and was allowed to go ashore with the cawass, for he had just been to the tomb of
            Abou-l-Hajjaj and had told that dead Sheykh all his affliction and promised, if he came
            back safe, to come every year to his _moolid_ (festival) and pay the whole expenses
            (_i.e._ feed all comers). Mustapha wanted him to dine with him and me, but the cawass
            could not allow it, so Mustapha sent him a fine sheep and some bread, fruit, etc. I made
            him a present of some quinine, rhubarb pills, and sulphate of zinc for eye lotion. Here
            you know we all go upon a more than English presumption and believe every prisoner to be
            innocent and a victim—as he gets no trial he _never_ can be proved guilty—besides poor
            old El-Bedrawee declared he had not the faintest idea what he was accused of or how he
            had offended Effendina. </p>
         <p> I listened to all this in extreme amazement, and he said, ‘Ah! I know you English
            manage things very differently; I have heard all about your excellent justice.’ </p>
         <p> He was a stout, dignified-looking fair man, like a Turk, but talking broad Lower Egypt
            fellah talk, so that I could not understand him, and had to get Mustapha and Omar to
            repeat his words. His father was an Arab, and his mother a Circassian slave, which gave
            the fair skin and reddish beard. He must be over fifty, fat and not healthy; of course
            he is _meant_ to die up in Fazoghlou, especially going at this season. He owns (or
            owned, for God knows who has it now) 12,000 feddans of fine land between Tantah and
            Samanhoud, and was enormously rich. He consulted me a great deal about his health, and I
            gave him certainly very good advice. I cannot write in a letter which I know you will
            show what drugs a Turkish doctor had furnished him with to ‘strengthen’ him in the
            trying climate of Fazoghlou. I wonder was it intended to kill him or only given in
            ignorance of the laws of health equal to his own? </p>
         <p> After a while the pretty boy became better and recovered consciousness, and his poor
            father, who had been helping me with trembling hands and swimming eyes, cried for joy,
            and said, ‘By God the most high, if ever I find any of the English, poor or sick or
            afflicted up in Fazoghlou, I will make them know that I Abu Mahommed never saw a face
            like the pale face of the English lady bent over my sick boy.’ And then El-Bedrawee and
            his fellah kinsman, and all the crew blessed me and the Captain, and the cawass said it
            was time to sail. So I gave directions and medicine to Abu Mahommed, and kissed the
            pretty boy and went out. El-Bedrawee followed me up the bank, and said he had a request
            to make—would I pray for him in his distress. I said, ‘I am not of the Muslimeen,’ but
            both he and Mustapha said, _Maleysh_ (never mind), for that it was quite certain I was
            not of the _Mushkireen_, as they hate the Muslimeen and their deeds are evil—but blessed
            be God, many of the English begin to repent of their evil, and to love the Muslims and
            abound in kind actions. So we parted in much kindness. It was a strange feeling to me to
            stand on the bank and see the queer savage-looking boat glide away up the stream, bound
            to such far more savage lands, and to be exchanging kind farewells quite in a homely
            manner with such utter ‘aliens in blood and faith.’ ‘God keep thee Lady, God keep thee
            Mustapha.’ Mustapha and I walked home very sad about poor El-Bedrawee. </p>
         <p> _Friday_, _July_ 7.—It has been so ‘awfully’ hot that I have not had pluck to go on
            with my letter, or indeed to do anything but lie on a mat in the passage with a minimum
            of clothes quite indescribable in English. _Alhamdulilah_! laughs Omar, ‘that I see the
            clever English people do just like the lazy Arabs.’ The worst is not the positive heat,
            which has not been above 104° and as low as 96° at night, but the horrible storms of hot
            wind and dust which are apt to come on at night and prevent one’s even lying down till
            twelve or one o’clock. Thebes is bad in the height of summer on account of its expanse
            of desert, and sand and dust. The Nile is pouring down now gloriously, and _really_ red
            as blood—more crimson than a Herefordshire lane—and in the distance the reflection of
            the pure blue sky makes it deep violet. It had risen five cubits a week ago; we shall
            soon have it all over the land here. It is a beautiful and inspiriting sight to see the
            noble old stream as young and vigorous as ever. No wonder the Egyptians worshipped the
            Nile: there is nothing like it. We have had all the plagues of Egypt this year, only the
            lice are commuted for bugs, and the frogs for mice; the former have eaten me and the
            latter have eaten my clothes. We are so ragged! Omar has one shirt left, and has to
            sleep without and wash it every night. The dust, the drenching perspiration, and the
            hard-fisted washing of Mahommed’s slave-women destroys everything. </p>
         <p> Mustapha intends to give you a grand _fantasia_ if you come, and to have the best
            dancing girls down from Esneh for you; but I am consternated to hear that you can’t come
            till December. I hoped you would have arrived in <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> early in November, and spent a month there with me, and come up
            the river in the middle of December when <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> gets
            very cold. </p>
         <p> I remain very well in general health, but my cough has been troublesome again. I do not
            feel at all like breathing cold damp air again. This depresses me very much as you may
            suppose. You will have to divorce me, and I must marry some respectable Kadee. I have
            been too ‘lazy Arab,’ as Omar calls it, to go on with my Arabic lessons, and Yussuf has
            been very busy with law business connected with the land and the crops. Every harvest
            brings a fresh settling of the land. Wheat is selling at £1 the ardeb {188} here _on the
            threshing-floor_, and barley at one hundred and sixteen piastres; I saw some Nubians pay
            Mustapha that. He is in comic perplexity about saying _Alhamdulillah_ about such
            enormous gains—you see it is rather awkward for a Muslim to thank God for dear bread—so
            he compounds by very lavish almsgiving. He gave all his fellaheen clothes the other
            day—forty calico shirts and drawers. Do you remember my describing an Arab _emancipirtes
            Fraülein_ at Siout? Well, the other day I saw as I thought a nice-looking lad of sixteen
            selling corn to my opposite neighbour, a Copt. It was a girl. Her father had no son and
            is infirm, so she works in the field for him, and dresses and does like a man. She
            looked very modest and was quieter in her manner than the veiled women often are. </p>
         <p> I am so glad to hear such good accounts of my Rainie and Maurice. I can hardly bear to
            think of another year without seeing them. However it is fortunate for me that ‘my lines
            have fallen in pleasant places,’ so long a time at the Cape or any Colony would have
            become intolerable. Best love to Janet, I really can’t write, it’s too hot and dusty.
            Omar desires his salaam to his great master and to that gazelle Sittee Ross.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>