<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Mrs. Austin, LUXOR, April 29, 1865.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/59">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <date when="1865-04-29">29 April 1865</date>
               <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/360502">Luxor</settlement>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/59830344">Sarah Austin</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST MUTTER, </p>
         <p> Since I wrote last I have received the box with the cheese quite fresh (and very good
            it tastes), and the various things. Nothing called forth such a shout of joy from me as
            your photo of the village pothouse. How green and fresh and tidy! Many Mashallah’s have
            been uttered over the _beyt-el-fellaheen_ (peasant’s house) of England. The railings,
            especially, are a great marvel. I have also heard from Janet that Ross has bought me a
            boat for £200 which is to take four of his agents to Assouan and then come back for me.
            So all my business is settled, and, _Inshallah_! I shall depart in another three or four
            weeks. </p>
         <p> The weather is quite cool and fresh again but the winds very violent and the dust pours
            over us like water from the dried up land, as well as from the Goomeh mountain. It is
            miserably uncomfortable, but my health is much better again—spite of all. </p>
         <p> The Hakeem business goes on at a great rate. I think on an average I have four sick a
            day. Sometimes a dozen. A whole gipsy camp are great customers—the poor souls will bring
            all manner of gifts it goes to my heart to eat, but they can’t bear to be refused. They
            are astounded to hear that people of their blood live in England and that I knew many of
            their customs—which are the same here. </p>
         <p> Kursheed Agha came to take final leave being appointed to Keneh. He had been at Gau and
            had seen Fadil Pasha sit and make the soldiers lay sixty men down on their backs by ten
            at a time and _chop_ them to death with the pioneers’ axes. He estimated the people
            killed—men, women, and children at 1,600—but Mounier tells me it was over 2,000. Sheykh
            Hassan agreed exactly with Kursheed, only the Arab was full of horror and the Circassian
            full of exultation. His talk was exactly what we all once heard about ‘Pandies,’ and he
            looked and talked and laughed so like a fine young English soldier, that I was ashamed
            to call him the kelb (dog) which rose to my tongue, and I bestowed it on Fadil Pasha
            instead. I must also say in behalf of my own countrymen that they _had_ provocation
            while here there was none. Poor Haggee Sultan lies in chains at Keneh. One of the best
            and kindest of men! I am to go and take secret messages to him, and money from certain
            men of religion to bribe the Moudir with. The Shurafa who have asked me to do this are
            from another place, as well as a few of the Abu-l-Hajjajieh. A very great Shereef indeed
            from lower Egypt, said to me the other day, ‘Thou knowest if I am a Muslim or no. Well,
            I pray to the most Merciful to send us Europeans to govern us, and to deliver us from
            these wicked men.’ We were all sitting after the funeral of one of the Shurafa and I was
            sitting between the Shereef of Luxor and the Imám—and this was said before thirty or
            forty men, all Shurafa. No one said ‘No,’ and many assented aloud. </p>
         <p> The Shereef asked me to lend him the New Testament, it was a pretty copy and when he
            admired it I said, ‘From me to thee, oh my master the Shereef, write in it as we do in
            remembrance of a friend—the gift of a Nazraneeyeh who loves the Muslimeen.’ The old man
            kissed the book and said ‘I will write moreover—to a Muslim who loves all such
            Christians’—and after this the old Sheykh of Abou Ali took me aside and asked me to go
            as messenger to Haggee Sultan for if one of them took the money it would be taken from
            them and the man get no good by it. </p>
         <p> Soldiers are now to be quartered in the Saeed—a new plague worse than all the rest. Do
            not the cawasses already rob the poor enough? They fix their own price in the market and
            beat the sakkas as sole payment. What will the soldiers do? The taxes are being
            illegally levied on lands which are _sheragi_, _i.e._ totally unwatered by the last Nile
            and therefore exempt _by law_—and the people are driven to desperation. I feel sure
            there will be more troubles as soon as there arises any other demagogue like Achmet
            et-Tayib to incite the people and now every Arab sympathises with him. Janet has written
            me the <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> version of the affair cooked for the
            European taste—and monstrous it is. The Pasha accuses some Sheykh of the Arabs of having
            gone from Upper Egypt to India to stir up the Mutiny against us! _Pourquoi pas_ to
            conspire in Paris or London? It is too childish to talk of a poor Saeedee Arab going to
            a country of whose language and whereabouts he is totally ignorant, in order to conspire
            against people who never hurt him. You may suppose how Yussuf and I talk by ourselves of
            all these things. He urged me to try hard to get my husband here as
            Consul-General—assuming that he would feel as I do. I said, my master is not young, and
            to a just man the wrong of such a place would be a martyrdom. ‘Truly thou hast said it,
            but it is a martyr we Arabs want; shall not the reward of him who suffers daily vexation
            for his brethren’s sake be equal to that of him who dies in battle for the faith? If
            thou wert a man, I would say to thee, take the labour and sorrow upon thee, and thine
            own heart will repay thee.’ He too said like the old Sheykh, ‘I only pray for Europeans
            to rule us—now the fellaheen are really worse off than any slaves.’ I am sick of telling
            of the daily oppressions and robberies. If a man has a sheep, the Moodir comes and eats
            it, if a tree, it goes to the Nazir’s kitchen. My poor sakka is beaten by the cawasses
            in sole payment of his skins of water—and then people wonder my poor friends tell lies
            and bury their money. </p>
         <p> I now know everybody in my village and the ‘cunning women’ have set up the theory that
            my eye is lucky; so I am asked to go and look at young brides, visit houses that are
            building, inspect cattle, etc. as a bringer of good luck—which gives me many a curious
            sight. </p>
         <p> I went a few days ago to the wedding of handsome Sheykh Hassan the Abab’deh, who
            married the butcher’s pretty little daughter. The group of women and girls lighted by
            the lantern which little Achmet carried up for me was the most striking thing I have
            seen. The bride—a lovely girl of ten or eleven all in scarlet, a tall dark slave of
            Hassan’s blazing with gold and silver necklaces and bracelets, with long twisted locks
            of coal black hair and such glittering eyes and teeth, the wonderful wrinkled old women,
            and the pretty, wondering, yet fearless children were beyond description. The mother
            brought the bride up to me and unveiled her and asked me to let her kiss my hand, and to
            look at her, I said all the usual _Bismillah Mashallah’s_, and after a time went to the
            men who were eating, all but Hassan who sat apart and who begged me to sit by him, and
            whispered anxious enquiries about his _aroosah’s_ looks. After a time he went to visit
            her and returned in half an hour very shy and covering his face and hand and kissed the
            hands of the chief guests. Then we all departed and the girl was taken to look at the
            Nile, and then to her husband’s house. Last night he gave me a dinner—a very good dinner
            indeed, in his house which is equal to a very poor cattle shed at home. We were only
            five. Sheykh Yussuf, Omar, an elderly merchant and I. Hassan wanted to serve us but I
            made him sit. </p>
         <p> The merchant, a well-bred man of the world who has enjoyed life and married wives
            everywhere—had arrived that day and found a daughter of his dead here. He said he felt
            very miserable—and everyone told him not to mind and consoled him oddly enough to
            English ideas. Then people told stories. Omar’s was a good version of the man and wife
            who would not shut the door and agreed that the first to speak should do it—very funny
            indeed. Yussuf told a pretty tale of a Sultan who married a Bint el-Arab (daughter of
            the Bedawee) and how she would not live in his palace, and said she was no fellaha to
            dwell in houses, and scorned his silk clothes and sheep killed for her daily, and made
            him live in the desert with her. A black slave told a prosy tale about thieves—and the
            rest were more long than pointed. </p>
         <p> Hassan’s Arab feelings were hurt at the small quantity of meat set before me. (They
            can’t kill a sheep now for an honoured guest.) But I told him no greater honour could be
            paid to us English than to let us eat lentils and onions like one of the family, so that
            we might not feel as strangers among them—which delighted all the party. After a time
            the merchant told us his heart was somewhat dilated—as a man might say his toothache had
            abated—and we said ‘Praise be to God’ all round. </p>
         <p> A short time ago my poor friend the Maōhn had a terrible ‘tile’ fall on his head. His
            wife, two married daughters and nine miscellaneous children arrived on a sudden, and the
            poor man is now tasting the pleasures which Abraham once endured between Sarah and
            Hagar. I visited the ladies and found a very ancient Sarah and a daughter of wonderful
            beauty. A young man here—a Shereef—has asked me to open negotiations for a marriage for
            him with the Maōhn’s grand daughter a little girl of eight—so you see how completely I
            am ‘one of the family.’ </p>
         <p> My boat has not yet made its appearance. I am very well indeed now, in spite, or
            perhaps because of, the great heat. But there is a great deal of sickness—chiefly
            dysentery. I never get less than four new patients a day and my ‘practice’ has become
            quite a serious business. I spent all day on Friday in the Abab’deh quarters where
            Sheykh Hassan and his slave Rahmeh were both uncommonly ill. Both are ‘all right’ now.
            Rahmeh is the nicest negro I ever knew, and a very great friend of mine. He is a most
            excellent, honest, sincere man, and an Effendi (_i.e._ writes and reads) which is more
            than his master can do. He has seen all the queer people in the interior of Africa. </p>
         <p> The Sheykh of the Bishareen—eight days’ journey from Assouan has invited me and
            promises me all the meat and milk I can eat, they have nothing else. They live on a high
            mountain and are very fine handsome people. If only I were strong I could go to very odd
            places where Frangees are not. Read a very stupid novel (as a story) called ‘_le Secret
            du Bonheur_’—it gives the truest impression of the manners of Arabs that I have read—by
            Ernest Feydeau. According to his book _achouat_ (we are brothers). The ‘caressant’ ways
            of Arabs are so well described. </p>
         <p> It is the same here. The people come and pat and stroke me with their hands, and one
            corner of my brown abbaieh is faded with much kissing. I am hailed as _Sitt Betaana_
            ‘Our own Lady,’ and now the people are really enthusiastic because I refused the offer
            of some cawasses as a guard which a Bimbashee made me. As if I would have such fellows
            to help to bully my friends. The said Bimbashee (next in rank to a Bey) a coarse man
            like an Arnoout, stopped here a day and night and played his little Turkish game,
            telling me to beware—for the Ulema hated all Franks and set the people against us—and
            telling the Arabs that Christian Hakeems were all given to poison Muslims. So at night I
            dropped in at the Maōhn’s with Sheykh Yussuf carrying my lantern—and was loudly hailed
            with a _Salaam Aleykee_ from the old Shereef himself—who began praising the Gospel I had
            given him, and me at the same time. Yussuf had a little reed in his hand—the _kalem_ for
            writing, about two feet long and of the size of a quill. I took it and showed it to the
            Bimbashee and said—‘Behold the _neboot_ wherewith we are all to be murdered by this
            Sheykh of the Religion.’ The Bimbashee’s bristly moustache bristled savagely, for he
            felt that the ‘Arab dogs’ and the Christian _khanzeereh_ (feminine pig) were laughing at
            it together. </p>
         <p> Another steam boat load of prisoners from Gau has just gone up. A little comfort is
            derived here from the news that, ‘Praise be to God, Moussa Pasha (Governor of the
            Soudan) is dead and gone to Hell.’ It must take no trifle to send him there judging by
            the quiet way in which Fadil Pasha is mentioned. </p>
         <p> You will think me a complete rebel—but I may say to you what most people would think
            ‘like my nonsense’—that one’s pity becomes a perfect passion, when one _sits among the
            people_—as I do, and sees it all; least of all can I forgive those among Europeans and
            Christians who can help to ‘break these bruised reeds.’ However, in <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> and more still in Alexandria, all is quite different.
            There, the same system which has been so successfully copied in France prevails. The
            capital is petted at the expense of the fellaheen. Prices are regulated in <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> for meat and bread as they are or were in Paris, and
            the ‘dangerous classes’ enjoy all sorts of exemptions. Just like France! The Cairenes
            eat the bread and the fellaheen eat the stick. </p>
         <p> The people here used to dislike Mounier who arrived poor and grew rich and powerful,
            but they all bless him now and say at El-Moutaneh a man eats his own meat and not the
            courbash of the Moudir—and Mounier has refused soldiers (as I refused them on my small
            account) and ‘Please God,’ he will never repent it. Yussuf says ‘What the Turkish
            Government fears is not for _your_ safety, but lest we should learn to love you too
            well,’ and it is true. Here there is but one voice. ‘Let the Franks come, let us have
            the laws of the Christians.’ </p>
         <p> In <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> the Franks have dispelled this _douce
            illusion_ and done the Turk’s work as if they were paid for it. But here come only
            travellers who pay with money and not with stick—a degree of generosity not enough to be
            adored. </p>
         <p> I perceive that I am a bore—but you will forgive my indignant sympathy with the kind
            people who treat me so well. Yussuf asked me to let the English papers know about the
            Gau business. An Alim ed Deen ul-Islam would fain call for help to the Times! Strange
            changes and signs of the times—these—are they not so? </p>
         <p> I went to Church on Good Friday with the Copts. The scene was very striking—the priest
            dressed like a beautiful Crusader in white robes with crimson crosses. One thing has my
            hearty admiration. The few children who are taken to Church are allowed to play! Oh my
            poor little Protestant fellow Christians, can you conceive a religion so delightful as
            that which permits Peep-bo behind the curtain of the sanctuary! I saw little Butrus and
            Scendariah at it all church time—and the priest only patted their little heads as he
            carried the sacrament out to the Hareem. Fancy the parson kindly patting a noisy boy’s
            head, instead of the beadle whacking him! I am entirely reconciled to the Coptic
            rules.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>