<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, CAIRO, December 17, 1863.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/22">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/360630">Cairo</settlement>
               <date when="1863-12-17">17 December 1863</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff Gordon</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK, </p>
         <p> At last I hope I shall get off in a few days. I have had one delay and bother after
            another, chiefly caused by relying on the fine speeches of Mr. D. On applying straight
            to the French Consulate at Alexandria, Janet got me the loan of the _Maison de France_
            at Thebes at once. M. Mounier, the agent to Halim Pasha, is going up to Esneh, and will
            let me travel in the steamer which is to tow his dahabieh. It will be dirty, but will
            cost little and take me out of this dreadful cold weather in five or six days. </p>
         <p> _December_ 22.—I wrote the above five days ago, since when I have had to turn out of
            Thayer’s house, as his new Vice-Consul wanted it, and am back at Briggs’. M. Mounier is
            waiting in frantic impatience to set off, and I ditto; but Ismail Pasha keeps him from
            day to day. The worry of depending on anyone in the East is beyond belief. Tell your
            mother that Lady Herbert is gone up the river; her son was much the better for
               <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>. I saw Pietro, her courier, who is
            stupendously grand, he offered Omar £8 a month to go with them; you may imagine how
            Pietro despised his heathenish ignorance in preferring to stay with me for £3. It quite
            confirmed him in his contempt for the Arabs. </p>
         <p> You would have laughed to hear me buying a carpet. I saw an old broker with one on his
            shoulder in the bazaar, and asked the price, ‘eight napoleons’—then it was unfolded and
            spread in the street, to the great inconvenience of passers-by, just in front of a
            coffee-shop. I look at it superciliously, and say, ‘Three hundred piastres, O uncle,’
            the poor old broker cries out in despair to the men sitting outside the coffee-shop: ‘O
            Muslims, hear that and look at this excellent carpet. Three hundred piastres! By the
            faith, it is worth two thousand!’ But the men take my part and one mildly says: ‘I
            wonder that an old man as thou art should tell us that this lady, who is a traveller and
            a person of experience, values it at three hundred—thinkest thou we will give thee
            more?’ Then another suggests that if the lady will consent to give four napoleons, he
            had better take them, and that settles it. Everybody gives an opinion here, and the
            price is fixed by a sort of improvised jury. </p>
         <p> _Christmas Day_.—At last my departure is fixed. I embark to-morrow afternoon at
               <placeName ref="Boulak">Boulak</placeName>, and we sail—or steam, rather—on Sunday
            morning early, and expect to reach Thebes in eight days. I heard a curious illustration
            of Arab manners to-day. I met Hassan, the janissary of the American Consulate, a very
            respectable, good man. He told me he had married another wife since last year—I asked
            what for. It was the widow of his brother who had always lived with him in the same
            house, and who died leaving two boys. She is neither young nor handsome, but he
            considered it his duty to provide for her and the children, and not to let her marry a
            stranger. So you see that polygamy is not always sensual indulgence, and a man may
            practise greater self-sacrifice so than by talking sentiment about deceased wives’
            sisters. Hassan has £3 a month, and two wives come expensive. I said, laughing, to Omar
            as we left him, that I did not think the two wives sounded very comfortable. ‘Oh no! not
            comfortable at all for the man, but he take care of the women, that’s what is
            proper—that is the good Mussulman.’ </p>
         <p> I shall have the company of a Turkish Effendi on my voyage—a Commissioner of Inland
            Revenue, in fact, going to look after the tax-gatherers in the Saeed. I wonder whether
            he will be civil. Sally is gone with some English servants out to the Virgin’s tree, the
            great picnic frolic of Cairene Christians, and, indeed, of Muslimeen also at some
            seasons. Omar is gone to a _Khatmeh_—a reading of the Koran—at Hassan the donkey-boy’s
            house. I was asked, but am afraid of the night air. A good deal of religious celebration
            goes on now, the middle of the month of Regeb, six weeks before Ramadan. I rather dread
            Ramadan as Omar is sure to be faint and ill, and everybody else cross during the first
            five days or so; then their stomachs get into training. The new passenger-steamers have
            been promised ever since the 6th, and will not now go till after the races—6th or 7th of
            next month. Fancy the <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> races! It is growing
            dreadfully Cockney here, I must go to Timbuctoo: and we are to have a railway to Mecca,
            and take return tickets for the _Haj_ from all parts of the world.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>