<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, April, 1865.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/58">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <date when="1865-04">April 1865</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff Gordon</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALEXANDER, </p>
         <p> Yesterday was the Bairam I rejoice to say and I have lots of physic to make up, for all
            the stomachs damaged by Ramadan. </p>
         <p> I have persuaded Mr. Fowler the engineer who was with Lord Dudley to take my dear
            little pupil Achmet son of Ibn Mustapha to learn the business at Leeds instead of idling
            in his father’s house here. I will give the child a letter to you in case he should go
            to London. He has been reading the gospels with me at his own desire. I refused till I
            had asked his father’s consent, and Sheykh Yussuf who heard me begged me by all means to
            make him read it carefully so as to guard him against the heretical inventions he might
            be beset with among the English ‘of the vulgar sort.’ What a poser for a missionary! </p>
         <p> I sent down the poor black lad with Arakel Bey. He took leave of me with his ugly face
            all blubbered like a sentimental hippopotamus. He said ‘for himself, he wished to stay
            with me, but then what would his boy, his little master do—there was only a stepmother
            who would take all the money, and who else would work for the boy?’ Little Achmet was
            charmed to see Khayr go, of whom he chose to be horribly jealous, and to be wroth at all
            he did for me. Now the Sheykh-el-Beled of Baidyeh has carried off my watchman, and the
            Christian Sheykh-el-Hara of our quarter of Luxor has taken the boy Yussuf for the Canal.
            The former I successfully resisted and got back Mansoor, not indeed _incolumes_ for _he_
            had been handcuffed and bastinadoed to make _me_ pay 200 piastres, but he bore it like a
            man rather than ask me for the money and was thereupon surrendered. But the Copt will be
            a tougher business—he will want more money and be more resolved to get it. _Veremus_. I
            must I suppose go to the Nazir at the Canal—a Turk—and beg off my donkey boy. </p>
         <p> [Picture: Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, from sketch by G. F. Watts, R.A.] </p>
         <p> I saw Hassan Sheykh-el-Abab’deh yesterday, who was loud in praise of your good looks
            and gracious manners. ‘Mashallah, thy master is a sweet man, O Lady!’ </p>
         <p> Yesterday was Bairam, and lots of Hareem came in their best clothes to wish me a happy
            year and enjoyed themselves much with sweet cakes, coffee, and pipes. Kursheed’s wife
            (whom I cured completely) looked very handsome. Kursheed is a Circassian, a fine young
            fellow much shot and hacked about and with a Crimean medal. He is cawass here and a
            great friend of mine. He says if I ever want a servant he will go with me anywhere and
            fight anybody—which I don’t doubt in the least. He was a Turkish memlook and his
            condescension in wishing to serve a Christian woman is astounding. His fair face and
            clear blue eyes, and brisk, neat, soldier-like air contrast curiously with the brown
            fellaheen. He is like an Englishman only fairer and like them too fond of the courbash.
            What would you say if I appeared in Germany attended by a memlook with pistols, sword,
            dagger, carbine and courbash, and with a decided and imperious manner the very reverse
            of the Arab softness—and such a Muslim too—prays five times a day and extra fasts
            besides Ramadan. ‘I beat my wife’ said Kursheed, ‘oh! I beat her well! she talked so,
            and I am like the English, I don’t like too many words.’ He was quite surprised that I
            said I was glad _my_ master didn’t dislike talking so much. </p>
         <p> I was talking the other day with Yussuf about people trying to make converts and I said
            that eternal bêtise, ‘Oh they mean well.’ ‘True, oh Lady! perhaps they do mean well, but
            God says in the Noble Koran that he who injures or torments those Christians whose
            conduct is not evil, merely on account of religion, shall never smell the fragrance of
            the Garden (paradise). Now when men begin to want to make others change their faith it
            is extremely hard for them _not_ to injure or torment them and therefore I think it
            better to abstain altogether and to wish rather to see a Christian a good Christian and
            a Muslim a good Muslim.’ </p>
         <p> No wonder a most pious old Scotchman told me that the truth which undeniably existed in
            the Mussulman faith was the work of Satan and the Ulema his _meenesters_. My dear saint
            of a Yussuf a _meenester_ of Satan! I really think I _have_ learnt some ‘Muslim
            humility’ in that I endured the harangue, and accepted a two-penny tract quite mildly
            and politely and didn’t argue at all. As his friend ‘Satan’ would have it, the Fikees
            were reading the Koran in the hall at Omar’s expense who gave a Khatmeh that day, and
            Omar came in and politely offered him some sweet prepared for the occasion. I have been
            really amazed at several instances of English fanaticism this year. Why do people come
            to a Mussulman country with such bitter hatred ‘in their stomachs’ as I have seen three
            or four times. I feel quite hurt often at the way the people here thank me for what the
            poor at home would turn up their noses at. I think hardly a dragoman has been up the
            river since Rashedee died but has come to thank me as warmly as if I had done himself
            some great service—and many to give some little present. While the man was ill numbers
            of the fellaheen brought eggs, pigeons, etc. etc. even a turkey, and food is worth money
            now, not as it used to be. I am quite weary too of hearing ‘Of all the Frangee I never
            saw one like thee.’ Was no one ever at all humane before? For remember I give no
            money—only a little physic and civility. How the British cottagers would ‘thank ye for
            nothing’—and how I wish my neighbours here could afford to do the same. </p>
         <p> After much wrangling Mustapha has got back my boy Yussuf but the Christian
            Sheykh-el-Hara has made his brother pay £2 whereat Mohammed looks very rueful. Two
            hundred men are gone out of our village to the works and of course the poor Hareem have
            not bread to eat as the men had to take all they had with them. I send you a very pretty
            story like Tannhäuser. </p>
         <p> There was once a man who loved a woman that lived in the same quarter. But she was true
            to her husband, and his love was hopeless, and he suffered greatly. One day as he lay on
            his carpet sick with love, one came to him and said, O, such-a-one, thy beloved has died
            even now, and they are carrying her out to the tomb. So the lover arose and followed the
            funeral, and hid himself near the tomb, and when all were gone he broke it open, and
            uncovered the face of his beloved, and looked upon her, and passion overcame him, and he
            took from the dead that which when living she had ever denied him. </p>
         <p> But he went back to the city and to his house in great grief and anguish of mind, and
            his sin troubled him. So he went to a Kadee, very pious and learned in the noble Koran,
            and told him his case, and said, ‘Oh my master the Kadee, can such a one as I obtain
            salvation and the forgiveness of God? I fear not.’ And the Kadee gave him a staff of
            polished wood which he held in his hand, and said ‘Who knoweth the mercy of God and his
            justice, but God alone—take then this staff and stick it in the sand beside the tomb
            where thou didst sin and leave it the night, and go next morning and come and tell me
            what thou shalt find, and may the Lord pardon thee, for thy sin is great.’ </p>
         <p> And the man went and did as the Kadee had desired, and went again at sunrise, and
            behold the staff had sprouted and was covered with leaves and fruit. And he returned and
            told the Kadee what had happened, and the Kadee replied, ‘Praise be to God, the
            merciful, the compassionate.’</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>