<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Mrs. Austin. FESHN, Monday, November 30, 1862.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/3">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/361329">Al Fashn</settlement>
               <date when="1862-11-30">30 November 1862</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/59830344">Sarah Austin</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p> </p>
         <p> DEAREST MUTTER, </p>
         <p> I have now been enjoying this most delightful way of life for ten days, and am
            certainly much better. I begin to eat and sleep again, and cough less. My crew are a
            great amusement to me. They are mostly men from near the first Cataract above Assouan,
            sleek-skinned, gentle, patient, merry black fellows. The little black Reis is the very
            picture of good-nature and full of fun, ‘chaffing’ the girls as we pass the villages,
            and always smiling. The steersman is of lighter complexion, also very cheery, but
            decidedly pious. He prays five times a day and utters ejaculations to the apostle Rusool
            continually. He hurt his ankle on one leg and his instep on the other with a rusty nail,
            and they festered. I dressed them with poultices, and then with lint and strapping, with
            perfect success, to the great admiration of all hands, and he announced how much better
            he felt, ‘Alhamdulillah, kieth-el-hairack khateer ya Sitti’ (Praise be to God and thanks
            without end O Lady), and everyone echoed, ‘kieth-el-hairack khateer.’ The most important
            person is the ‘weled’—boy—Achmet. The most merry, clever, omnipresent little rascal,
            with an ugly little pug face, a shape like an antique Cupid, liberally displayed, and a
            skin of dark brown velvet. His voice, shrill and clear, is always heard foremost; he
            cooks for the crew, he jumps overboard with the rope and gives advice on all occasions,
            grinds the coffee with the end of a stick in a mortar, which he holds between his feet,
            and uses the same large stick to walk proudly before me, brandishing it if I go ashore
            for a minute, and ordering everybody out of the way. ‘Ya Achmet!’ resounds all day
            whenever anybody wants anything, and the ‘weled’ is always ready and able. My favourite
            is Osman, a tall, long-limbed black who seems to have stepped out of a hieroglyphical
            drawing, shirt, skull-cap and all. He has only those two garments, and how anyone
            contrives to look so inconceivably ‘neat and respectable’ (as Sally truly remarked) in
            that costume is a mystery. He is always at work, always cheerful, but rather silent—in
            short, the able seaman and steady, respectable ‘hand’ _par excellence_. Then we have El
            Zankalonee from near <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>, an old fellow of white
            complexion and a valuable person, an inexhaustible teller of stories at night and always
            _en train_, full of jokes and remarkable for a dry humour much relished by the crew. I
            wish I understood the stories, which sound delightful, all about Sultans and Efreets,
            with effective ‘points,’ at which all hands exclaim ‘Mashallah!’ or ‘Ah!’ (as long as
            you can drawl it). The jokes, perhaps, I may as well be ignorant of. There is a certain
            Shereef who does nothing but laugh and work and be obliging; helps Omar with one hand
            and Sally with the other, and looks like a great innocent black child. The rest of the
            dozen are of various colours, sizes and ages, some quite old, but all very quiet and
            well-behaved. </p>
         <p> We have had either dead calm or contrary wind all the time and the men have worked very
            hard at the tow-rope. On Friday I proclaimed a halt in the afternoon at a village at
            prayer-time for the pious Muslims to go to the mosque; this gave great satisfaction,
            though only five went, Reis, steersman, Zankalonee and two old men. The up-river men
            never pray at all, and Osman occupied himself by buying salt out of another boat and
            stowing it away to take up to his family, as it is terribly dear high up the river. At
            Benisouef we halted to buy meat and bread, it is _comme qui dirait_ an assize town,
            there is one butcher who kills one sheep a day. I walked about the streets escorted by
            Omar in front and two sailors with huge staves behind, and created a sensation
            accordingly. It is a dull little country town with a wretched palace of Said Pasha. On
            Sunday we halted at Bibbeh, where I caught sight of a large Coptic church and sallied
            forth to see whether they would let me in. The road lay past the house of the headman of
            the village, and there ‘in the gate’ sat a patriarch, surrounded by his servants and his
            cattle. Over the gateway were crosses and queer constellations of dots, more like
            Mithraic symbols than anything Christian, but Girgis was a Copt, though the chosen head
            of the Muslim village. He rose as I came up, stepped out and salaamed, then took my hand
            and said I must go into his house before I saw the church and enter the hareem. His old
            mother, who looked a hundred, and his pretty wife, were very friendly; but, as I had to
            leave Omar at the door, our talk soon came to an end, and Girgis took me out into the
            divan, without the sacred precincts of the hareem. Of course we had pipes and coffee,
            and he pressed me to stay some days, to eat with him every day and to accept all his
            house contained. I took the milk he offered, and asked him to visit me in the boat,
            saying I must return before sunset when it gets cold, as I was ill. The house was a
            curious specimen of a wealthy man’s house—I could not describe it if I tried, but I felt
            I was acting a passage of the Old Testament. We went to the church, which outside looked
            like nine beehives in a box. Inside, the nine domes resting on square pillars were very
            handsome. Girgis was putting it into thorough repair at his own expense, and it will
            cost a good deal, I think, to repair and renew the fine old wood panelling of such
            minute and intricate workmanship. The church is divided by three screens; one in front
            of the eastern three domes is impervious and conceals the holy of holies. He opened the
            horseshoe door for me to look in, but explained that no Hareem might cross the
            threshold. All was in confusion owing to the repairs which were actively going on
            without the slightest regard to Sunday; but he took up a large bundle, kissed it, and
            showed it me. What it contained I cannot guess, and I scrupled to inquire through a
            Muslim interpreter. To the right of this sanctum is the tomb of a Muslim saint! enclosed
            under the adjoining dome. Here we went in and Girgis kissed the tomb on one side while
            Omar salaamed it on the other—a pleasant sight. They were much more particular about our
            shoes than in the mosques. Omar wanted to tie handkerchiefs over my boots like at
               <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>, but the priest objected and made me take
            them off and march about in the brick and mortar rubbish in my stockings. I wished to
            hear the service, but it was not till sunset, and, as far as I could make out, not
            different on Sunday to other days. The Hareems are behind the screen furthest removed
            from the holy screen, behind a third screen where also was the font, locked up and
            shaped like a Muslim tomb in little. (Hareem is used here just like the German
            _Frauenzimmer_, to mean a respectable woman. Girgis spoke of me to Omar as ‘Hareem.’)
            The Copts have but one wife, but they shut her up much closer than the Arabs. The
            children were sweetly pretty, so unlike the Arab brats, and the men very good-looking.
            They did not seem to acknowledge me at all as a _co-religionnaire_, and asked whether we
            of the English religion did not marry our brothers and sisters.</p>
         <p>The priest then asked me to drink coffee at his house close by, and there I ‘sat in the
            gate’—_i.e._, in a large sort of den raised 2 feet from the ground and matted, to the
            left of the gate. A crowd of Copts collected and squatted about, and we were joined by
            the mason who was repairing the church, a fine, burly, rough-bearded old Mussulman, who
            told how the Sheykh buried in the church of Bibbeh had appeared to him three nights
            running at <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> and ordered him to leave his work
            and go to Bibbeh and mend his church, and how he came and offered to do so without pay
            if the Copts would find the materials. He spoke with evident pride, as one who had
            received a Divine command, and the Copts all confirmed the story and everyone was highly
            gratified by the miracle. I asked Omar if he thought it was all true, and he had no
            doubt of it. The mason he knew to be a respectable man in full work, and Girgis added
            that he had tried to get a man to come for years for the purpose without success. It is
            not often that a dead saint contrives to be equally agreeable to Christians and
            Mussulmans, and here was the staunch old ‘true believer’ working away in the sanctuary
            which they would not allow an English fellow-Christian to enter.</p>
         <p> Whilst we sat hearing all these wonders, the sheep and cattle pushed in between us,
            coming home at eve. The venerable old priest looked so like Father Abraham, and the
            whole scene was _so_ pastoral and Biblical that I felt quite as if my wish was fulfilled
            to live a little a few thousands of years ago. They wanted me to stay many days, and
            then Girgis said I must stop at Feshn where he had a fine house and garden, and he would
            go on horseback and meet me there, and would give me a whole troop of Fellaheen to pull
            the boat up quick. Omar’s eyes twinkled with fun as he translated this, and said he knew
            the Sitt would cry out, as she always did about the Fellaheen, as if she were hurt
            herself. He told Girgis that the English customs did not allow people to work without
            pay, which evidently seemed very absurd to the whole party.</p>
         <p>GEBEL SHEYK EMBARAK, _Thursday_.</p>
         <p> I stopped last night at Feshn, but finding this morning that my Coptic friends were not
            expected till the afternoon, I would not spend the whole day, and came on still against
            wind and stream. If I could speak Arabic I should have enjoyed a few days with Girgis
            and his family immensely, to learn their _Ansichten_ a little; but Omar’s English is too
            imperfect to get beyond elementary subjects. The thing that strikes me most is the
            tolerant spirit that I see everywhere. They say ‘Ah! it is your custom,’ and express no
            sort of condemnation, and Muslims and Christians appear perfectly good friends, as my
            story of Bibbeh goes to prove. I have yet to see the much-talked-of fanaticism, at
            present I have not met with a symptom of it. There were thirteen Copt families at Bibbeh
            and a considerable Muslim population, who had elected Girgis their headman and kissed
            his hand very heartily as our procession moved through the streets. Omar said he was a
            very good man and much liked.</p>
         <p>The villages look like slight elevations in the mud banks cut into square shapes. The
            best houses have neither paint, whitewash, plaster, bricks nor windows, nor any visible
            roofs. They don’t give one the notion of human dwellings at all at first, but soon the
            eye gets used to the absence of all that constitutes a house in Europe, the impression
            of wretchedness wears off, and one sees how picturesque they are, with palm-trees and
            tall pigeon-houses, and here and there the dome over a saint’s tomb. The men at work on
            the river-banks are exactly the same colour as the Nile mud, with just the warmer hue of
            the blood circulating beneath the skin. Prometheus has just formed them out of the
            universal material at hand, and the sun breathed life into them. Poor fellows—even the
            boatmen, ragged crew as they are—say ‘Ah, Fellaheen!’ with a contemptuous pity when they
            see me watch the villagers at work.</p>
         <p>The other day four huge barges passed us towed by a steamer and crammed with hundreds of
            the poor souls torn from their homes to work at the Isthmus of Suez, or some palace of
            the Pasha’s, for a nominal piastre a day, and find their own bread and water and cloak.
            One of my crew, Andrasool, a black savage whose function is always to jump overboard
            whenever the rope gets entangled or anything is wanted, recognised some relations of his
            from a village close to Assouan. There was much shouting and poor Andrasool looked very
            mournful all day. It may be his turn next. Some of the crew disloyally remarked that
            they were sure the men there wished they were working for a Sitti Ingleez, as Andrasool
            told them he was. Think too what splendid pay it must be that the boat-owner can give
            out of £25 a month to twelve men, after taking his own profits, the interest of money
            being enormous.</p>
         <p>When I call my crew black, don’t think of negroes. They are elegantly-shaped Arabs and
            all gentlemen in manners, and the black is transparent, with amber _reflets_ under it in
            the sunshine; a negro looks _blue_ beside them. I have learned a great deal that is
            curious from Omar’s confidences, who tells me his family affairs and talks about the
            women of his family, which he would not to a man. He refused to speak to his brother, a
            very grand dragoman, who was with the Prince of Wales, and who came up to us in the
            hotel at <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> and addressed Omar, who turned his
            back on him. I asked the reason, and Omar told me how his brother had a wife, ‘An old
            wife, been with him long time, very good wife.’ She had had three children—all dead. All
            at once the dragoman, who is much older than Omar, declared he would divorce her and
            marry a young woman. Omar said, ‘No, don’t do that; keep her in your house as head of
            your home, and take one of your two black slave girls as your Hareem.’ But the other
            insisted, and married a young Turkish wife; whereupon Omar took his poor old
            sister-in-law to live with him and his own young wife, and cut his grand brother dead.
            See how characteristic!—the urging his brother to take the young slave girl ‘as his
            Hareem,’ like a respectable man—that would have been all right; but what he did was ‘not
            good.’ I’ll trouble you (as Mrs. Grote used to say) to settle these questions to
            everyone’s satisfaction. I own Omar seemed to me to take a view against which I had
            nothing to say. His account of his other brother, a confectioner’s household with two
            wives, was very curious. He and they, with his wife and sister-in-law, all live
            together, and one of the brother’s wives has six children—three sleep with their own
            mother and three with their _other_ mother—and all is quite harmonious.</p>
         <p>SIOUT, _December_ 10.</p>
         <p>I could not send a letter from Minieh, where we stopped, and I visited a sugar
            manufactory and a gentlemanly Turk, who superintended the district, the Moudir. I heard
            a boy singing a _Zikr_ (the ninety-nine attributes of God) to a set of dervishes in a
            mosque, and I think I never heard anything more beautiful and affecting. Ordinary Arab
            singing is harsh and nasal, but it can be wonderfully moving. Since we left Minieh we
            have suffered dreadfully from the cold; the chickens died of it, and the Arabs look blue
            and pinched. Of course it is _my weather_ and there never was such cold and such
            incessant contrary winds known. To-day was better, and Wassef, a Copt here, lent me his
            superb donkey to go up to the tomb in the mountain. The tomb is a mere cavern, so
            defaced, but the view of beautiful Siout standing in the midst of a loop of the Nile was
            ravishing. A green deeper and brighter than England, graceful minarets in crowds, a
            picturesque bridge, gardens, palm-trees, then the river beyond it, the barren yellow
            cliffs as a frame all around that. At our feet a woman was being carried to the grave,
            and the boys’ voices rang out the Koran full and clear as the long procession—first
            white turbans and then black veils and robes—wound along. It is all a dream to me. You
            can’t think what an odd effect it is to take up an English book and read it and then
            look up and hear the men cry, ‘Yah Mohammad.’ ‘Bless thee, Bottom, how art thou
            translated;’ it is the reverse of all one’s former life when one sat in England and read
            of the East. ‘_Und nun sitz ich mitten drein_’ in the real, true Arabian Nights, and
            don’t know whether ‘I be I as I suppose I be’ or not.</p>
         <p>Tell Alick the news, for I have not written to any but you. I do so long for my Rainie.
            The little Copt girls are like her, only pale; but they don’t let you admire them for
            fear of the evil-eye.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>