<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, LUXOR, December 31, 1886.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/91">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <date when="1866-12-31">31 December 1866</date>
               <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/360502">Luxor</settlement>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff Gordon</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK, </p>
         <p> I meant to have sent you a long yarn by a steamer which went the other day, but I have
            been in my bed. The weather set in colder than I ever felt it here, and I have been very
            unwell for some time. Dr. Osman Ibraheem (a friend of mine, an elderly man who studied
            in Paris in Mohammed Ali’s time) wants me to spend the summer up here and take sand
            baths, _i.e._ bury myself up to the chin in the hot sand, and to get a Dongola slave to
            rub me. A most fascinating derweesh from Esneh gave me the same advice; he wanted me to
            go and live near him at Esneh, and let him treat me. I wish you could see Sheykh Seleem,
            he is a sort of remnant of the Memlook Beys—a Circassian—who has inherited his master’s
            property up at Esneh, and married his master’s daughter. The master was one of the Beys,
            also a slave inheriting from his master. Well after being a terrible _Shaitan_ (devil)
            after drink, women, etc. Seleem has repented and become a man of pilgrimage and prayer
            and perpetual fasting; but he has retained the exquisite grace and charm of manner which
            must have made him irresistible in his _shaitan_ days, and also the beautifully delicate
            style of dress—a dove-coloured cloth _sibbeh_ over a pale blue silk _kuftan_, a turban
            like a snow-drift, under which flowed the silky fair hair and beard, and the dainty
            white hands under the long muslin shirt sleeve made a picture; and such a smile, and
            such ready graceful talk. Sheykh Yussuf brought him to me as a sort of doctor, and also
            to try and convert me on one point. Some Christians had made Yussuf quite miserable, by
            telling him of the doctrine that all unbaptized infants went to eternal fire; and as he
            knew that I had lost a child very young, it weighed on his mind that perhaps I fretted
            about this, and so he said he could not refrain from trying to convince me that God was
            not so cruel and unjust as the Nazarene priests represented Him, and that all infants
            whatsoever, as well as all ignorant persons, were to be saved. ‘Would that I could take
            the cruel error out of the minds of all the hundreds and thousands of poor Christian
            mothers who must be tortured by it,’ said he, ‘and let them understand that their dead
            babies are with Him who sent and who took them.’ I own I did not resent this
            interference with my orthodoxy, especially as it is the only one I ever knew Yussuf
            attempt. </p>
         <p> Dr. Osman is a lecturer in the <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> school of
            medicine, a Shereef, and eminently a gentleman. He came up in the passenger steamer and
            called on me and spent all his spare time with me. I liked him better than the
            bewitching derweesh Seleem; he is so like my old love Don Quixote. He was amazed and
            delighted at what he heard here about me. ‘_Ah Madame, on vous aime comme une sœur, et
            on vous respecte comme une reine; cela rejouit le cœur des honnêtes gens de voir tous
            les préjugés oubliés et détruits à ce point_.’ We had no end of talk. Osman is the only
            Arab I know who has read a good deal of European literature and history and is able to
            draw comparisons. He said, ‘_Vous seule dans toute l’Egypte connaissez le peuple et
            comprenez ce qui se passe, tous les autres Européens ne savent absolument rien que les
            dehors; il n’y a que vous qui ayez inspiré la confiance qu’il faut pour connaître la
            vénté_.’ Of course this is between ourselves, I tell you, but I don’t want to boast of
            the kind thoughts people have of me, simply because I am decently civil to them. </p>
         <p> In Egypt we are eaten up with taxes; there is not a penny left to anyone. The taxes for
            the whole year _eight months in advance_ have been levied, as far as they can be beaten
            out of the miserable people. I saw one of the poor dancing girls the other day, (there
            are three in Luxor) and she told me how cruel the new tax on them is. It is left to the
            discretion of the official who farms it to make each woman pay according to her presumed
            gains, _i.e._ her good looks, and thus the poor women are exposed to all the caprices
            and extortions of the police. This last new tax has excited more disgust than any. ‘We
            now know the name of our ruler,’ said a fellah who had just heard of it, ‘he is _Mawas_
            Pasha.’ I won’t translate—but it is a terrible epithet when uttered in a tone which
            gives it the true meaning, though in a general way the commonest word of abuse to a
            donkey, or a boy, or any other cattle. The wages of prostitution are unclean, and this
            tax renders all Government salaries unlawful according to strict law. The capitation tax
            too, which was remitted for three years on the pasha’s accession to the people of
               <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>, Alexandria, Damietta and Rascheed, is now
            called for. Omar will have to pay about £8 back tax, which he had fondly imagined
            himself excused from. You may conceive the distress this must cause among artisans,
            etc., who have spent their money and forgotten it, and feel cheated out of the blessings
            they then bestowed on the Pasha—as to that they will take out the change in curses. </p>
         <p> There was a meeting here the other day of the Kadee, Sheykh el-Beled, and other
            notables to fix the amount of tax each man was to pay towards the increased police tax;
            and the old Shereef at the end spoke up, and said he had heard that one man had asked me
            to lend him money, and that he hoped such a thing would not happen again. Everyone knew
            I had had heavy expenses this year, and most likely had not much money; that my heart
            was soft, and that as everyone was in distress it would be ‘breaking my head,’ and in
            short that he should think it unmanly if anyone tried to trouble a lone woman with his
            troubles. I did offer one man £2 that he might not be forced to run away to the desert,
            but he refused it and said, ‘I had better go at once and rob out there, and not turn
            rogue towards thee—never could I repay it.’ The people are running away in all
            directions. </p>
         <p> When the Moolid of the Sheykh came the whole family Abu-l-Hajjaj could only raise six
            hundred and twenty piastres among them to buy the buffalo cow, which by custom—strong as
            the laws of the Medes and Persians—must be killed for the strangers who come; and a
            buffalo cow is worth one thousand piastres. So the stout old Shereef (aged 87) took his
            staff and the six hundred and twenty piastres, and sallied forth to walk to Erment and
            see what God would send them; and a charitable woman in Erment did give a buffalo cow
            for the six hundred and twenty piastres, and he drove her home the twenty miles
            rejoicing. </p>
         <p> There has been a burglary over at Gourneh, an unheard-of event. Some men broke into the
            house of the Coptic _gabit_ (tax-gatherer) and stole the money-box containing about
            sixty purses—over £150. The _gabit_ came to me sick with the fright which gave him
            jaundice, and about eight men are gone in chains to Keneh on suspicion. Hajjee Baba too,
            a Turkish cawass, is awfully bilious; he says he is ‘sick from beating men, and it’s no
            use, you can’t coin money on their backs and feet when they haven’t a para in the
            world.’ Altogether everyone is gloomy, and many desperate. I never saw the aspect of a
            population so changed. </p>
         <p> January 1, 1867. God bless you, dearest Alick, and grant you many good years more. I
            must finish this to go to-morrow by the steamer. I would give a great deal to see you
            again, but when will that be?</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>