<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, LUXOR, January 12, 1867.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/92">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <date when="1867-01-12">12 January 1867</date>
               <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/360502">Luxor</settlement>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff Gordon</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK, </p>
         <p> Only two days ago I received letters from you of the 17 September and the 19 November.
            I wonder how many get lost and where? Janet gives me hopes of a visit of a few days in
            March and promises me a little terrier dog, whereat Omar is in raptures. I have made no
            plans at all, never having felt well enough to hope to be able to travel. The weather
            has changed for the better, and it is not at all old now; we shall see what the warmth
            does for me. You make my bowels yearn with your account of Rainie. If only we had Prince
            Achmet’s carpet, and you could all come here for a few months. </p>
         <p> We were greatly excited here last week; a boy was shot out in the sugar-cane field: he
            was with four Copts, and at first it looked ugly for the Copts. But the Maōhn tells me
            he is convinced they are innocent, and that they only prevaricated from fear—it was
            robbers shot the poor child. What struck and surprised me in the affair was the
            excessive horror and consternation it produced; the Maōhn had not had a murder in his
            district at all in eight years. The market-place was thronged with wailing women, Omar
            was sick all day, and the Maōhn pale and wretched. The horror of killing seems greater
            here than ever I saw it. Palgrave says the same of the Arabian Arabs in his book: it is
            not one’s notion of Oriental feeling, but a murder in England is taken quite as a joke
            compared with the scene here. I fear there will be robberies, owing to the distress, and
            the numbers who are running away from the land unable to pay their taxes. Don’t fear for
            me, for I have two watchmen in the house every night—the regular guard and an amateur, a
            man whose boy I took down to <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> to study in Gama’l
            Azhar. </p>
         <p> Palgrave has written to Ross wanting Mabrook back. I am very sorry, the more so as
            Mabrook is recalcitrant. ‘I want to stay with thee, I don’t want to go back to the
            Nazarene.’ A boy who heard him said, ‘but the Lady is a Nazarene too;’ whereupon Mabrook
            slapped his face with great vigour. He will be troublesome if he does turn restive, and
            he is one who can only be managed by kindness. He is as good and quiet as possible with
            us, but the stubborn will is there and he is too ignorant to be reasoned with. </p>
         <p> _January_ 14.—To-day the four Copts have again changed their story, and after swearing
            that the robbers were strangers, have accused a man who has shot birds for me all this
            winter: and the poor devil is gone to Keneh in chains. The weather seems to have set in
            steadily for fine. I hope soon to get out, but my donkey has grown old and shaky and I
            am too weak to walk, so I sit in the balcony.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>