<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, CAIRO, November 14, 1863.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/18">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/360630">Cairo</settlement>
               <date when="1863-11-14">14 November 1863</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff Gordon</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Here I am at last in my old quarters at Thayer’s house, after a tiresome negotiation
            with the Vice-Consul, who had taken possession and invented the story of women on the
            ground-floor. I was a week in Briggs’ damp house, and too ill to write. The morning I
            arrived at <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> I was seized with hæmorrhage, and
            had two days of it; however, since then I am better. I was very foolish to stay a
            fortnight in Alexandria.</p>

         <p>The passage under the railway-bridge at Tantah (which is only opened once in two days)
            was most exciting and pretty. Such a scramble and dash of boats—two or three hundred at
            least. Old Zedan, the steersman, slid under the noses of the big boats with my little
            _Cangia_ and through the gates before they were well open, and we saw the rush and
            confusion behind us at our ease, and headed the whole fleet for a few miles. Then we
            stuck, and Zedan raged; but we got off in an hour and again overtook and passed all. And
            then we saw the spectacle of devastation—whole villages gone, submerged and melted, mud
            to mud, and the people with their animals encamped on spits of sand or on the dykes in
            long rows of ragged makeshift tents, while we sailed over where they had lived. Cotton
            rotting in all directions and the dry tops crackling under the bows of the boat. When we
            stopped to buy milk, the poor woman exclaimed: ‘Milk! from where? Do you want it out of
            my breasts?’ However, she took our saucepan and went to get some from another family. No
            one refuses it if they have a drop left, for they all believe the murrain to be a
            punishment for churlishness to strangers—by whom committed no one can say. Nor would
            they fix a price, or take more than the old rate. But here everything has doubled in
            price.</p>

         <p>Never did a present give such pleasure as Mme. De Leo’s bracelet. De Leo came quite
            overflowing with gratitude at my having remembered such a trifle as his attending me and
            coming three times a day! He thinks me looking better, and advises me to stay on here
            till I feel it cold. Mr. Thayer’s underling has been doing Levantine rogueries, selling
            the American protégé’s claims to the Egyptian Government, and I witnessed a curious
            phase of Eastern life. Omar, when he found him in _my_ house, went and ordered him out.
            I was ill in bed, and knew nothing till it was done, and when I asked Omar how he came
            to do it, he told me to be civil to him if I saw him as it was not for me to know what
            he was; that was his (Omar’s) business. At the same time Mr. Thayer’s servant sent him a
            telegram so insolent that it amounted to a kicking. Such is the Nemesis for being a
            rogue here. The servants know you, and let you feel it. I was quite ‘flabbergasted’ at
            Omar, who is so reverential to me and to the Rosses, and who I fancied trembled before
            every European, taking such a tone to a man in the position of a ‘gentleman.’ It is a
            fresh proof of the feeling of actual equality among men that lies at the bottom of such
            great inequality of position. Hekekian Bey has seen a Turkish Pasha’s shins kicked by
            his own servants, who were cognizant of his misdeeds. Finally, on Thursday we got the
            keys of the house, and Omar came with two _ferashes_ and shovelled out the Levantine
            dirt, and scoured and scrubbed; and on Friday afternoon (yesterday) we came in. Zeyneb
            has been very good ever since she has been with us, she will soon be a complete
            ‘dragowoman,’ for she is learning Arabic from Omar and English from us fast. In Janet’s
            house she only heard a sort of ‘lingua franca’ of Greek, Italian, Nubian and English.
            She asked me ‘How piccolo bint?’ (How’s the little girl?) a fine specimen of
            Alexandrian. Ross is here, and will dine with me to-night before starting by an express
            train which Ismail Pasha gives him.</p>

         <p>On Thursday evening I rode to the Abbassieh, and met all the schoolboys going home for
            their Friday. Such a pretty sight! The little Turks on grand horses with velvet
            trappings and two or three sais running before them, and the Arab boys fetched—some by
            proud fathers on handsome donkeys, some by trusty servants on foot, some by poor mothers
            astride on shabby donkeys and taking up their darlings before them, some two and three
            on one donkey, and crowds on foot. Such a number of lovely faces—all dressed in white
            European-cut clothes and red tarbooshes.</p>

         <p>Last night we had a wedding opposite. A pretty boy, about Maurice’s size, or rather
            less, with a friend of his own size, dressed like him in a scarlet robe and turban, on
            each side, and surrounded by men carrying tapers and singing songs, and preceded by
            cressets flaring. He stepped along like Agag, very slowly and mincingly, and looked very
            shy and pretty. My poor Hassan (donkey-driver) is ill—I fear very ill. His father came
            with the donkey for me, and kept drawing his sleeve over his eyes and sighing so
            heavily. ‘_Yah Hassan meskeen_! _yah Hassan ibn_!’ (Oh poor Hassan! oh Hassan my son!);
            and then, in a resigned tone, ‘_Allah kereem_’ (God is merciful). I will go and see him
            this morning, and have a doctor to him ‘by force,’ as Omar says, if he is very bad.
            There is something heart-rending in the patient, helpless suffering of these people.</p>

         <p>_Sunday_.—Abu Hassan reported his son so much better that I did not go after him, having
            several things to do, and Omar being deep in cooking a _festin de Balthazar_ because
            Ross was to dine with me. The weather is delicious—much what we had at Bournemouth in
            summer—but there is a great deal of sickness, and I fear there will be more, from people
            burying dead cattle on their premises inside the town. It costs 100 _gersh_ to bury one
            outside the town. All labour is rendered scarce, too, as well as food dear, and the
            streets are not cleaned and water hard to get. My _sakka_ comes very irregularly, and
            makes quite a favour of supplying us with water. All this must tell heavily on the poor.
            Hekekian’s wife had seventy head of cattle on her farm—one wretched bullock is left;
            and, of seven to water the house in <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>, also one
            left, and that expected to die. I wonder what ill-conditioned fellow of a Moses is at
            the bottom of it. Hajjee Ali has just been here, and offers me his tents if I like to go
            up to Thebes and not live in a boat, so that I may not be dependent on getting a house
            there. He is engaged by Lady Herbert of Lea, so will not go to Syria this year and has
            all his tents to spare. I fancy I might be very comfortable among the tombs of the Kings
            or in the valley of Assaseef with good tents. It is never cold at all among the hills at
            Thebes—_au contraire_. On the sunny side of the valley you are broiled and stunned with
            heat in January, and in the shade it is heavenly. How I do wish you could come too, how
            you would enjoy it! I shall rather like the change from a boat life to a Bedawee one,
            with my own sheep and chickens and horse about the tent, and a small following of ragged
            retainers; moreover, it will be considerably cheaper, I think.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>