<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, Tuesday, March 6, 1866.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/73">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <date when="1866-03-06">6 March 1866</date>
               <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/360502">Luxor</settlement>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff Gordon</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK, </p>
         <p> I write to be ready for the last _down_ steamer which will be here in a few days. Mr.
            and Miss North are here working hard at sketching, and M. Brune will take a place in
            their Dahabieh (my old Zint el Bahreyn), and leave me in six or seven days. I shall
            quite grieve to lose his company. If ever you or yours fall in with him, pray cultivate
            his acquaintance, he is very clever, very hard working, and a ‘thorough-bred gentleman’
            as Omar declares. We are quite low-spirited at parting after a month spent together at
            Thebes. </p>
         <p> I hear that Olagnier has a big house in Old <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>
            and will lodge me. The Norths go to-day (Thursday) and M. Brune does not go with them as
            he intended, but will stay on and finish a good stroke of work and take his chance of a
            conveyance. </p>
         <p> I spent yesterday out in Mustapha’s tent among the bean gatherers, and will go again. I
            think it does me good and is not too long a ride. The weather has set in suddenly very
            hot, which rather tries everybody, but gloriously fine clear air. I hope you will get
            this, as old fat Hassan will take it to the office in <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> himself—for the post is very insecure indeed. I have written very
            often, if you don’t get my letters I suppose they interest the court of Pharaoh. </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>