<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Mrs. Austin, CAIRO, December 5, 1865.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/65">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <date when="1865-12-05">5 December 1865</date>
               <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/360630">Cairo</settlement>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/59830344">Sarah Austin</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST MUTTER, </p>
         <p> _Alhamdulillah_—now I am at rest. I have got all the boat in order. My captain, Reis
            Mohammed, is very satisfactory, and to-day we sail as soon as Omar comes back with the
            meat, etc. from market. </p>
         <p> I received Meadow’s review; I wish he had not said so much about me in it. </p>
         <p> Mohammed Gazowee begs to give his best Salaam to Sheykh Stanley whom he longs to see
            again. He says that all the people said he was not a Christian, for he was not proud
            ever towards them as Christians are, but a real Sheykh, and that the Bedaween still talk
            of Sheykh Stanley and of his piety. The old half-witted jester of Luxor has found me
            out—he has wandered down here to see his eldest son who is serving in the army. He had
            brought a little boy with him, but is ‘afraid for him’ here, I don’t know why, and has
            begged me to take the child up to his mother. These licensed _possenreisser_ are like
            our fools in old times—but less witty than we fancy them to have been—thanks to
            Shakespeare, I suppose. Each district has one who attends all _moolids_ and other
            gatherings of the people, and picks up a living. He tells me that the Turkish Názir of
            Zeneea has begun some business against our Kadee, Sheykh Ibraheem, and Sheykh Yussuf,
            accused them of something—he does not know what—_perhaps of being friends of Hajjee
            Sultan, or of stealing wood_!! If all the friends of Hajjee Sultan are to be prosecuted
            that will include the whole Saeed. </p>
         <p> Of course I am anxious about my friends. All Haleem Pasha Oghdee’s villages have been
            confiscated (those tributary to him for work) _sous prétexte_ that he ill-used the
            people, _n.b._ he alone paid them—a bad example. Pharoah is indeed laying intolerable
            burthens—not on the Israelites—but on the fellaheen. </p>
         <p> Omar said of the great dinner to-day, ‘I think all the food will taste of blood, it is
            the blood of the poor, and more _haram_ than any pork or wine or blood of beasts.’ Of
            course such sentiments are not to be repeated—but they are general. The _meneggets_ who
            picked and made ten mattrasses and fourteen cushions for me in half a day, were laughing
            and saying, ‘for the Pasha’s boat we work also, at so much a day and we should have done
            it in four days.’ ‘And for me if I paid by the day instead of by the piece, how long?’
            ‘One day instead of half, O Lady, for fear thou shouldest say to us, you have finished
            in half a day and half the wages is enough for you.’ That is the way in which all the
            work is done for _Effendeena_—no wonder his steamers don’t pay. </p>
         <p> I saw Ross yesterday—he tells me the Shereef of Mecca has sent him a horse.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>