<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Mrs. Austin. GRAND CAIRO, Tuesday, November 11, 1862.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/1">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/360630">Cairo</settlement>
               <date when="1862-11-11">11 November 1862</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/59830344">Sarah Austin</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Dearest <foreign xml:lang="de">Mutter</foreign>,</p>

         <p>I write to you out of the real Arabian Nights. Well may the Prophet (whose name be
            exalted) smile when he looks on <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>. It is a
            golden existence, all sunshine and poetry, and, <hi rend="it">I</hi> must add, kindness
            and civility. I came up last <date when="1862-11-06">Thursday</date> by railway with the
            American Consul-General, a charming person, and had to stay at this horrid Shepheard's
            Hotel. But I do little but sleep here. <persName>Hekekian Bey</persName>, a learned old
            Armenian, takes care of me every day, and the Amerian Vice-Consul is my sacrifice. I
            went on <date when="1862-11-09">Sunday</date> to his child's christening, and heard
               <persName>Sakna</persName>, the <q>Restorer of Hearts.</q> She is wonderfully like
               <persName>Rachel</persName>, and her singing is <foreign xml:lang="de">hinreisend</foreign> from expression and passion. <persName>Mr. Wilkinson</persName>
            (the Consul) is a Levantine, and his wife Armenian, so they had a grand fantasia; people
            feasted all over the house and in the street. Arab music <foreign xml:lang="de">schmetterte</foreign>, women yelled the <foreign xml:lang="ar">zaghareet</foreign>,
            black servants served sweetmeats, pipes, and coffee, and behaved as if they belonged to
            the company, and I was strongly under the impression that I was at Nurreddin's wedding
            with the Vizier's daughter. Yesterday I went to <placeName>Heliopolis</placeName> with
               <persName>Hekekian Bey</persName> and his wife, and visited an Armenian country lady
            close by.</p>

         <p>My servant <persName>Omar</persName> turns out a jewel. He has <foreign xml:lang="fr">deterre</foreign> an excellent boat for the Nile voyage, and I am to be mistress of
            a captain, a mate, eight men and a cabin boy for 25 pounds a month. I went to <placeName ref="Boulak">Boulak</placeName>, the port of <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>, and saw various boats, and admired the way in which the English
            travellers pay for their insolence and caprices. Similar boats cost people with
            dragomans 50 to 65 pounds. But, then, 'I shall lick the fellows,' etc., is what I hear
            all round. The dragoman, I conclude, pockets the difference. The owner of the boat,
               <persName>Sid Achmet el-Berberi</persName>, asked 30 pounds, whereupon I touched my
            breast, mouth and eyes, and stated through <persName>Omar</persName> that I was not,
            like other Ingeleez, made of money, but would give 20 pounds. He then showed another
            boat at 20 pounds, very much worse, and I departed (with fresh civilities) and looked at
            others, and saw two more for 20 pounds; but neither was clean, and neither had a little
            boat for landing. Meanwhile <persName>Sid Achmet</persName> came after me and explained
            that, if I was not like other Ingeleez in money, I likewise differed in politeness, and
            had refrained from abuse, etc., etc., and I should have the boat for 25 pounds. It was
            so very excellent in all fittings, and so much larger, that I thought it would make a
            great difference in health, so I said if he would go before the American Vice-Consul
            (who is looked on as a sharp hand) and would promise all he said to me before him, it
            should be well.</p>

         <p>
                <persName>Mr. Thayer</persName>, the American Consul-General, gives me letters to every
            consular agent depending on him; and two Coptic merchants whom I met at the fantasia
            have already begged me to <q>honour their houses.</q> I rather think the poor agents,
            who are all Armenians and Copts, will think I am the republic in person. The weather has
            been all this time like a splendid English August, and I hope I shall get rid of my
            cough in time, but it has been very bad. There is no cold at night here as at the Cape,
            but it is nothing like so clear and bright.</p>

         <p>
                <persName>Omar</persName> took <persName>Sally</persName> sightseeing all day while I
            was away, into several mosques; in one he begged her to wait a minute while he said a
            prayer. They compare notes about their respective countries and are great friends; but
            he is put out at my not having provided her with a husband long ago, as is one's duty
            towards a <q>female servant,</q> which almost always here means a slave.</p>

         <p>Of all the falsehoods I have heard about the East, that about women being old hags at
            thirty is the biggest. Among the poor fellah women it may be true enough, but not nearly
            as much as in Germany; and I have now seen a considerable number of Levantine ladies
            looking very handsome, or at least comely, till fifty. <persName>Sakna</persName>, the
            Arab Grisi, is fifty-five--an ugly face, I am told (she was veiled and one only saw the
            eyes and glimpses of her mouth when she drank water), but the figure of a leopard, all
            grace and beauty, and a splendid voice of its kind, harsh but thrilling like
               <persName>Malibran</persName>'s. I guessed her about thirty, or perhaps thirty-five.
            When she improvised, the finesse and grace of her whole <foreign xml:lang="de">Wesen</foreign> were ravishing. I was on the point of shouting out <q>Wallah!</q> as
            heartily as the natives. The eight younger <foreign xml:lang="ar">Halmeh</foreign>
            (i.e., learned women, which the English call Almeh and think is an improper word) were
            ugly and screeched. <persName>Sakna</persName> was treated with great consideration and
            quite as a friend by the Armenian ladies with whom she talked between her songs. She is
            a Muslimeh and very rich and charitable; she gets 50 pounds for a night's singing at
            least.</p>

         <p>It would be very easy to learn colloquial Arabic, as they all speak with such perfect
            distinctness that one can follow the sentences and catch the words one knows as they are
            repeated. I think I know forty or fifty words already, besides my <q>
                    <foreign xml:lang="ar">salaam aleikum</foreign>
                </q> and <q>
                    <foreign xml:lang="ar">backsheesh.</foreign>
                </q>
            </p>

         <p>The reverse of the brilliant side of the medal is sad enough: deserted palaces, and
            crowded hovels scarce good enough for pigstyes. <q>One day man see his dinner, and one
               other day none at all,</q> as <persName>Omar</persName> observes; and the children
            are shocking from bad food, dirt and overwork, but the little pot-bellied, blear-eyed
            wretches grow up into noble young men and women under all their difficulties. The faces
            are all sad and rather what the Scotch call 'dour,' not <foreign xml:lang="fr">mechant</foreign> at all, but harsh, like their voices. All the melody is in walk
            and gesture; they are as graceful as cats, and the women have exactly the <q>breasts
               like pomegranates</q> of their poetry. A tall Bedaween woman came up to us in the
            field yesterday to shake hands and look at us. She wore a white sackcloth shift and
            veil, <foreign xml:lang="de">und weiter nichts</foreign>, and asked <persName>Mrs.
               Hekekian</persName> a good many questions about me, looked at my face and hands, but
            took no notice of my rather smart gown which the village women admired so much, shook
            hands again with the air of a princess, wished me health and happiness, and strode off
            across the graveyard like a stately ghost. She was on a journey all alone, and somehow
            it looked very solemn and affecting to see her walking away towards the desert in the
            setting sun like Hagar. All is so Scriptural in the country here.
               <persName>Sally</persName> called out in the railroad, <q>There is
                  <persName>Boaz</persName>, sitting in the cornfield</q>; and so it was, and there
            he has sat for how many thousand years,--and <persName>Sakna</persName> sang just like
               <persName>Miriam</persName> in one war-song.</p>

         <p>
                <date when="1862-11">Wednesday.</date>--My contract was drawn up and signed by the
            American Vice-Consul to-day, and my Reis kissed my hand in due form, after which I went
            to the <foreign xml:lang="ar">bazaar</foreign> to buy the needful pots and pans. The
            transaction lasted an hour. The copper is so much per oka, the workmanship so much;
            every article is weighed by a sworn weigher and a ticket sent with it. More Arabian
            Nights. The shopkeeper compares notes with me about numerals, and is as much amused as
            I. He treats me to coffee and a pipe from a neighbouring shop while
               <persName>Omar</persName> eloquently depreciates the goods and offers half the value.
            A water-seller offers a brass cup of water; I drink, and give the huge sum of twopence,
            and he distributes the contents of his skin to the crowd (there always is a crowd) in my
            honour. It seems I have done a pious action. Finally a boy is called to carry the
               <foreign xml:lang="fr">batterie de cuisine</foreign>, while <persName>Omar</persName>
            brandishes a gigantic kettle which he has picked up a little bruised for four shillings.
            The boy has a donkey which I mount astride <foreign xml:lang="fr">a l'Arabe</foreign>,
            while the boy carries all the copper things on his head. We are rather a grand
            procession, and quite enjoy the fury of the dragomans and other leeches who hang on the
            English at such independent proceedings, and <persName>Omar</persName> gets reviled for
            spoiling the trade by being cook, dragoman, and all in one.</p>

         <p>I went this morning with <persName>Hekekian Bey</persName> to the two earliest mosques.
            The Touloun is exquisite--noble, simple, and what ornament there is is the most delicate
            lacework and embossing in stone and wood. This Arab architecture is even more lovely
            than our Gothic. The Touloun is now a vast poorhouse, a nest of paupers. I went into
            three of their lodgings. Several Turkish families were in a large square room neatly
            divided into little partitions with old mats hung on ropes. In each were as many bits of
            carpet, mat and patchwork as the poor owner could collect, and a small chest and a
            little brick cooking-place in one corner of the room with three earthern pipkins for I
            don't know how many people;--that was all--they possess no sort of furniture, but all
            was scrupulously clean and no bad smell whatever. A little boy seized my hand and showed
            where he slept, ate and cooked with the most expressive pantomime. As there were women,
               <persName>Hekekian</persName> could not come in, but when I came out an old man told
            us they received three loaves (cakes as big as a sailor's biscuit), four piastres a
               month--<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>, eightpence per adult--a suit of clothes a year,
            and on festive occasions lentil soup. Such is the almshouse here. A little crowd
            belonging to the house had collected, and I gave sixpence to an old man, who transferred
            it to the first old man to be <hi rend="italic">divided</hi> among them all, ten or
            twelve people at least, mostly blind or lame. The poverty wrings my heart. We took leave
            with <foreign xml:lang="ar">salaam</foreign>s and politeness like the best society, and
            then turned into an Arab hut stuck against the lovely arches. I stooped low under the
            door, and several women crowded in. This was still poorer, for there were no mats or
            rags of carpet, a still worse cooking-place, a sort of dog-kennel piled up of loose
            stones to sleep in, which contained a small chest and the print of human forms on the
            stone floor. It was, however, quite free from dust, and perfectly sweet. I gave the
            young woman who had led me in sixpence, and here the difference between Turk and Arab
            appeared. The division of this created a perfect storm of noise, and we left the five or
            six Arab women out-shrieking a whole rookery. I ought to say that no one begged at
            all.</p>

         <p>
                <date when="1862-11">Friday</date>.--I went to-day on a donkey to a mosque in the
               <foreign xml:lang="ar">bazaar</foreign>, of what we call Arabesque style, like the
               <placeName>Alhambra</placeName>, very handsome. The <foreign xml:lang="ar">Kibleh</foreign> was very beautiful, and as I was admiring it
               <persName>Omar</persName> pulled a lemon out of his breast and smeared it on the
            porphyry pillar on one side of the arch, and then entreated me to lick it. It cures all
            diseases. The old man who showed the mosque pulled eagerly at my arm to make me perform
            this absurd ceremony, and I thought I should have been forced to do it. The base of the
            pillar was clogged with lemon-juice. I then went to the tombs of the <foreign xml:lang="ar">Khalifah</foreign>; one of the great ones had such arches and such
            wondrous cupolas but all in ruins. There are scores of these noble buildings, any one of
            which is a treasure, falling to decay. The next, strange to say, was in perfect repair.
            I got off the donkey, and <persName>Omar</persName> fidgeted and hesitated a little and
            consulted with a woman who had the key. As there were no overshoes I pulled my boots
            off, and was rewarded by seeing the footprints of <persName>Mohammed</persName> on two
            black stones, and a lovely little mosque, a sort of <foreign xml:lang="fr">Sainte
               Chapelle</foreign>. <persName>Omar</persName> prayed with ardent fervour and went out
            backwards, saluting the Prophet aloud. To my surprise the woman was highly pleased with
            sixpence, and did not ask for more. When I remarked this, <persName>Omar</persName> said
            that no Frank had ever been inside to his knowledge. A mosque-keeper of the sterner sex
            would not have let me in. I returned home through endless streets and squares of Moslem
            tombs, those of the Memlooks among them. It was very striking; and it was getting so
            dark that I thought of <persName>Nurreddin Bey</persName>, and wondered if a <foreign xml:lang="ar">Jinn</foreign> would take me anywhere if I took up my night's lodging
            in one of the comfortable little cupola-covered buildings.</p>

         <p>My Coptic friend has just called in to say that his brother expects me at
               <placeName>Kenneh</placeName>. I find nothing but civility and a desire to please. My
            boat is the <rs>
                    <foreign xml:lang="ar">Zint el Bachreyn</foreign>
                </rs>, and I carry the
            English flag and a small American distinguishing pennant as a signal to my consular
            agents. We sail next <date when="1862-11">Wednesday</date>. Good-bye for the present,
            dearest <foreign xml:lang="de">Mutter</foreign>.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>