<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Alick, CAIRO, July 17, 1866.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/81">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <date when="1866-07-17">17 July 1866</date>
               <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/360630">Cairo</settlement>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff Gordon</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Dearest Alick, </p>
         <p> I am perfectly comfortable now with my aquatic _ménage_. The Reis is very well behaved
            and steady and careful, and the sort of Caliban of a sailor is a very worthy savage.
            Omar of course is hardworked—what with going to market, cooking, cleaning, ironing, and
            generally keeping everything in nice order but he won’t hear of a maid of any sort. No
            wonder! </p>
         <p> A clever old Reis has just come and over-hauled the bottom of the boat, and says he can
            mend her without taking her out of the water. We shall see; it will be great luck if he
            can. As I am the river doctor, all the sailoring men are glad to do me a civility. </p>
         <p> We have had the hottest of summers; it is now 98 in the cabin. I have felt very unwell,
            but my blue devils are quite gone, and I am altogether better. What a miserable war it
            is in Europe! I am most anxious for the next papers. Here it is money misery; the Pasha
            is something like bankrupt, and no one has had a day’s pay these three months, even
            pensions of sixty piastres a month (seven shillings) to poor old female slaves of
            Mahommed Ali’s are stopped. </p>
         <p> _August_ 4.—The heat is and has been something fearful: we are all panting and puffing.
            I can’t think what Palgrave meant about my being tired of poor old Egypt; I am very
            happy and comfortable, only I felt rather weak and poorly this year, and sometimes, I
            suppose, rather _wacham_, as the Arabs say, after you and the children. The heat, too,
            has made me lazy—it is 110 in the cabin, and 96 at night. </p>
         <p> I saw the _Moolid en-Nebbee_ (Festival of the Prophet), and the wonderful _Dóseh_
            (treading); it is an awful sight; so many men drunk with religious ardour. {293} I also
            went to a Turkish Hareem, where my darweesh friends sent me; it is just like a tea-party
            at Hampton Court, only handsomer, not as to the ladies, but the clothes, furniture and
            jewels, and not a bit like the description in Mrs. Lott’s most extraordinary book.
            Nothing is so clean as a Turkish hareem, the furniture is Dutch as to cleanliness, and
            their persons only like themselves—but oh! how dull and _triste_ it all seemed. One nice
            lady said to me, ‘If I had a husband and children like thee, I would die a hundred times
            rather than leave them for an hour,’ another envied me the power of going into the
            street and seeing the _Dóseh_. She had never seen it, and never would. </p>
         <p> To-morrow Olagnier will dine and spend the night here, to see the cutting of the canal,
            and the ‘Bride of the Nile’ on Monday morning. We shall sail up to old <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> in the evening with the Bride’s boat; also Hajjee
            Hannah is coming for the fantasia; after the high Nile we shall take the boat out and
            caulk her and then, if the excessive heat continues, I rather think of a month’s jaunt
            to Beyrout just to freshen me up. Hajjee Ali is there, with all his travelling materials
            and tents, so I need only take Omar and a bath and carpet-bag. If the weather gets cool
            I shall stay in my boat. The heat is far more oppressive here than it was at Luxor two
            years ago; it is not so dry. The Viceroy is afraid of cholera, and worried the poor
            Hajjees this year with most useless quarantine. The _Mahmal_ was smuggled into
               <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> before sunrise, without the usual honours,
            and all sightseers and holiday makers disappointed, and all good Muslims deeply
            offended. The idea that the Pasha has turned Christian or even Jew is spreading fast; I
            hear it on all sides. The new firman illegitimatising so many of his children is of
            course just as agreeable to a sincere Moslem as a law sanctioning polygamy for our royal
            family would be with us.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>