<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Mrs. Austin, LUXOR, March 6, 1867.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/97">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <date when="1867-03-06">6 March 1867</date>
               <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/360502">Luxor</settlement>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/59830344">Sarah Austin</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST MUTTER, </p>
         <p> The warm weather has set in, and I am already as much the better for it as usual. I had
            a slight attack, not nearly so bad as that at Soden, but it lingered and I kept my bed
            as a measure of precaution. Dear Yussuf was with me the evening I was attacked, and sat
            up all night to give me my medicine every hour. At the prayer of dawn, an hour and a
            half before sunrise, I heard his supplications for my life and health, and for you and
            all my family; and I thought of what I had lately read, how the Greeks massacred their
            own patriots because the Turks had shown them mercy—a display of temper which I hope
            will enlighten Western Christendom as to what the Muslims have to expect, if they (the
            Western Christians) help the Eastern Christians to get the upper hand. Yussuf was asking
            about a lady the other day who has turned Catholic. ‘Poor thing,’ said he, ‘the priests
            have drawn out her brains through her ears, no doubt: but never fear, her heart is good
            and her charity is great, and God will not deal hardly with those who serve Him with
            their hearts, though it is sad she should bow down before images. But look at thy slave
            Mabrook, can he understand one hundredth part of the thoughts of thy mind?
            Never-the-less he loves thee, and obeys thee with pleasure and alacrity; and wilt thou
            punish him because he knows not all thy ways? And shall God, who is so much higher above
            us as thou art above thy slave, be less just than thou?’ I pinned him at once, and
            insisted on knowing the orthodox belief; but he quoted the Koran and the decisions of
            the Ulema to show that he stretched no point as far as Jews and Christians are
            concerned, and even that idolaters are not to be condemned by man. Yussuf wants me to
            write a short account of the faith from his dictation. Would anyone publish it? It
            annoys him terribly to hear the Muslims constantly accused of intolerance, and he is
            right—it is not true. They show their conviction that their faith is the best in the
            world with the same sort of naïveté that I have seen in very innocent and ignorant
            English women; in fact, display a sort of religious conceit; but it is not often bitter
            or _haineux_, however much they are in earnest. </p>
         <p> I am going to write to Palgrave and ask him to let me send another boy or the money for
            Mabrook, who can’t endure the notion of leaving me. Achmet, who was always hankering
            after the fleshpots of Alexandria, got some people belonging to the boats to promise to
            take him, and came home and picked a quarrel and departed. Poor little chap; the Sheykh
            el-Beled ‘put a spoke in his wheel’ by informing him he would be wanted for the Pasha’s
            works and must stay in his own place. Since he went Mabrook has come out wonderfully and
            does his own work and Achmet’s with the greatest satisfaction. He tells me he likes it
            best so; he likes to be quiet. He just suits me and I him, it is humiliating to find how
            much more I am to the taste of savages than of the ‘polite circles.’ </p>
         <p> The old lady of the Maōhn proposed to come to me, but I would not let her leave her
            home, which would be quite an adventure to her. I knew she would be exclamatory, and
            lament over me, and say every minute, ‘Oh my liver. Oh my eyes! The name of God be upon
            thee, and never mind! to-morrow please God, thou wilt be quite well,’ and so forth.
            People send me such odd dishes, some very good. Yussuf’s wife packed two calves’ feet
            tight in a little black earthern pan, with a seasoning of herbs, and baked it in the
            bread oven, and the result was excellent. Also she made me a sort of small macaroni,
            extremely good. Now too we can get milk again, and Omar makes _kishta_, alias clotted
            cream. </p>
         <p> Do send me a good edition of the ‘Arabian Nights’ in Arabic, and I should much like to
            give Yussuf Lane’s Arabic dictionary. He is very anxious to have it. I can’t read the
            ‘Arabian Nights,’ but it is a favourite amusement to make one of the party read aloud; a
            stray copy of ‘Kamar ez-Zeman and Sitt Boodoora’ went all round Luxor, and was much
            coveted for the village _soirées_. But its owner departed, and left us to mourn over the
            loss of his MSS. </p>
         <p> I must tell you a black standard of respectability (it is quite equal to the English
            one of the gig, or the ham for breakfast). I was taking counsel with my friend Rachmeh,
            a negro, about Mabrook, and he urged me to buy him of Palgrave, because he saw that the
            lad really loved me. ‘Moreover,’ he said, ‘the boy is of a respectable family, for he
            told me his mother wore a cow’s tail down to her heels (that and a girdle to which the
            tail is fastened, and a tiny leathern apron in front, constituted her whole wardrobe),
            and that she beat him well when he told lies or stole his neighbours eggs.’ Poor woman;
            I wish this abominable slave trade had spared her and her boy. What folly it is to stop
            the Circassian slave trade, if it is stopped, and to leave this. The Circassians take
            their own children to market, as a way of providing for them handsomely, and both boys
            and girls like being sold to the rich Turks; but the blacks and Abyssinians fight hard
            for their own liberty and that of their cubs. Mabrook swears that there were two
            Europeans in the party which attacked his village and killed he knew not how many, and
            carried him and others off. He was not stolen by Arabs, or by Barrabias, like Hassan,
            but taken in war from his home by the seaside, a place called Bookee, and carried in a
            ship to Jedda, and thence back to Koseir and Keneh, where Palgrave bought him. I must
            say that once here the slaves are happy and well off, but the waste of life and the
            misery caused by the trade must be immense. The slaves are coming down the river by
            hundreds every week, and are very cheap—twelve to twenty pounds for a fine boy, and nine
            pounds and upwards for a girl. I heard that the last _gellab_ offered a woman and baby
            for anything anyone would give for them, on account of the trouble of the baby.
            By-the-bye, Mabrook displays the negro talent for babies. Now that Achmet is gone, who
            scolded them and drove them out, Mohammed’s children, quite babies, are for ever
            trotting after ‘Maboo,’ as they pronounce his name, and he talks incessantly to them. It
            reminds me so of Janet and poor Hassan, but Mabrook is not like Hassan, he is one of the
            sons of Anak, and already as big and strong as a man, with the most prodigious chest and
            limbs. </p>
         <p> Don’t be at all uneasy about me as to care. Omar knows exactly what to do as he showed
            the other day when I was taken ill. I had shown him the medicines and given him
            instructions so I had not even to speak, and if I were to be ill enough to want more
            help, Yussuf would always sit up alternate nights; but it is not necessary. Arabs make
            no grievance about broken rest; they don’t ‘go to bed properly,’ but lie down half
            dressed, and have a happy faculty of sleeping at odd times and anyhow, which enables
            them to wait on one day and night, without distressing themselves as it distresses us. </p>
         <p> _Thursday_.—A telegram has just come announcing that Janet will leave <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> to-morrow in a steamer, and therefore be here,
            Inshallah, this day week. I enclose a note from a Copt boy, which will amuse you. He is
            ‘sapping’ at English, and I teach him whenever I am able. I am a special favourite with
            all the young lads; they must not talk much before grown men, so they come and sit on
            the floor round my feet, and ask questions and advice, and enjoy themselves amazingly.
            Hobble-de-hoy-hood is very different here from what it is with us; they care earlier for
            the affairs of the grown-up world, and are more curious and more polished, but lack the
            fine animal gaiety of our boys. The girls are much more _gamin_ than the boys, and more
            romping and joyous. </p>
         <p> It is very warm now. I fear Janet will sigh terribly over the heat. They have left
            their voyage too late for such as do not love the Shems el-Kebeer (the big sun), which
            has just begun. I who worship Ammun Ra, love to feel him in his glory. It is long since
            I had any letters, I want so to hear how you all are.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>