<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Mrs. Austin, BAIRAM, April, 1866.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/77">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <date when="1866-04">April 1866</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/59830344">Sarah Austin</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST MUTTER, </p>
         <p> I write this to go down by Mr. Palgrave who leaves to-morrow. He has been with Mustapha
            Bey conducting an enquiry into Mustapha A’gha’s business. Mariette Bey struck Mustapha,
            and I and some Americans took it ill and wrote a very strong complaint to our respective
            Consuls. Mariette denied the blow and the words ‘liar, and son of a dog’—so the American
            and English Consuls sent up Palgrave as commissioner to enquire into the affair, and the
            Pasha sent Mustapha Bey with him. Palgrave is very amusing of course, and his knowledge
            of languages is wonderful, Sheykh Yussuf says few _Ulema_ know as much of the literature
            and niceties of grammar and composition. Mustapha Bey is a darling; he knew several
            friends of mine, Hassan Effendi, Mustapha Bey Soubky, and others, so we were friends
            directly. </p>
         <p> I have not yet got a woman-servant, but I don’t miss it at all; little Achmet is very
            handy, Mahommed’s slave girl washes, and Omar irons and cleans the house and does
            housemaid, and I have kept on the meek cook, Abd el-Kader, whom I took while the
            Frenchman was here. I had not the heart to send him away; he is such a _meskeen_. He was
            a smart travelling waiter, but his brother died, leaving a termagant widow with four
            children, and poor Abd el-Kader felt it his duty to bend his neck to the yoke, married
            her, and has two more children. He is a most worthy, sickly, terrified creature. </p>
         <p> I have heard that a decent Copt here wants to sell a black woman owing to reverses of
            fortune, and that she might suit me. Sheykh Yussuf is to negotiate the affair and to see
            if the woman herself likes me for a mistress, and I am to have her on trial for a time,
            and if I like her and she me, Sheykh Yussuf will buy her with my money in his name. I
            own I have very little scruple about the matter, as I should consider her price as an
            advance of two or three years’ wages and tear the paper of sale as soon as she had
            worked her price out, which I think would be a fair bargain. But I must see first
            whether Feltass (the Copt) really wants to sell her or only to get a larger price than
            is fair, in which case I will wait till I go to <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>. Anything is better than importing a European who at once thinks one
            is at her mercy on account of the expense of the journey back. </p>
         <p> I went out this morning to the early prayer of Bairam day, held in the burial-place.
            Mahmoud ibn-Mustapha preached, but the boys and the Hareem made such a noise behind us
            that I could not hear the sermon. The weather has set in hot these last days, and I am
            much the better. It seems strange that what makes others languid seems to strengthen me.
            I have been very weak and languid all the time, but the camel’s milk has fattened me
            prodigiously, to Sherayeff’s great delight; and the last hot days have begun to take
            away the miserable feeling of fatigue and languor. </p>
         <p> Palgrave is not well at all, and his little black boy he fears will die, and several
            people in the steamer are ill, but in Luxor there is no sickness to speak of, only
            chronic old women, so old and ugly and _achy_, that I don’t know what to do with them,
            except listen to their complaints, which begin, ‘_Ya ragleh_.’ _Ragel_ is man, so
            _ragleh_ is the old German _Männin_, and is the civil way of addressing a Saeedee woman.
            To one old body I gave a powder wrapped up in a fragment of a _Saturday Review_. She
            came again and declared Mashallah! the _hegab_ (charm) was a powerful one, for though
            she had not been able to wash off all the fine writing from the paper, even that little
            had done her a deal of good. I regret that I am unable to inform you what the subject of
            the article in the _Saturday_ which had so drastic an effect. </p>
         <p> Good-bye, dearest Mutter, I must go and take a sleep before the time of receiving the
            visits of to-day (the great festival). I was up before sunrise to see the prayer, so
            must have a siesta in a cool place. To-morrow morning early this will go. I hope you got
            a letter I sent ten days or so ago.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>