<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Mr. Tom Taylor, March 16, 1864.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/34">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <date when="1864-03-16">16 March 1864</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName>Tom Taylor</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAR TOM, </p>
         <p> I cannot tell you how delighted I was to hear that all had gone well with Laura and
            your little daughter. _Mashallah_! God bless her! When I told Omar that a friend ‘like
            my brother,’ as Arabs say, had got a baby, he proposed to illuminate our house and fire
            off all the pistols in the premises. Pray give my kind love and best wishes to Laura. </p>
         <p> I am living here a very quiet, dreamy sort of life in hot Thebes, visiting a little
            among my neighbours and learning a little Arabic from a most sweet, gentle young Sheykh
            who preaches on Fridays in the mosque of Luxor. I wish I could draw his soft brown face
            and graceful, brown-draped figure; but if I could, he is too devout I believe, to permit
            it. The police magistrate—el-Maōhn—Seleem Effendi, is also a great friend of mine, and
            the Kadee is civil, but a little scornful to heretical Hareem, I think. It is already
            very hot, and the few remaining traveller’s dahabiehs are now here on their way down the
            river; after that I shall not see a white face for many months, except Sally’s. </p>
         <p> Sheykh Yussuf laughed so heartily over a print in an illustrated paper, from a picture
            of Hilton’s, of Rebekah at the well, with the old _Vakeel_ of Sidi Ibraheem (Abraham’s
            chief servant) _kneeling_ before the girl he was sent to fetch like an old fool without
            his turban, and Rebekah and the other girls in queer fancy dresses, and the camels with
            snouts like pigs. ‘If the painter could not go to Es-Sham (Syria) to see how the Arab
            (Bedaween) really look,’ said Sheykh Yussuf, ‘why did he not paint a well in England
            with girls like English peasants? At least it would have looked natural to English
            people, and the _Vakeel_ would not seem so like a _majnoon_ (a madman) if he had taken
            off a hat.’ I cordially agreed with Yussuf’s art criticism. Fancy pictures of Eastern
            things are hopelessly absurd, and fancy poems too. I have got hold of a stray copy of
            Victor Hugo’s ‘_Orientales_,’ and I think I never laughed more in my life. </p>
         <p> The corn is now full-sized here, but still green; in twenty days will be harvest, and I
            am to go to the harvest-home to a fellah friend of mine in a village a mile or two off.
            The crop is said to be unusually fine. Old Nile always pays back the damage he does when
            he rises so very high. The real disaster is the cattle disease, which still goes on, I
            hear, lower down. It has not at present spread above Minieh, but the destruction has
            been fearful. </p>
         <p> I more and more feel the difficulty of quite understanding a people so unlike
            ourselves—the more I know them, I mean. One thing strikes me, that like children, they
            are not conscious of the great gulf which divides educated Europeans from themselves; at
            least, I believe it is so. We do not attempt to explain our ideas to them, but I cannot
            discover any such reticence in them. I wonder whether this has struck people who can
            talk fluently and know them better than I do? I find they appeal to my sympathy in
            trouble quite comfortably, and talk of religious and other feelings apparently as freely
            as to each other. In many respects they are more unprejudiced than we are, and very
            intelligent, and very good in many ways; and yet they seem so strangely childish, and I
            fancy I detect that impression even in Lane’s book, though he does not say so. </p>
         <p> If you write to me, dear Tom, please address me care of Briggs and Co., <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>. I shall be so glad to hear of you and yours. Janet is
            going to England. I wish I were going too, but it is useless to keep trying a hopeless
            experiment. At present I am very comfortable in health as long as I do nothing and the
            weather is warm. I suffer little pain, only I feel weak and weary. </p>
         <p> I have extensive practice in the doctoring line; bad eyes, of course, abound. My love
            to Watts, and give greetings to any other of my friends. I grieve over Thackeray much,
            and more over his girls’ lonely sort of position. </p>
         <p> I think you would enjoy, as I do, the peculiar sort of social equality which prevails
            here; it is the exact contrary of French _égalité_. There are the great and powerful
            people, much honoured (outwardly, at all events), but nobody has _inferiors_. A man
            comes in and kisses my hand, and sits down _off_ the carpet out of respect; but he
            smokes his pipe, drinks his coffee, laughs, talks and asks questions as freely as if he
            were an Effendi or I were a fellahah; he is not my inferior, he is my poor brother. The
            servants in my friends’ houses receive me with profound demonstrations of respect, and
            wait at dinner reverently, but they mix freely in the conversation, and take part in all
            amusements, music, dancing-girls, or reading of the Koran. Even the dancing-girl is not
            an outcast; she is free to talk to me, and it is highly irreligious to show any contempt
            or aversion. The rules of politeness are the same for all. The passer-by greets the one
            sitting still, or the one who comes into a room those who are already there, without
            distinction of rank. When I have greeted the men they always rise, but if I pass
            without, they take no notice of me. All this is very pleasant and graceful, though it is
            connected with much that is evil. The fact that any man may be a Bey or a Pasha
            to-morrow is not a good fact, for the promotion is more likely to fall on a bad slave
            than on a good or intelligent free man. Thus, the only honourable class are those who
            have nothing to hope from the great—I won’t say anything to fear, for all have cause for
            that. Hence the high respectability and _gentility_ of the merchants, who are the most
            independent of the Government. The English would be a little surprised at Arab judgments
            of them; they admire our veracity and honesty, and like us on the whole, but they blame
            the men for their conduct to women. They are shocked at the way Englishmen talk about
            Hareem among themselves, and think the English hard and unkind to their wives, and to
            women in general. English Hareemát is generally highly approved, and an Arab thinks
            himself a happy man if he can marry an English girl. I have had an offer for Sally from
            the chief man here for his son, proposing to allow her a free exercise of her religion
            and customs as a matter of course. I think the influence of foreigners is much more real
            and much more useful on the Arabs than on the Turks, though the latter show it more in
            dress, etc. But all the engineers and physicians are Arabs, and very good ones, too. Not
            a Turk has learnt anything practical, and the dragomans and servants employed by the
            English have learnt a strong appreciation of the value of a character for honesty,
            deserved or no; but many do deserve it. Compared to the couriers and _laquais de place_
            of Europe, these men stand very high. Omar has just run in to say a boat is going, so
            good-bye, and God bless you.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>