<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, March_ 31, 1866.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/75">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <date when="1866-03-31">31 March 1866</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff Gordon</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK, </p>
         <p> As for me I am much better again; the cough has subsided, I really think the Arab
            specific, camel’s milk, has done me great good. I have mended ever since I took it. It
            has the merit of being quite delicious. Yesterday I was much amused when I went for my
            afternoon’s drink, to find Sheriff in a great taking at having been robbed by a woman,
            under his very nose. He saw her gathering hummuz from a field under his charge, and went
            to order her off, whereupon she coolly dropped the end of her _boordeh_ which covered
            the head and shoulders, effectually preventing him from going near her; made up her
            bundle and walked off. His respect for the Hareem did not, however, induce him to
            refrain from strong language. </p>
         <p> M. Brune has made very pretty drawings of the mosque here, both outside and in; it is a
            very good specimen of modern Arab architecture; and he won’t believe it could be built
            without ground plan, elevations, etc., which amuses the people here, who build without
            any such inventions. </p>
         <p> The harvest here is splendid this year, such beans and wheat, and prices have fallen
            considerably in both: but meat, butter, etc., remain very dear. My fame as a Hakeemeh
            has become far too great, and on market-days I have to shut up shop. Yesterday a very
            handsome woman came for medicine to make her beautiful, as her husband had married
            another who teazed her, and he rather neglected her. And a man offered me a camel load
            of wheat if I would read something over him and his wife to make them have children. I
            don’t try to explain to them how very irrational they are but use the more intelligible
            argument that all such practices savour of the _Ebu er Rukkeh_ (equivalent to black
            art), and are _haram_ to the greatest extent; besides, I add, being ‘all lies’ into the
            bargain. The applicants for child-making and charm-reading are Copts or Muslims, quite
            in equal numbers, and appear alike indifferent as to what ‘Book’: but all but one have
            been women; the men are generally perfectly rational about medicine and diet. </p>
         <p> I find there is a good deal of discontent among the Copts with regard to their priests
            and many of their old customs. Several young men have let out to me at a great rate
            about the folly of their fasts, and the badness and ignorance of their priests. I
            believe many turn Muslim from a real conviction that it is a better religion than their
            own, and not as I at first thought merely from interest; indeed, they seldom gain much
            by it, and often suffer tremendous persecution from their families; even they do not
            escape the rationalizing tendencies now abroad in Christendom. Then their early and
            indissoluble marriages are felt to be a hardship: a boy is married at eight years old,
            perhaps to his cousin aged seventeen (I know one here in that case), and when he grows
            up he wishes it had been let alone. A clever lad of seventeen propounded to me his
            dissatisfaction, and seemed to lean to Islam. I gave him an Arabic New Testament, and
            told him to read that first, and judge for himself whether he could not still conform to
            the Church of his own people, and inwardly believe and try to follow the Gospels. I told
            him it was what most Christians had to do, as every man could not make a sect for
            himself, while few could believe everything in any Church. I suppose I ought to have
            offered him the Thirty-nine Articles, and thus have made a Muslim of him out of hand. He
            pushed me a little hard about several matters, which he says he does not find in ‘the
            Book’: but on the whole he is well satisfied with my advice. </p>
         <p> _Coptic Palm Sunday_, _April_ 1. </p>
         <p> We hear that Fadil Pasha received orders at Assouan to go up to Khartoum in Giaffar
            Pasha’s place: it is a civil way of killing a fat old Turk, if it is true. He was here a
            week or two ago. My informant is one of my old crew who was in Fadil Pasha’s boat. </p>
         <p> I shall wait to get a woman-servant till I go to <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>, the women here cannot iron or sew; so, meanwhile, the wife of Abd
            el-Kader, does my washing, and Omar irons; and we get on capitally. Little Achmet waits,
            etc., and I think I am more comfortable so than if I had a maid,—it would be no use to
            buy a slave, as the trouble of teaching her would be greater than the work she would do
            for me. </p>
         <p> My medical reputation has become far too great, and all my common drugs—Epsom salts,
            senna, aloes, rhubarb, quassia—run short. Especially do all the poor, tiresome, ugly old
            women adore me, and bore me with their aches and pains. They are always the doctor’s
            greatest plague. The mark of confidence is that they now bring the sick children, which
            was never known before, I believe, in these parts. I am sure it would pay a European
            doctor to set up here; the people would pay him a little, and there would be good profit
            from the boats in the winter. I got turkeys when they were worth six or eight shillings
            apiece in the market, and they were forced upon me by the fellaheen. I must seal up this
            for fear the boat should come; it will only pick up M. Brune and go on.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>