<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Mrs. Austin, ALEXANDRIA, November 2, 1865.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
      <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/63">
         <correspAction type="sent">
            <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
            <date when="1865-11-02">2 November 1865</date>
            <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/361058">Alexandria</settlement>
         </correspAction>
         <correspAction type="received">
            <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/59830344">Sarah Austin</persName>
         </correspAction>
      </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST MUTTER, </p>
         <p> The boat like all other things goes but slowly—however the weather here is unusually
            dry and fine. </p>
         <p> I have just been to see my poor friend Sittee Zubeydeh, widow of Hassaneyn Effendi who
            died in England—and I am filled with admiration at her good sense and courage. She has
            determined to carry on her husband’s business of letting boats herself, and to educate
            her children to the best of her power in habits of independence. I hope she will be
            successful, and receive the respect such rare conduct in a Turkish woman deserves from
            the English. I was much gratified to hear from her how kindly she had been treated in
            Glasgow. She said that nothing that could be done for her was left undone. She arrived
            this morning and I went to see her directly and was really astonished at all she said
            about her plans for herself and her children. Poor thing! it is a sad blow—for she and
            Hassaneyn were as thoroughly united as any Europeans could be. </p>
         <p> I went afterwards to my boat, which I hope will be done in five or six days. I am
            extremely impatient to be off. She will be a most charming boat—both comfortable and
            pretty. The boom for the big sail is new—and I exclaimed, ‘why you have broken the new
            boom and mended it with leather!’ Omar had put on a _sham splice_ to avert the evil eye
            from such a fine new piece of wood! Of course I dare not have the blemish renewed or
            _gare_ the first puff of wind—besides it is too characteristic. </p>
         <p> There is some cholera about again, I hear—ten deaths yesterday—so Olagnier tells me. I
            fancy the rush of Europeans back again, each bringing ‘seven other devils worse than
            himself’ is the cause of it. </p>
         <p> I think I am beginning to improve a little; my cough has been terribly harassing
            especially at night—but the weather is very good, cool, and not damp.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>