<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, March 10, 1863.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/7">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <date when="1863-03-10">10 March 1863</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff Gordon</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>


         <lg>
            <l>‘If in the street I led thee, dearest,</l>
            <l>Though the veil hid thy face divine,</l>
            <l>They who beheld thy graceful motion</l>
            <l>Would stagger as though drunk with wine.</l>
         </lg>

         <lg>
            <l>Nay, e’en the holy Sheykh, while praying</l>
            <l>For guidance in the narrow way,</l>
            <l>Must needs leave off, and on the traces</l>
            <l>Of thine enchanting footsteps stray.</l>
         </lg>

         <lg>
            <l>O ye who go down in the boats to Dumyat,</l>
            <l>Cross, I beseech ye, the stream to Budallah;</l>
            <l>Seek my beloved, and beg that she will not</l>
            <l>Forget me, I pray and implore her by Allah.</l>
         </lg>

         <lg>
            <l>‘Fair as two moons is the face of my sweetheart,</l>
            <l>And as to her neck and her bosom—Mashallah.</l>
            <l>And unless to my love I am soon reunited</l>
            <l>Death is my portion—I swear it by Allah.’</l>
         </lg>

         <p>Thus sings Ali Asleemee, the most _debraillé_ of my crew, a _hashshásh_, {48} but a
            singer and a good fellow. The translation is not free, though the sentiments are. I
            merely rhymed Omar’s literal word-for-word interpretation. The songs are all in a
            similar strain, except one funny one abusing the ‘Sheykh el-Beled, may the fleas bite
            him.’ Horrid imprecation! as I know to my cost, for after visiting the Coptic monks at
            Girgeh I came home to the boat with myriads. Sally said she felt like Rameses the Great,
            so tremendous was the slaughter of the active enemy.</p>

         <p>I had written the first page just as I got to Siout and was stopped by bad news of
            Janet; but now all is right again, and I am to meet her in <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>, and she proposes a jaunt to Suez and to Damietta. I have got a
            superb illumination to-night, improvised by Omar in honour of the Prince of Wales’s
            marriage, and consequently am writing with flaring candles, my lantern being on duty at
            the masthead, and the men are singing an epithalamium and beating the tarabookeh as loud
            as they can.</p>

         <p>You will have seen my letter to my mother, and heard how much better I am for the
            glorious air of Nubia and the high up-country. Already we are returning into misty
            weather. I dined and spent the day with Wassef and his Hareem, such an amiable, kindly
            household. I was charmed with their manner to each other, to the slaves and family. The
            slaves (all Muslims) told Omar what an excellent master they had. He had meant to make a
            dance-fantasia, but as I had not good news it was countermanded. Poor Wassef ate his
            boiled beans rather ruefully, while his wife and I had an excellent dinner, she being
            excused fasting on account of a coming baby. The Copt fast is no joke, neither butter,
            milk, eggs nor fish being allowed for fifty-five days. They made Sally dine with us, and
            Omar was admitted to wait and interpret. Wassef’s younger brother waited on him as in
            the Bible, and his clerk, a nice young fellow, assisted. Black slaves brought the dishes
            in, and capital the food was. There was plenty of joking between the lady and Omar about
            Ramadan, which he had broken, and the Nasranee fast, and also about the number of wives
            allowed, the young clerk intimating that he rather liked that point in Islam. I have
            promised to spend ten or twelve days at their house if ever I go up the Nile again. I
            have also promised to send Wassef all particulars as to the expense, etc. of educating
            his boy in England, and to look after him and have him to our house in the holidays. I
            can’t describe how anxiously kind these people were to me. One gets such a wonderful
            amount of sympathy and real hearty kindness here. A curious instance of the affinity of
            the British mind for prejudice is the way in which every Englishman I have seen scorns
            the Eastern Christians, and droll enough that sinners like Kinglake and I should be the
            only people to feel the tie of the ‘common faith’ (_vide_ ‘Eothen’). A very pious Scotch
            gentleman wondered that I could think of entering a Copt’s house, adding that they were
            the publicans (tax-gatherers) of this country, which is partly true. I felt inclined to
            mention that better company than he or I had dined with publicans, and even sinners.</p>

         <p>The Copts are evidently the ancient Egyptians. The slightly aquiline nose and long eye
            are the very same as the profiles of the tombs and temples, and also like the very
            earliest Byzantine pictures; _du reste_, the face is handsome, but generally sallow and
            rather inclined to puffiness, and the figure wants the grace of the Arabs. Nor has any
            Copt the thoroughbred, _distingué_ look of the meanest man or woman of good Arab blood.
            Their feet are the long-toed, flattish foot of the Egyptian statue, while the Arab foot
            is classically perfect and you could put your hand under the instep. The beauty of the
            Ababdeh, black, naked, and shaggy-haired, is quite marvellous. I never saw such delicate
            limbs and features, or such eyes and teeth.</p>

         <p>CAIRO, _March_ 19.</p>

         <p>After leaving Siout I caught cold. The worst of going up the Nile is that one must come
            down again and find horrid fogs, and cold nights with sultry days. So I did not attempt
            Sakhara and the Pyramids, but came a day before my appointed time to <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>. Up here in the town it is much warmer and dryer, and
            my cough is better already. I found all your letters in many volumes, and was so excited
            over reading them that I could not sleep one moment last night, so excuse dulness, but I
            thought you’d like to know I was safe in Briggs’ bank, and expecting Janet and Ross
            to-night.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>