<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Mrs. Austin, BOULAK, ON BOARD A RIVER STEAM-BOAT, December 27, 1863.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/23">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/360630">Cairo</settlement>
               <date when="1863-12-27">27 December 1863</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/59830344">Sarah Austin</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST MUTTER, </p>
         <p> After infinite delays and worries, we are at last on board, and shall sail to-morrow
            morning. After all was comfortably settled, Ismail Pasha sent for _all_ the steamers up
            to Rhoda, near Minieh, and at the same time ordered a Turkish General to come up
            instantly somehow. So Latif Pasha, the head of the steamers, had to turn me out of the
            best cabin, and if I had not come myself, and taken rather forcible possession of the
            forecastle cabin, the servants of the Turkish General would not have allowed Omar to
            embark the baggage. He had been waiting all the morning in despair on the bank; but at
            four I arrived, and ordered the _hammals_ to carry the goods into the forecabin, and
            walked on board myself, where the Arab captain pantomimically placed me in his right eye
            and on the top of his head. Once installed, this has become a hareem, and I may defy the
            Turkish Effendi with success. I have got a good-sized cabin with good, clean divans
            round three sides for Sally and myself. Omar will sleep on deck and cook where he can. A
            poor Turkish lady is to inhabit a sort of dusthole by the side of my cabin; if she seems
            decent, I will entertain her hospitably. There is no furniture of any sort but the
            divan, and we cook our own food, bring our own candles, jugs, basins, beds and
            everything. If Sally and I were not such complete Arabs we should think it very
            miserable; but as things stand this year we say, _Alhamdulillah_ it is no worse! Luckily
            it is a very warm night, so we can make our arrangements unchilled. There is no door to
            the cabin, so we nail up an old plaid, and, as no one ever looks into a hareem, it is
            quite enough. All on board are Arabs—captain, engineer, and men. An English Sitt is a
            novelty, and the captain is unhappy that things are not _alla Franca_ for me. We are to
            tow three dahabiehs—M. Mounier’s, one belonging to the envoy from the Sultan of Darfour,
            and another. Three steamers were to have done it, but the Pasha had a fancy for all the
            boats, and so our poor little craft must do her best. Only fancy the Queen ordering all
            the river steamers up to Windsor! </p>
         <p> At Minieh the Turkish General leaves us, and we shall have the boat to ourselves, so
            the captain has just been down to tell me. I should like to go with the gentlemen from
            Darfor, as you may suppose. See what strange combinations of people float on old Nile.
            Two Englishwomen, one French (Mme. Mounier), one Frenchman, Turks, Arabs, Negroes,
            Circassians, and men from Darfor, all in one party; perhaps the third boat contains some
            other strange element. The Turks are from Constantinople and can’t speak Arabic, and
            make faces at the muddy river water, which, indeed, I would rather have filtered. </p>
         <p> I hope to have letters from home to-morrow morning. Hassan, my faithful donkey-boy,
            will go to the post as soon as it is open and bring them down to <placeName ref="Boulak">Boulak</placeName>. Darling Rainie sent me a card with a cock robin for Christmas;
            how terribly I miss her dear little face and talk! I am pretty well now; I only feel
            rather weaker than before and more easily tired. I send you a kind letter of Mme.
            Tastu’s, who got her son to lend me the house at Thebes.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>