<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, THEBES, December 20,
               1862.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/4">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/347342">Thebes</settlement>
               <date when="1862-12-20">20 December 1862</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff Gordon</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAR ALICK,</p>

         <p>I have had a long, dawdling voyage up here, but enjoyed it much, and have seen and heard
            many curious things. I only stop here for letters and shall go on at once to Wady
            Halfeh, as the weather is very cold still, and I shall be better able to enjoy the ruins
            when I return about a month hence, and shall certainly prefer the tropics now. I can’t
            describe the kindness of the Copts. The men I met at a party in <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> wrote to all their friends and relations to be civil to me.
            Wassef’s attentions consisted first in lending me his superb donkey and accompanying me
            about all day. Next morning arrived a procession headed by his clerk, a gentlemanly
            young Copt, and consisting of five black memlooks carrying a live sheep, a huge basket
            of the most delicious bread, a pile of cricket-balls of creamy butter, a large copper
            caldron of milk and a cage of poultry. I was confounded, and tried to give a good
            baksheesh to the clerk, but he utterly declined. At Girgeh one Mishrehgi was waiting for
            me, and was in despair because he had only time to get a few hundred eggs, two turkeys,
            a heap of butter and a can of milk. At Keneh one Issa (Jesus) also lent a donkey, and
            sent me three boxes of delicious Mecca dates, which Omar thought stingy. Such attentions
            are agreeable here where good food is not to be had except as a gift. They all made me
            promise to see them again on my return and dine at their houses, and Wassef wanted to
            make a fantasia and have dancing girls. How you would love the Arab women in the country
            villages. I wandered off the other day alone, while the men were mending the rudder, and
            fell in with a troop of them carrying water-jars—such sweet, graceful beings, all smiles
            and grace. One beautiful woman pointed to the village and made signs of eating and took
            my hand to lead me. I went with her, admiring them as they walked. Omar came running
            after and wondered I was not afraid. I laughed, and said they were much too pretty and
            kindly-looking to frighten anyone, which amused them immensely when he told them so.
            They all wanted me to go and eat in their houses, and I had a great mind to it, but the
            wind was fair and the boat waiting, so I bid my beautiful friends farewell. They asked
            if we wanted anything—milk or eggs—for they would give it with pleasure, it was not
            their custom to sell things, they said, I offered a bit of money to a little naked
            child, but his mother would not let him take it. I shall never forget the sweet,
            engaging creatures at that little village, or the dignified politeness of an old weaver
            whose loom I walked in to look at, and who also wished to ‘set a piece of bread before
            me.’ It is the true poetical pastoral life of the Bible in the villages where the
            English have not been, and happily they don’t land at the little places. Thebes has
            become an English watering-place. There are now nine boats lying here, and the great
            object is to _do the Nile_ as fast as possible. It is a race up to Wady Halfeh or
            Assouan. I have gained so much during this month that I hope the remaining three will do
            real good, as the weather will improve with the new year they tell me. All the English
            stay here and ‘make Christmas,’ as Omar calls it, but I shall go on and do my devotions
            with the Copts at Esneh or Edfou. I found that their seeming disinclination to let one
            attend their service arose from an idea that we English would not recognise them as
            Christians. I wrote a curious story of a miracle to my mother, I find that I was wrong
            about the saint being a Mussulman (and so is Murray); he is no less than Mar Girghis,
            our own St. George himself. Why he selected a Mussulman mason I suppose he best
            knows.</p>

         <p>In a week I shall be in Nubia. Some year we must all make this voyage; you would revel
            in it. Kiss my darlings for me.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>