<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Mrs. Austin, LUXOR, February 15, 1866.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/70">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <date when="1866-02-15">15 February 1866</date>
               <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/360502">Luxor</settlement>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/59830344">Sarah Austin</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST MUTTER, </p>
         <p> I have only time for a short letter to say that the cold weather is over and that I
            continue to improve, not very fast, but still very sensibly. </p>
         <p> My young Frenchman turns out to be a M. Brune _grand prix de Rome_, an architect, and
            is a very nice fellow indeed, and a thorough gentleman. His odd awkward manner proved to
            be mere vexation at finding himself quartered _nolens volens_ on a stranger, and a
            woman; but we have made great friends, and I have made him quite happy by telling him
            that he shall pay his share of the food. He was going to hurry off from shyness though
            he had begun a work here by which I fancy he hopes to get _Kudos_. I see he is poor and
            very properly proud. He goes out to the temple at sunrise, and returns to dinner at
            dark, and works well, and his drawings are very clever. In short, I am as much obliged
            to the French Consul for sending me such an intelligent man as I was vexed at first. An
            _homme sérieux_ with an absorbing pursuit is always good company in the long run.
            Moreover M. Brune behaves like a perfect gentleman in every way. So _tout est pour le
            mieux_. </p>
         <p> I am sorry to say that Marie has become so excessively bored, dissatisfied, and, she
            says, ill, that I am going to send her back rather than be worried so—and _damit hats
            eine ende_ of European maids. Of course an ignorant girl _must_ be bored to death here—a
            land of no amusements and no flirtation _is_ unbearable. I shall borrow a slave of a
            friend here, an old black woman who is quite able and more than willing to serve me, and
            when I go down to <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> I will get either a ci-devant
            slave or an elderly Arab woman. Dr. Patterson strongly advised me to do so last year. He
            had one who has been thirteen years his housekeeper, an old bedaweeyeh, I believe, and
            as I now am no longer looked upon as a foreigner, I shall be able to get a respectable
            Arab woman, a widow or a divorced woman of a certain age who will be too happy to have
            ‘a good home,’ as our maids say. I think I know one, a certain Fatoomeh, a widow with no
            children who does washing and needlework in <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>.
            You need not be at all uneasy. I shall be taken good care of if I fall ill, much better
            than I should get from a European in a sulky frame of mind. Hajjee Ali has very kindly
            offered to take Marie down to <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> and start her off
            to Alexandria, whence Ross’s people can send her home. If she wants to stay in
            Alexandria and get placed by the nuns who piously exhorted her to extort ninety francs a
            month from me, so much the better for me. Ali refuses to take a penny from me for her
            journey—besides bringing me potatoes and all sorts of things: and if I remonstrate he
            says he and all his family and all they have is mine, in consequence of my treatment of
            his brother. </p>
         <p> You will be amused and pleased to hear how Sheykh Yussuf was utterly puzzled and
            bewildered by the civilities he received from the travellers this year, till an American
            told Mustapha I had written a book which had made him (the American) wish well to the
            poor people of this country, and desire to behave more kindly to them than would have
            been the case before. </p>
         <p> To-morrow is the smaller Bairam, and I shall have all the Hareem here to visit me. </p>
         <p> Two such nice Englishmen called the other day and told me they lived in Hertford Street
            opposite Lady D. G.’s and saw Alexander go in and out, and met Maurice in the gardens.
            It gave me a terrible twinge of _Heimweh_, but I thought it so kind and pretty and
            _herzlich_ of them to come and tell me how Alexander and Maurice looked as they went
            along the street.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>