<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Mrs. Austin, BOULAK, August 8, 1867.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/108">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <date when="1867-08-08">8 August 1867</date>
               <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/360630">Cairo</settlement>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/59830344">Sarah Austin</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST MUTTER, </p>
         <p> Two of my sailors were in Paris and have just come home. I hear they are dreadfully
            shocked by the dancing, and by the French women of the lower class generally. They sit
            in the coffee-shops like _shaers_ (poets), and tell of the wonders of Paris to admiring
            crowds. They are enthusiastic about the courtesy of the French police, who actually did
            not beat them when they got into a quarrel, but scolded the Frankish man instead, and
            accompanied them back to the boat quite politely. The novelty and triumph of not being
            beaten was quite intoxicating. There is such a curious sight of a crowd of men carrying
            huge blocks of stone up out of a boat. One sees exactly how the stones were carried in
            ancient times; they sway their bodies all together like one great lithe animal with many
            legs, and hum a low chant to keep time. It is quite unlike any carrying heavy weights in
            Europe. </p>
         <p> It is getting dusk and too windy for candles, so I must say goodnight and eat the
            dinner which Darfour has pressed upon me two or three times, he is a pleasant little
            creature, so lively and so gentle. It is washing day. I wish you could see Mabrook
            squatting out there, lathering away at the clothes with his superb black arms. He is a
            capital washer and a fair cook, but an utter savage. </p>
         <p> [The foregoing letter reached England the day after the death of my grandmother, Mrs.
            Austin, which was a great shock to my mother and made her ill and unhappy; so it was
            settled that my brother Maurice should go out and spend the winter with her on the
            Nile.]</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>