<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, LUXOR, April 19, 1867.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/100">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <date when="1867-04-19">19 April 1867</date>
               <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/360502">Luxor</settlement>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff Gordon</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK, </p>
         <p> I have been much amused lately by a new acquaintance, who, in romances of the last
            century, would be called an ‘Arabian sage.’ Sheykh Abdurrachman lives in a village half
            a day’s journey off, and came over to visit me and to doctor me according to the science
            of Galen and Avicenna. Fancy a tall, thin, graceful man, with a grey beard and liquid
            eyes, absorbed in studies of the obsolete kind, a doctor of theology, law, medicine and
            astronomy. We spent three days in arguing and questioning; I consented to swallow a
            potion or two which he made up before me, of very innocent materials. My friend is
            neither a quack nor superstitious, and two hundred years ago would have been a better
            physician than most in Europe. Indeed I would rather swallow his physic now than that of
            many a M.D. I found him like all the learned theologians I have known, extremely liberal
            and tolerant. You can conceive nothing more interesting and curious than the
            conversation of a man learned and intelligent, and utterly ignorant of all our modern
            Western science. If I was pleased with him, he was enchanted with me, and swore by God
            that I was a Mufti indeed, and that a man could nowhere spend time so delightfully as in
            conversation with me. He said he had been acquainted with two or three Englishmen who
            had pleased him much, but that if all Englishwomen were like me the power must
            necessarily be in our hands, for that my _akl_ (brain, intellect) was far above that of
            the men he had known. He objected to our medicine that it seemed to consist in
            palliatives, which he rather scorned, and aimed always at a radical cure. I told him
            that if he had studied anatomy he would know that radical cures were difficult of
            performance, and he ended by lamenting his ignorance of English or some European
            language, and that he had not learned our _Ilm_ (science) also. Then we plunged into
            sympathies, mystic numbers, and the occult virtues of stones, etc., and I swallowed my
            mixture (consisting of liquorice, cummin and soda) just as the sun entered a particular
            house, and the moon was in some favourable aspect. He praised to me his friend, a
            learned Jew of <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>. I could have fancied myself
            listening to Abu Suleyman of Cordova, in the days when we were the barbarians and the
            Arabs were the learned race. There is something very winning in the gentle, dignified
            manners of all the men of learning I have seen here, and their homely dress and habits
            make it still more striking. I longed to photograph my Sheykh as he sat on the divan
            pulling MSS. out of his bosom to read me the words of _El-Hakeem Lokman_, or to
            overwhelm me with the authority of some physician whose very name I had never heard. </p>
         <p> The hand of the Government is awfully heavy upon us. All this week the people have been
            working night and day cutting their unripe corn, because three hundred and ten men are
            to go to-morrow to work on the railroad below Siout. This green corn is, of course,
            valueless to sell and unwholesome to eat; so the magnificent harvest of this year is
            turned to bitterness at the last moment. From a neighbouring village all the men are
            gone, and seven more are wanted to make up the _corvée_. The population of Luxor is
            1,000 males of all ages, so you can guess how many strong men are left after three
            hundred and ten are taken. </p>
         <p> I don’t like to think too much about seeing you and Maurice next winter for fear I
            should be disappointed. If I am too sick and wretched I can hardly wish you to come
            because I know what a nuisance it is to be with one always coughing and panting, and
            unable to do like other people. But if I pick up tolerably this summer I shall indeed be
            glad to see you and him once more. </p>
         <p> This house is falling sadly to decay, which produces snakes and scorpions. I sent for
            the _hawee_ (snake-catcher) who caught a snake, but who can’t conjure the scorpions out
            of their holes. One of my fat turkeys has just fallen a victim, and I am in constant
            fear for little Bob, only he is always in Omar’s arms. I think I described to you the
            festival of Sheykh Gibrieel: the dinner, and the poets who improvised; this year I had a
            fine piece of declamation in my honour. A real calamity is the loss of our good Maōhn,
            Seleem Effendi. The Mudir hailed him from his steamer to go to Keneh directly, with no
            further notice. We hoped some good luck for him, and so it would have been to a Turk. He
            is made overseer over the poor people at the railway work, and only gets two pounds five
            shillings per month additional, he has to keep a horse and a donkey, and to buy them and
            to hire a sais, and he does _not_ know how to squeeze the fellaheen. It is true ‘however
            close you skin an onion, a clever man can always peel it again,’ which means that even
            the poorest devils at the works can be beaten into giving a little more; but our dear
            Seleem, God bless him, will be ruined and made miserable by his promotion. I had a very
            woeful letter from him yesterday.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>