<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, BOULAK, July 29, 1867.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/106">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <date when="1867-07-29">29 July 1867</date>
               <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/360630">Cairo</settlement>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff Gordon</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK, </p>
         <p> Your letter has arrived to my great relief—only I fear you are not at all well. About
            Maurice. If he wishes to see the Nile let him come, but if he is only to be sent because
            of me, let it alone. I know I am oppressive company now, and am apt, like Mr. Wodehouse
            in ‘Emma,’ to say, ‘Let us all have some gruel.’ </p>
         <p> We know nothing here of a prohibition of gunpowder, at this moment some Europeans are
            popping away incessantly at Embabeh just opposite. Evidently the Pasha wants to
            establish a right of search on the Nile. That absurd speech about slaves he made in
            Paris shows that. With 3,000 in his hareem, several slave regiments, and lots of gangs
            on all his sugar plantations, his impudence is wonderful. He is himself the greatest
            living slave trader as well as owner. My lads are afraid to go out alone for fear of
            being snapped up by cawasses and taken to the army or the sugar works. You will be sorry
            to hear that your stalwart friend Hassan has had fifty blows on each foot-sole, and had
            to pay six pounds. He was taking two donkeys to Shepheard’s hotel before sunrise for a
            French lady and gentleman to go to the Pyramids, when a cawass met him, seized the
            donkeys, and on Hassan’s refusal to give them up, spat on the side-saddle and reviled
            Hassan’s own Hareem and began to beat him with his courbash. Hassan got impatient, took
            the cawass up in his arms and threw him on the ground, and went on. Presently four
            cawasses came after him, seized him and took him to the Zaptieh (police office), where
            they all swore he had beaten them, torn their clothes, and robbed one of an imaginary
            gold watch—all valued at twenty-four pounds. After the beating he was carried to prison
            in chains, and there sentenced to be a soldier. A friend however interfered and settled
            the matter for six pounds. Hassan sends you his best salaam. </p>
         <p> Last night was very pretty—all the boats starting for the _moolid_ of Seyd el-Bedawee
            at Tanta. Every boat had a sort of pyramid of lanterns, and the derweeshes chanted, and
            the worldly folks had profane music and singing, and I sat and looked and listened, and
            thought how many thousand years ago just the same thing was going on in honour of
            Bubastis. </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>