<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, URANIA, BOULAK, October 21, 1867.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/111">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <date when="1867-10-21">21 October 1867</date>
               <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/360630">Cairo</settlement>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff Gordon</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK, </p>
         <p> So many thanks for the boxes and their contents. My slaves are enchanted with all that
            the ‘great master’ has sent. Darfour hugged the horsecloth in ecstasy that he should
            never again be cold at night. The waistcoats of printed stuff, and the red flannel
            shirts are gone to be made up, so my boys will be like Pashas this winter, as they told
            the Reis. He is awfully perturbed about the evil eye. ‘Thy boat, _Mashallah_, is such as
            to cause envy from all beholders; and now when they see a son with thee, _Bismillah_!
            _Mashallah_! like a flower, verily. I fear, I fear greatly from the eye of the people.’
            We have bought a tambourine and a tarabouka, and are on the look-out for a man who can
            sing well, so as to have fantasia on board. </p>
         <p> _October_ 22.—I hear to-day that the Pasha sent a telegram _hochst eigenhändig_ to
            Koos, in consequence whereof one Stefanos, an old Copt of high character, many years in
            Government employ, was put in chains and hurried off within twenty minutes to Fazoghlou
            with two of his friends, for no other crime than having turned Presbyterian. This is
            quite a new idea in Egypt, and we all wonder why the Pasha is so anxious to ‘brush the
            coat’ of the Copt Patriarch. We also hear that the people up in the Saaed are running
            away by wholesale, utterly unable to pay the new taxes and to do the work exacted. Even
            here the beating is fearful. My Reis has had to send all his month’s wages to save his
            aunt and his sister-in-law, both widows, from the courbash. He did not think so much of
            the blows, but of the ‘shame’; ‘those are women, lone women, from whence can they get
            the money?’ </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>