<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sultan Steamek, at Sea, between Cape St. Vincent and Gibraltar, October 4th,
               1850.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from https://archive.org/details/lettersfromegypt00brom</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/william-arnold-bromfield/letters/1">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/160825459">William Arnold
                  Bromfield</name>
               <name type="place">Sultan Steamek, at Sea, between Cape St. Vincent and
                  Gibraltar</name>
               <date when="1850-10-04">4 October 1850</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person">Eliza Bromfield</name>
               <name type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/2638911">Ryde</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>My dear <name type="person" ref="#eliza_bromfield">E</name>
            </p>

         <p>Early to-morrow we shall probably be at <name type="place" ref="#gibraltar">Gibraltar</name>, and as the vessel will remain for a few hours only to coal before
            continuing her course to <name type="place" ref="#malta">Malta</name>, but little time
            will be afforded for going ashore, and none left for writing to England. The
            delightfully calm and now sunny weather enables me to sit down and give you a short
            account of our progress since we left <name type="place" ref="#southampton">Southampton</name>, which, till to day, the rough state of the sea would not permit
            me to do, and even now, the vibration of the vessel, as you will perceive, makes writing
            not the most agreeable or easy task.</p>

         <p>Our number of passengers altogether amounts to about thirty, and we have a very heavy
            cargo of goods on board. We shall arrive I trust at <name type="place" ref="#malta">Malta</name> on Wednesday or Thursday, when I must put myself in quarantine for
            three days, until the Government steamer is ready to take me and the Indian passengers
            to <name type="place" ref="#alexandria">Alexandria </name>, on arriving at which place,
            we shall be admitted without delay to pratique, which would not be the case, if we had
            communicated or gone ashore at <name type="place" ref="#malta">Malta</name>.</p>

         <p>We had very heavy weather in crossing the Bay of Biscay, a great deal of sea, and a
            constantly over-cast sky of whity-brown, with occasional rain and fog, from which we did
            not emerge until this morning, in about the latitude of Cape St. Yincent. Nothing could
            be more dull and dreary than the aspect of sea and sky as we ran down the coasts of
            Spain and Portugal, of which, from the thickness of the weather we had only occasional
            glimpses, and very bleak and iron -bound they appeared, but lofty and picturesque,
            reminding me (I speak of the small range of coast-line off Cape Finisterre), of the
            coast of Ireland near Cape Clear, wild and rocky in the extreme.</p>

         <p>I was far from comfortable all Tuesday and Wednesday, but I have now found my sea-legs
            and appetite, and all other nautical requisites; the time passes but slowly however,
            even with my own books, and a very nice little library on board. The weather is
            delightfully warm and sunny, and all the ladies have come forth from their hiding
            places, and are enjoying themselves on deck, singing Italian airs to a piano. Our worthy
            Captain is a great favourite with all on board, his round face glowing with such a high
            colour and good humour, that it does one's heart good to look at him. The table is not
            so luxurious and profuse as on board the West India packets, but what is much better, it
            is good, plain and substantial, with wine (port and sherry) and spirits included;
            champagne twice a week. We have plenty of room, and the passengers are all disposed to
            be sociable and pleased with each other, a state of things which can hardly be otherwise
            with such a Captain to preside over our little society.</p>

         <p>Head winds retarded our progress down channel, and afterwards the wind and heavy sea
            were not in favour of quick progress; on the whole however, we have done very fairly,
            and our passage hitherto cannot be considered a bad one, although somewhat long. I am
            told that the passage from <name type="place" ref="#southampton">Southampton</name> to
               <name type="place" ref="#gibraltar">Gibraltar</name> has been made by the " Sultan "
            in four days and twenty hours, more than once; the distance is 1142 miles nautical. I
            have just heard that there is great probability that the quarantine betwixt <name type="place" ref="#malta">Malta</name> and <name type="place" ref="#alexandria">Alexandria </name> has been suspended, and that vessels will be at once admitted to
            pratique at the latter place, if they can procure a clean bill of health from the
            former; if this should prove true, there will be no necessity for any of our party
            putting ourselves in quarantine on arriving at <name type="place" ref="#malta">Malta</name>, but we can go quietly on shore to our hotel, undisturbed by the fear
            of having to expiate the deed in the Lazaretto at <name type="place" ref="#alexandria">Alexandria </name>, for I know not how many days. We cannot be sure of this good
            report being true, till we arrive at <name type="place" ref="#gibraltar">Gibraltar</name>, or even perhaps at <name type="place" ref="#malta">Malta</name>;
            but the authorities at <name type="place" ref="#gibraltar">Gibraltar</name> will
            probably be apprized of a relaxation of the lately existing quarantine laws to the
            eastward. </p>

         <p>The weather to-night is quite warm, so that we can sit with pleasure on deck, and the
            sky is much clearer than on any previous day; although by no means what people picture
            to themselves of the atmosphere of the south of Spain.</p>

         <p>October 4th, 8 p.m. The sea is calm as a mirror; our noble vessel making her way fast
            towards the entrance of the Strait, with a motion scarcely perceptible below.
            Unfortunately we shall not arrive at <name type="place" ref="#gibraltar">Gibraltar</name> by day-light. We have kept so far out to sea, that the coast of
            Spain and Portugal has been unseen from the deck, but we are to have a splendid view of
            the Spanish shore to-morrow, and a good glimpse of <name type="place" ref="#algiers">Algiers</name>. Had the weather been fine and clear, we should have run close along
            shore a great part of the way from <name type="place" ref="#cape_finisterre">Cape
               Finisterre</name> to <name type="place" ref="#gibraltar">Gibraltar</name>. As we
            shall remain on shore for several hours, I hope to see a good deal of the place on this
            first visit, and will do all I can to find out Major H 's tomb in the military burial
            ground, and report on its state for his sister's information. </p>

         <p>
                <name type="place" ref="#gibraltar">Gibraltar</name> , October; 5th. We arrived here
            this morning very early, and I was up and on deck, at six o'clock, to admire the
            magnificent view of the Bay and Rock of <name type="place" ref="#gibraltar">Gibraltar</name>, which fully came up to, and I may almost say, surpassed the idea I
            had formed of it. From arriving so early, our supply of coals had been got in sooner
            than was anticipated, and the Captain announced his intention of starting for <name type="place" ref="#malta">Malta</name> at noon instead of at 2 p.m., so that we had
            two hours less for going ashore than we had calculated upon. As a permit for ascending
            the " Rock " could not be had so early from the townmajor's office, I gave up all idea
            of going to the summit this time, and contented myself with perambulating the lower
            parts of the Rock and the town, and botanizing along the shore between the new and old
            towns. However, I gained a very considerable elevation, quite sufficient to give me a
            perfect view of the glorious panorama of sea and land, in survevinar which, I found my
            telescope a most invaluable companion. With what raptures would <name type="person" ref="#eliza_bromfield">E</name> have looked on the majestic mountains of Spain, and
            the vast Atlas range on the opposite coast of Africa, lighted up by a bright sun, with
            the deep blue of the bay beneath; and how often I wished for her at my side, for there
            was a dry fresh breeze on the rock that would have made the temperature perfectly
            supportable, if not almost agreeable to her.</p>

         <p>The chief defect of the landscape is the want of wood, which gives an air of nakedness
            and sameness to the mountains, but they are sprinkled with low bushes and tufted plants
            which render them not wholly devoid of verdure; whilst the rock itself between the new
            and old towns is one continued garden. The town is much better built, and far cleaner
            than I expected; and the Rock on a more extensive scale than I imagined. Very few wild
            plants were in flower; most of them being either quite burnt up, in seed, or not yet in
            bloom; nevertheless I found a great many curious species I had not before seen growing,
            and the garden vegetation has almost as much of a tropical aspect as in the West Indies.
            The town is a very amusing place, from the endless variety of features and costumes ; I
            remarked many very handsome Spanish faces, such as we see depicted by the old masters,
            but numbers had very ordinary ones, although fine black eyes are nearly universal. I
            shall hope to spend a week or a fortnight at this interesting place on my return; as
            yet, I have only an imperfect idea of <name type="place" ref="#gibraltar">Gibraltar</name>, We had a splendid view of the back of the rock, as we rounded
            Europa Point, a bare, black precipice, totally devoid of vegetation; and immediately the
            high mountains of Andalusia came into view, part, I believe, of the Sierra Nevada; but a
            slight haze, and our distance from them, only rendered their outlines visible, which
            were very fine.</p>

         <p>Sunday, October 6th, (between <name type="place" ref="#gibraltar">Gibraltar</name> and
               <name type="place" ref="#malta">Malta</name>). We are now in the enjoyment of almost
            tropical weather, careering over the blue Mediterranean at ten knots an hour, with no
            wind, but with an uneasy swell, sufficient to affect me in a slight degree when sitting
            erect below to write, as I am doing now. Divine service has just been performed in the
            saloon; and the whole ship's crew mustered in their best attire; a most copious supply
            of bibles and prayer-books being distributed on the table from a stock kept on board by
            the "Company." The chief officer acted as reader.</p>

         <p>One of our most active stewards broke his leg this morning in running up a short ladder
            from the main to the quarter-deck; the foot having caught in between two of the steps,
            the bone was snapped across by the impetus acquired.</p>

         <p>Monday, October 1th. Getting on famously, nine and a half knots an hour. Passed <name type="place" ref="#algiers">Algiers</name> this morning about seven o'clock, but at
            too great a distance to distinguish anything on shore; we have seen merely a glimpse of
            the African continent since leaving <name type="place" ref="#gibraltar">Gibraltar</name>. The uneasy motion of the sea still continues, and there is no wind to
            keep the ship steady. The thermometer this morning in the Captain's cabin on deck, was
            78 at 9 a.m. The weather since we arrived at <name type="place" ref="#gibraltar">Gibraltar</name>, has been like our own in the height of summer, with a sky very
            similar in aspect, that is, streaked, mottled, and partly overspread with fleecy clouds.
            To-day the atmosphere is less clear. I cannot perceive the slightest increase of depth
            in the blue tone of the sky since we left <name type="place" ref="#southampton">Southampton</name>, although we are nearly 300 miles within that sea so renowned, in
            popular belief, for the azure purity of its heaven. The starlight too is not a whit more
            brilliant than with us on ordinary clear nights. The warmth of the climate is already
            exerting a most beneficial influence on me; I am in excellent spirits, appetite and
            digestion perfect ; and only long to escape the tedium of the voyage, which, however I
            contrive to while away very tolerably. There are I find eleven of us going on to <name type="place" ref="#alexandria">Alexandria </name>, but no one excepting myself, will
            stop in Egypt; the rest are all for <name type="place" ref="#bombay">Bombay</name>.</p>

         <p>October 8th. Much cooler to day, very fine, but a good deal of cloud floating in the sky
            at one time; our speed is increased to nearly eleven knots an hour; the motion of the
            ship very disagreeable, but no one ill on board. Passed some islands, the largest of
            which was Galita, all said to be uninhabited, very bare and bleak. Towards evening we
            neared the coast of Africa, and had a good view of Cape Bona, the highest headland
            between <name type="place" ref="#gibraltar">Gibraltar</name> and <name type="place" ref="#malta">Malta</name>. We were not near enough to distinguish any object on
            shore, and the line of coast though bold, had no particularly foreign or exotic
            character about it, nor was it invested with that clear transparent atmosphere one hears
            so much about in the Mediterranean, whose waves however had all the deep azure I
            remember to have been struck with in 1827. <name type="place" ref="#algiers">Algiers</name> was sighted in the morning, but at far too great a distance to get
            even a distinct view of the town. The evening was very clear and calm, but rather cool.
            We expect to reach <name type="place" ref="#malta">Malta</name> to-morrow between 3 and
            4 p.m., and, as you may suppose, are extremely anxious to learn our fate, whether it is
            to quarantine or pratique we are to be admitted. No one will rejoice more than myself to
            step ashore there, to have a bath, and a cup of tolerable tea or coffee, both of which
            are scarce luxuries on board packet ships.</p>

         <p>Should we be under the necessity of putting ourselves in quarantine, the Lazaretto at
               <name type="place" ref="#malta">Malta</name> is spoken of as by no means
            uncomfortable quarters, and our term of durance will be past when the over-land mail
            steamer from <name type="place" ref="#marseilles">Marseilles</name> comes to our relief.
            It is the being at a place which one is forbidden to ramble over, that makes quarantine
            in this case so provoking. Our evenings pass off very agreeably, the young ladies being
            now all recovered from sea-sickness; the piano, which is really a very good one, is in
            constant requisition, and singing and playing while away the time pleasantly. This
            voyage is the first I have made in which no cards have been introduced; and although
            wine, spirits, and other beverages are supplied gratis by the "Company," not one of our
            passengers has indulged in liberal potations. Lights are put out in the saloon at
            halfpast ten, but the floating wick lamps in the sleeping or state rooms, are allowed to
            burn themselves out, and usually last till daylight.</p>

         <p>October 9th. A most beautiful morning, very clear and moderately warm. <name type="place" ref="#malta">Malta</name> is now in sight, (10 a.m.) and a few hours
            will terminate three-fourths of the passage to <name type="place" ref="#alexandria">Alexandria </name>, which we expect to reach on the nineteenth.</p>

         <p>October 10th. <name type="place" ref="#malta">Malta</name> Lazaretto. Our hope of being
            allowed to take pratique without subjecting ourselves to quarantine at <name type="place" ref="#alexandria">Alexandria </name> has been disappointed, and we were
            compelled to put ourselves in the latter disagreeable position yesterday, on our arrival
            in the harbour of <name type="place" ref="#valetta">Valetta</name>, about three o'clock.
            Our party consists of twelve, all, except myself, going to India. The quarantine
            buildings stand on a point of the harbour, isolated from the rest of the town; and
            consist of ranges of apartments, very lofty, and beautifully clean, white-washed, and
            with stone floors, and each room is abundantly supplied, with water. The only furniture
            is a chair or two, a rough wash-hand stand and an iron bedstead. As we are not, properly
            speaking, in quarantine, but only in the position of persons not holding communication
            with an infected place, we are not allowed to have any servant to assist us, because
            were any one coming off from the town to touch us, we should be immediately in
            quarantine for the full time required to enable us to take pratique on our arriving at
               <name type="place" ref="#alexandria">Alexandria </name>, that is, ten or fifteen days
            at least. We must now perform the most menial offices for ourselves, make our own beds,
            &amp;c, with a guardian ever watching us, whom, if we were to touch, we should be
            obliged to perform full quarantine from that moment.</p>

         <p>The weather is extremely hot still; to clay, far warmer than any we have had since we
            left England, with an almost cloudless sky, the rainy season not having commenced.</p>

         <p>Bedding must be paid for here as an extra, but Captain Brookes, of the "Sultan," with
            great liberality, has ordered a quantity of mattresses, sheets, and blankets, to be sent
            to us from the ship, which he will take back on his return from <name type="place" ref="#constantinople">Constantinople</name>. None of us however could get much rest
            last night from the incessant attacks of mosquitoes; the only insect annoyance we are
            exposed to here: we can, it is true, have mosquito curtains by paying for them, but the
            narrowness of the beds themselves is another cause of discomfort, not to be remedied,
            and we are fain to put up with our light misfortunes, from which we look forward to be
            relieved on Sunday by the arrival of the steamer from <name type="place" ref="#marseilles">Marseilles</name>, In our party of twelve, there are only four
            gentlemen including myself; the rest are ladies, most of whom are girls, the daughters
            and nieces of Colonel S, an officer of the Indian army, returning with his wife to <name type="place" ref="#bombay">Bombay</name>, a pleasing and gentlemanly man. Mr. P, a
            young cadet going out to join his regiment in India, and Dr. F , are our other
            associates, and we form quite a sociable and merry party. Our way of living is droll
            enough, as we must touch nobody, not even the guardian, or the persons who bring us our
            meals, which are furnished from a trattoria close at hand, the owner of which is himself
            in pratique. As an instance of the extreme absurdity of the quarantine laws — although
            we are strictly forbidden to come in contact with any person employed in conveying food
            or messages to us poor prisoners, yet we touch and taste fruit, bread, vegetables,
            &amp;c, which they have handled, and money is allowed to pass freely between us.</p>

         <p>October 11th. Another charming day, with a delicious breeze on the flat stone or stucco
            roof of our prison house. The ladies have discovered that there are worse inmates than
            the mosquitoes in our apartments; but though seriously tormented by the latter, I have
            not seen the more odious insects in my room. We all slept better last night, but on
            meeting at breakfast this morning, the fair faces of our female friends bore the
            appearance of an attack of measles, and my hands and forehead are covered with bites. I
            endeavoured to exclude the enemy by tying a pocket handkerchief over the whole head and
            face, and lying completely enveloped in the upper sheet, but the remedy proved worse
            than the disease, from the heat thus generated, and the hindrance to breathing. The
            common house-fly swarms about everything eatable, but is not otherwise troublesome; and
            I have not observed a single bluebottle. A harmless myriapode, allied to Scolopendra,
            caused great disgust to our young Cadet last night, as it hurried across his bed; and we
            saw whilst at tea one of those large spiders so common in Suffolk and at Hampton Court,
            called daws or cardinals, but our only real annoyance hitherto has been the
            mosquitoes.</p>

         <p>Our rooms command a fine view of the town of <name type="place" ref="#valetta">La Valette</name> and the Quarantine Harbour, and
            the terrace on the flat roof is extremely spacious. There we pass a great deal of our
            time after sunset, and there I find great amusement at all times with my telescope,
            which does service pro bono publico. We are permitted to have a boat, and row about the
            quarantine harbour, but our limits are rigidly defined, and we cannot enter the great
            harbour, which I have not yet seen, but suppose that the "Medina" will go in to take
            passengers off on Sunday at twelve at noon, when, we are told, we shall be released from
            our not very irksome confinement. We breakfast at nine, dine at three, have tea at
            seven, and cheat the mosquitoes as long as we can by remaining on the house-top, upon
            which fortunately we are not prohibited from staying all night, if we think proper, and
            the temperature then is delicious, nor do the mosquitoes venture so high, at least in
            any numbers. Our guardian is a good looking Maltese or Italian, more to be pitied than
            any of us, having nothing to do but to keep guard over us, and to saunter about in the
            corridor, and on the shore below our castle. The only service he performs is to bring
            messages oral or written, to place the dishes at meals within reach and yet avoid coming
            in contact with any of our party. We really (bating the mosquitoes), pass our time of
            durance very pleasantly, with a brilliant sun ever shining on us, and an exhilarating
            temperature; and buoyed up with the hope of being within two days from this time winging
            our way to the land of the Pharoahs, whither we all look forward with impatience to
            arrive on Thursday next.</p>

         <p>Our expences in quarantine will not at the outside amount to more than ten shillings a
            day for each person, for everything is under Government regulation, and a price fixed.
            We do not hear of any new cases of cholera in the town, excepting a solitary one of two
            days back.</p>

         <p>The view from our windows, verandah, and roof, is very fine, but immeasurably behind
            that from the Bay and Rock of <name type="place" ref="#gibraltar">Gibraltar</name>; for
            there is here no very bold scenery, and a great deficiency of shadow in the landscape
            owing to the want of trees. There is not the slightest appearance of the rainy season
            approaching at present, the temperature at this moment, by the thermometer on the table
            at 1, p.m., is 73. The houses of <name type="place" ref="#valetta">La Valetta</name> are of a yellowish white free-stone, and
            with perfectly flat roofs. The Government House, and the English Church built by Queen
            Adelaide, are two of the most conspicuous of the public buildings, besides the walls and
            fortifications which are mantled with caper-bushes, the branches of which, hang
            gracefully in thick verdant tresses. The fruits supplied us here are very indifferent;
            the best are grapes, now going out of season, but most of these are thick-skinned and
            insipid; the peaches very large, hard, and worthless; the only pears we have seen were
            mellow, but sleepy, as are likewise the apples; the dried figs are good, pomegranates
            very poor; melons passably good. Our dining table is adorned with large bouquets of
            flowers? and we received a present of some this morning, all very inferior to English
            flowers of the same kind, and consisting of only the few following; white and red China
            roses, (poor of their kind), sweet scented verbena, heliotrope, and scarlet geranium,
            each and all of which would be thought very mediocre samples of their varieties with us.
            I forgot to mention a few dahlias, good in colour, but smaller than with us. It is not
            probable that these were the choicest productions of the Maltese flower gardens; yet the
            two gift bouquets are probably a pretty fair specimen of local cultivation. The potatoes
            here are excellent, and the growth of the island.</p>

         <p>October 12th. Another glorious day, after a night of restlessness from our pitiless
            enemies the mosquitoes, and I am sorry to add, less cleanly, though not more annoying
            foes. We all look forward to release from prison to-morrow, or on Monday morning at
            latest. We expect to find it as much warmer at <name type="place" ref="#alexandria">Alexandria </name>, as this place exceeds <name type="place" ref="#gibraltar">Gibraltar</name> in that respect; for although in very nearly the same latitude,
               <name type="place" ref="#malta">Malta</name> is surrounded by a sea of higher
            temperature than the Atlantic, and there is not the same indraught of cool air from the
            adjacent coasts, or ocean, or from the high mountains of the European or African shores,
            which keeps <name type="place" ref="#gibraltar">Gibraltar</name> comparatively cool. In
               <name type="place" ref="#malta">Malta</name>, the highest land I am told, is not
            above five or six hundred feet, and there being no wood, and few trees of any size, the
            glare and heat from the white rocks must be extreme. Of the city of <name type="place" ref="#valetta">La Valetta</name>, I can of
            course say nothing, although so close to the main part of it; it seems to be well built,
            and has a very imposing appearance from the water, but it is not so pretty an object as
            Ryde when seen from the pier-head. Queen Adelaide's new church is, as I have observed,
            the most conspicuous building on this side of the town, and its erection is said to have
            excited the most violent opposition from the Romish priesthood, which is extremely
            bigoted in <name type="place" ref="#malta">Malta</name>.</p>

         <p>
                <name type="place" ref="#alexandria">Alexandria </name> October 18th. We arrived off
            this place last night, in the Government steamer "Medina" from <name type="place" ref="#marseilles">Marseilles</name>, and entered the harbour this morning at sunrise,
            after an unpleasant but not stormy passage: the very uneasy motion of the vessel
            affecting every one of the passengers, being compounded of pitching and rolling; the
            worst kind of motion, and there was hardly any wind. The Medina, commanded as she is, by
            a Lieutenant in the Navy, exhibits a strange mixture of civil and naval arrangements and
            usages, with nothing like the order, promptness, and care, which one expects to see on
            Her Majesty's quarterdeck.</p>

         <p>We entered the bay of <name type="place" ref="#alexandria">Alexandria </name> under as
            English a looking sky as one could wish to have to remind one of home; and at <name type="place" ref="#malta">Malta</name>, the night of Sunday when we started was much
            over-cast, but during the passage the weather was uniformly fine. Picture to yourself
            our bright summer weather, when the heavens are canopied with detached flocculent masses
            of white, upon a ground of pale blue, and you have the exact idea of the prevailing
            aspect of the Arabian and Egyptian mackarel sky, which is exactly what I expected to
            find it, and very nearly that of the tropics.</p>

         <p>On entering the Harbour of <name type="place" ref="#alexandria">Alexandria </name>, the
            weather looked very threatening, but cleared off, and became fine and extremely hot all
            day, with a cool delicious breeze, and fine at night. Judge therefore of my astonishment
            on rising this morning, to find it pouring with rain, accompanied by occasional claps of
            thunder, but not very violent: the rain ceased before 10 a.m., and now, (19th at noon),
            it is both damp and hot, and this makes the mosquitoes very active and troublesome in
            broad day, which is not often the case: as to flies, I do not find more than in
            England; not a tithe of the numbers that settled on everything at <name type="place" ref="#malta">Malta</name>.</p>

         <p>We found all the men of war in the harbour decked out with flags, as we entered
            yesterday, it being a great Mahommedan festival; I believe that of Beiram. We saw
            several magnificent line of battle ships in apparently high order and discipline, from
            which the Turkish ensign, (the crescent and star), waved conspicuously. The harbour
            presented a far more animated and crowded appearance than that of Portsmouth, being
            literally filled with shipping. We were on shore before ten o'clock, and I, who alone of
            all the party remained at <name type="place" ref="#alexandria">Alexandria </name>, was
            neither asked for my passport nor compelled to submit to Custom-house examination, but
            drove quietly off to the hotel, (Ray's), in the Frank Square, heartily glad to escape
            from the closeness and confinement of our probationary sojourn at <name type="place" ref="#malta">Malta</name>, which had quite ruined, pro. tem., the complexions of our
            lady fellow travellers, three of whom were really very pretty.</p>

         <p>I have just learned that the Medina leaves this place on Monday with the English mail
            via <name type="place" ref="#marseilles">Marseilles</name>, so that I must have this
            dispatch posted without further delay, and must reserve my account of <name type="place" ref="#alexandria">Alexandria </name> for another letter.</p>

         <p>I enclose five little packets of seeds for Mr. Lawrence, to whom remember me.</p>

         <p>October 20th. Another wet morning, a very heavy shower for an hour or two, and the great
            Frank Square in which I lodge, covered with pools, or rather immense puddles, which the
            heat of the sun raises into vapour, and renders the air extremely damp, giving fresh
            life and vigour to my friends the mosquitoes.</p>

         <p>Believe me, My dear <name type="person" ref="#eliza_bromfield">E</name>, Your
            affectionate Brother, William Arnold Bromfield.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>