<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>On Board the Nile Boat Mary Victoria, Upper Egypt. December 23rd,
               1850.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from https://archive.org/details/lettersfromegypt00brom</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/william-arnold-bromfield/letters/11">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/160825459">William Arnold
                  Bromfield</name>
               <name type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/359888">On Board the Nile Boat Mary
                  Victoria, Upper Egypt</name>
               <date when="1850-12-23">23 December 1850</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person">Eliza Bromfield</name>
               <name type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/2638911">Ryde</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>My Dear <name type="person" ref="#eliza_bromfield">E</name>
            </p>

         <p>My last sheet left us at Luxor, on the evening of the 20th, moored close to the shore
            for the night, and just starting to take such a hasty glance at its lions, as we at
            present propose to indulge ourselves with: intending to make their more intimate
            acquaintance on our return down the mighty river, whose broad stream we shall then have
            navigated.</p>

         <p>The town of Luxor is like every other in Egypt, an accumulation of mean houses of
            unburnt brick, and mud hovels, but the beautiful country in which it stands on the wide
            and fertile plain of <name type="place" ref="#thebes">Thebes</name>, and the massy ruins
            of the great temple of Amunoph III and Eameses II, together with the colossal obelisk,
            the fellow to which now adoms the Place de la Concorde at Paris, rising high above the
            modern walls, give Luxor a more imposing aspect from whatever side you approach it, than
            any of the places we have yet seen on the banks of the Nile. But excepting the obelisk
            which stands isolated in the middle of the town, and is truly a fine object, from its
            gigantic size, height, and perfect condition, one must be deeply imbued with the
            antiquarian spirit, to fall into raptures with any other of the existing re: mains of
            Theban magnificence. The ruins at Luxor struck Mr. P. and myself, as ponderous
            structures, quite devoid of elegance of design, and finished execution, and, excepting
            the great pylon (portico or gateway), forming the principal entrance to the temple, and
            facing the river, little else of these remains is in a state to give us much idea of
            what the effect of the entire building might have been in the palmy days of the Egyptian
            Monarchy; so much are they encumbered with and en: croached upon by the mounds of
            rubbish, and miserable hovels of more recent times, crammed into every avail: able
            corner of the ancient walls which could be made subservient to the uses of a modern
            population. The colossal statues of Rameses II are more than half con: cealed by the
            accumulation of soil around them, and are besides much mutilated. The sculptured
            ornaments and hieroglyphics are not numerous at Luxor, and seemed alike poor in
            conception and in execution: the closer examination we intend making on our return, may
            disclose beauties unseen during the very superficial view we took on our upward voyage.
            I fear however, that the gorgeous magnificence of the temple at Dendereh, where
            grandeur, taste, and skill are so strikingly united with admirable preservation, quite
            unfitted us for relish: ing the heavy, and comparatively unadorned, barbaric, and now
            dilapidated structures of Luxor, thrown down and half buried beneath the surface of a
            soil, the accu: mulation of many ages, or hidden in great part by the squalid homes of
            the Egypt of our day. I must however again except the noble granite Obelisk of one
            enormous block, the height of which I am unable to state, but some idea may be conveyed
            of its vast proportions, whe I mention, that amidst my antiquarian researches, having an
            eye to the replenishment of onr larder on board 1 was unromantic enough to fire at what
            I took for a pigeon, perched like an idol-bird, on the very apex of this stupendous
            monolith, but which proved after all, to be an uneatable bird of prey, so indistinct
            were objects rendered by the distance from the eye, although that interval was but equal
            to the length of a single block of granite, I was prepared not to expect any very strik:
            ing remains at Luxor, as compared with other places that compose the aggregate of ruins
            named <name type="place" ref="#thebes">Thebes</name> ! for there is no special town,
            village, or other locality, so called, now in existence: still, I must own to feeling
            considerable disappointment in what I did see, and in this I had the sympathy of my
            fellow traveller, who declared himself quite as much dissatisfied as I was.</p>

         <p>The next morning, December 21st, we mounted our donkeys (as excellent as those at <name type="place" ref="#siout">Siout</name>) and with their drivers, and Ameen and
            Mohammed leading the caval: cade, we passed over part of the beautiful and extensive
            plain of <name type="place" ref="#thebes">Thebes</name>, followed by a host of unbidden
            and clamorous guides, to Karnak, about a mile and a half from Luxor, with which it is
            supposed to have been joined by a continuous avenue of sphinxes. The valley of the Nile
            at <name type="place" ref="#thebes">Thebes</name> is extremely wide, and the never:
            ceasing mountain barrier that forms its boundary on both banks, rises here into outlines
            the most abrupt and picturesque possible, aud encloses a vast plain, teeming with
            inexhaustible riches in fields of corn, cotton, indigo, and esculent vegetables of every
            description. The day was magnificent, the usual pale blue sky was without a speck, and a
            thin hot haze softened down, without im: pairing, the distinctness of the distant craggy
            steeps of the Theban mountains. High rose our expectations, as on nearing the object of
            our morning's ride, we sighted the massive columns and gateways of Karnak, through the
            long avenue of sphinxes or dromos, once the path by which votaries went from Luxor to
            the vast temple that formed a fitting termination to so magnificent an approach. But
            alas ! we were doomed to feel disappoint: ment greater than any experienced by us at
            Luxor the day before. On entering the precincts of the great temple, we became painfully
            sensible how much anti: quarian enthusiasm, and the proneness of travellers to make the
            most of every remarkable object on their route, had exaggerated the extent and
            magnificence of Karnak. I am quite ready to admit that the general effect of the
            buildings here when perfect, must have been grand, per: haps extremely so; the avenue of
            sphinxes, when entire, must have formed a noble approach to the temple, to judge from
            the most perfect of those remaining; but even the few in any tolerable preservation are
            but parts by which to judge of them when whole; the rest are reduced to small and.
            shapeless blocks of stone; and im: agination is obliged to supply that uniformity in
            mag: nitude, and excellence of workmanship, without which they must have failed in
            grandeur of effect. The truth is, we expected to find the avenue of sphinxes in much
            better preservation, and our imaginations less drawn upon to fill up deficiencies in
            this, and in most other portions of the edifice. The pylon or gate, at which the above
            avenue terminates, is undoubtedly a fine object as a whole: but the hieroglyphics and
            sculptures are poorly executed on this, and as we thought, on the most part of the
            structures at Karnak, — numbers of them being little better than such rude carvings of
            natural objects as a plough boy, or any other country lad, might easily execute with his
            knife in stone of equal softness,-flat tame scratches, instead of deeply chiselled and
            boldly designed figures, which we thought to have seen here as at Dendereh, and have
            since seen in the beautiful, and richly wrought temples at Esne and <name type="place" ref="#edfou">Edfou</name>. The columns in the grand temple at Karnak struck us both
            forcibly as being inelegant and poor in design, the ornaments of the capitals especially
            paltry, and in the worst taste, as if belonging to the earliest state of Egyptian art;
            which is one great reason perhaps why these ruins are so extravagantly be-praised, and
            their beauties magnified by the professed and zealous anti: quary, in whose eyes age is
            the greatest of recommenda: tion, and the highest of merits. The remains at Karnak are
            for the most part in a very dilapidated state, and greatly encumbered as usual with
            mounds and heaps of rubbish both of ancient and modern date, causing the various parts
            to appear isolated, as if originally uncon: nected with one another, which detracts from
            the general effect by destroying the primitive unity of design. Others have expressed
            themselves disappointed with Karnak, and many more would avow the same feeling had they
            the courage or candour to do so, or were dis: posed to view Egyptain antiquities with a
            sober un: prejudiced eye, seeing things as they really are, with all their defects as
            well as beauties, and being determined not to let imagination betray them into such
            extravagant encomiums as we meet with in many authors on this and on other subjects. A
            popular writer on Egypt gives an overdrawn picture of the " teeming vitality" of the
            Nile, enough to frighten any timid nervous person from approaching its banks. I can
            however safely assure such persons that glancing lizards are very far indeed from
            innumerable, being only seen at intervals, small, harm: less, and pretty; except it be
            their near relation the huge unwieldy crocodile, or the supposed friendly forewarner to
            man of his being nigh, the monitor lizard of the Nile, of which we have seen an
            occasional specimen basking in the sun along the stream, twice or thrice du: ring our
            voyage, and one of which Mr. P. had the good fortune to shoot with my gun from the boat,
            and which measured three feet and a half in total length. Of snakes, I have not fallen
            in with even a single example, although always on the look out for these reptiles, par:
            ticularly the cobra of Egypt, and the asp of Cleopatra, i.e., the Cerastes or horned
            viper, both of which, I hope to meet with ere long; but reptiles of this class
            (ophidians) and indeed of every other except the batrachians (frogs and toads) are seen
            but at intervals, or not at all, and (i countless insects of unimaginable forms " reduce
            themselves to a few dull, sombre looking and sober paced beetles; a large hornet is
            common, but inoffensive unless attacked; mosquitoes, in the warmer months, and common
            house flies, are, it must be owned, a serious annoyance in Egypt; but with these two ex:
            ceptions, and that of cockroaches on board the craft on the river, insects are
            remarkably few, both as individuals and species in the valley of the Nile, and are like
            the indigenous plants, not conspicuous in general for their size, colour, or variety.
            The writer I have alluded to speaks of the "rank vegetation of the Nile:" in what this
            rankness consists I am at a loss to conceive, for the Nile is in this respect unlike
            most other rivers, in that it nourishes few or no marsh plants along its banks; no
            swampy jungles, or beds of reed intrude on the deep brown alluvium that edges the stream
            along every part of its course that I have yet traversed. On the higher parts of the
            rich sandy loam (absurdly called the slime of the Nile by high flown writers),
            flourishes the only rank vegetation to be seen any where, in the shape of luxuriant
            fields of corn, cotton, tobacco, lentiles, lupines, and the thousand gifts of nature,
            which would be most welcome in its rankness to the poor hard working, and oppressed
            fellah, were he permitted to reap the fruits of his labour for Iris own benefit, and not
            for that of another. Beyond this alluvium all is dry and sandy, the earth is clothed
            with a few species of harsh coarse grasses, amongst which, the Halfeh grass (Poa
            cynosuroides), is preeminently abundant, and groves of date palms and acacias stretch
            inland to the rocky or sandy barrier that marks the limit of the valley of Egypt: beyond
            this again is the absolutely naked, solitary, sea-like desert, which in some parts, as
            for instance, near <name type="place" ref="#assouan">Assouan</name>, which we are now
            fast approaching, comes nearly to the very margin of the Nile itself. The sacred lotus
            of Egypt is not to be found in the entire valley of the Nile in modern times, having
            long since become extinct, and perhaps it was never indigenous there, but maintained by
            the care of man in a cultivated condition only. The ornithology of the Nile, is as to
            its subject, less susceptible of ex: aggeration than its zoology, for the multitudes of
            water fowl that haunt its stream, may justify the use of the word u swarming." The same
            expression might be applied with almost as much correctness to the various birds of prey
            that hover over its banks, far exceeding in variety of species, and number of
            individuals, any amount of the same tribes in other countries; and, in: deed
            constituting one of the most singular features of this strange and interesting land.
            Vast are the flocks of geese, pelicans, storks, cranes, spoonbills, flamingoes, shags,
            and other aquatic birds that overspread the river.</p>

         <p>Believe me, always, Your affectionate Brother, William Arnold Bromfield.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>