<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Cairo, June 11th, 1851.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from https://archive.org/details/lettersfromegypt00brom</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/william-arnold-bromfield/letters/19">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/160825459">William Arnold
                  Bromfield</name>
               <name type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/360630"><name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name></name>
               <date when="1851-06-11">11 June 1851</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person">Eliza Bromfield</name>
               <name type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/2638911">Ryde</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>My dear E</p>

         <p>We arrived here on the 4th, after a tedious passage from <name type="place" ref="#minieh">Minieh</name>, the wind dead against us nearly the whole way, and our
            crew obstinately determined not to exert themselves at the oars except at such times as
            suited their convenience or caprice. They had so constantly misconducted themselves
            since leaving <name type="place" ref="#assouan">Assouan</name>, and had received such
            repeated assurances from us of being mulcted of their "baksheesh" or customary douceur
            over and above their pay, that they probably felt all chance of re-establishing
            themselves in our good graces was lost, and they consequently took no further pains to
            regain their position. The boat's crew are paid by the owner, and not by the parties
            hiring it, but on the strength of their former good conduct we had advanced the men, at
            different times, pay to the amount of 1200 piastres, besides occasionally purchasing a
            sheep or goat for them to feast upon; their ordinary diet being bread and a sort of
            porridge of Indian corn, or Dhourah; meat, they cannot in general afford to buy. Yet
            this kindness which we were not called upon to evince, was lost upon these people; they
            are good humoured in the highest degree, but incorrigibly lazy and heartless. Want of
            gratitude is universally ascribed to the Arab and Berber races, and from what I have
            myself seen, the imputation is no result of prejudice, but it is really one of the
            commonest defects of their character: although from their constant good humour and
            readiness to oblige when no sacrifice and but little trouble is involved, one would not
            suspect that a want of gratitude formed so conspicuous a trait in the Arab
            character.</p>

         <p>Detained already by contrary winds far beyond our allotted time, I cannot quit <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name> till I have visited many remarkable places in
            the city and its neighbourhood, <name type="place" ref="#heliopolis">Heliopolis</name>,
            the mounds of Memphis, the pyramids of Saccareh, Abousheer, and Dashoor, the Colossi of
            Mitrahenny, the chicken-hatching ovens of Gheezeh, the Nilometer, and the quarries of
            Toureh, from whence the stones used in constructing the great pyramids were brought. I
            also propose making a trip to <name type="place" ref="#suez">Suez </name>, which in
            points of Scripture history possesses the highest interest.</p>

         <p><name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name> alone would give a traveller a good two
            months employment, in the endless variety which its labyrinthine mass of grotesque
            houses, narrow alleys, richly sculptured mosques, minarets, and tombs without number,
            offer to the eye; besides the diversity of life, of feature, of costume, and of colour,
            which the city displays, and which is scarcely to be conceived; yet, taken as a whole,
               <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name> exhibits a most melancholy picture of
            poverty, dirt, disease, and degradation; of wretched ignorance, superstition, and the
            most puerile and paltry pageantry; but bigotry and intolerance, though said to be still
            rampant, certainly do not appear on the surface at least, and I am convinced are rapidly
            giving way amongst the higher, and I think even among the lower grades of society,
            through daily increasing intercourse with Europeans. It is really quite astonishing to
            see the improvements that have been made in <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>
            since my first visit last autumn; ranges of handsome shops in the Frank quarter have
            been opened, and others are still in progress of completion, which let at quite a
            European rental.</p>

         <p>It is confidently asserted that a contract has been made by the Pasha for the immediate
            construction of a railway, from <name type="place" ref="#alexandria">Alexandria </name>
            to <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>, and that Mr. Stephenson will be the
            engineer to carry it into effect. The French are losing ground fast in Egypt, and the
            English rising as much in the estimation of the government. An Englishman can do almost
            anything here he likes, and of the respect in which the British name and character are
            held, we ought to feel very proud. The Moslem even respects our Church; because with all
            their contempt for other Christian sects, they say we do not bow down before images as
            they of the Greek and Roman and Coptic churches do.</p>

         <p>Believe me, Dear E., Your affectionate Brother, William Arnold Bromfield.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>