<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sheppard's British Hotel, Uzbekieh, <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>,
               October 29th, 1850.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from https://archive.org/details/lettersfromegypt00brom</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/william-arnold-bromfield/letters/3">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/160825459">William Arnold
                  Bromfield</name>
               <name type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/360630">Sheppard's British Hotel,
                  Uzbekieh, <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>
                    </name>
               <date when="1850-10-29">29 October 1850</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person">Eliza Bromfield</name>
               <name type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/2638911">Ryde</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p> My dear <name type="person" ref="#eliza_bromfield">E</name>
            </p>

         <p>In my last letter dispatched from this interestingcity, I had not space left for any
            account of my voyage of thirty hours from <name type="place" ref="#alexandria">Alexandria </name>, which I shall now proceed with, before giving you my impressions
            of <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>, of which I have already seen some of
            the chief lions, including the Pasha himself. The heat, though much below what it is a
            month earlier, still continues very high for the season, keeping steadily at 80° or 82°
            during the day; this morning at eight o'clock it was only 78°, and the sun when not
            veiled as it was yesterday by thin stratified clouds, is scorchingly hot, and the nights
            are still so warm that a single sheet is an ample covering under the mosquito net, which
            of course is a necessary evil, as it obstructs the ingress of cool, and the egress of
            heated air. Captain Lindguist, who has been residing six years at <name type="place" ref="#suez">Suez </name>, as an agent of the Oriental company, or Transit
            administration, tells me, that when here in ordinary seasons, he is accustomed to have a
            fire in his office from the 1st of November, and that this year the cold was so long
            protracted, that he did not leave off fires till the 25th of April, which really seems
            incredible in this latitude, 30°, and at the sea level. Mr. Trail, late gardener to
            Ibrahim Pasha at Rhoda, for whom I had a letter and pamphlet from Sir W. J. Hooker, and
            whom I traced out to his abode at Old <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>
            yesterday, informs me, that hoar frost is no uncommon tiling here in the winter
            mornings, and that he has seen ice, (thin of course), formed on pools in the desert ;
            probably more through the brisk evaporation by the wind in this dry climate, than
            through the actually low temperature of the atmosphere. At present, I do not conceive
            that the most chilly person in the world would think of a fire in his room without a
            double distillation of lily dew at every pore, from the bare idea; but the temperature
            will perhaps fall rapidly when it begins to sink, and I am thankful when I look on the
            warm clothing, flannel waistcoats, &amp;c, which I had the precaution to add to my
            travelling list on leaving England.</p>

         <p>I left <name type="place" ref="#alexandria">Alexandria </name> at 5 p.m. on the 24th, in
            one of the boats for the conveyance to <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name> of
            ordinary passengers, (not going to India), and which is tracked by a small steamer that
            likewise has passengers on board, on the Mahmoudeh canal, as far as Atfeh, where the
            canal joins the Xile, and where a steamer of a larger size waits to receive the
            passengers and their luggage, and take them on to <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>. These boats belong to the Transit administration, which is entirely in
            the hands of the Pasha, The time of departure was unfortunate, inasmuch as the most
            interesting part of the trip on the canal to Atfeh was performed in the dark, and indeed
            for most part of the night in a thick fog which shrouded from view all that a bright,
            but rather late rising moon would have revealed of the banks on either side of the
            canal. Hence, I got no sight of the former situation of Sais, once the capital of the
            Delta, and the new buildings at Atfeh, the locks, &amp;c, were but dimly caught sight of
            across the mist which wetted everything on deck, and caused some unpleasant reflections
            on intermittent or remittent fever to cross my mind occasionally, as a few hours before
            embarking the heat was very great, and the air now felt chilly as well as damp, and I
            wished for a great coat in addition to the light clothing 1 had on, not desiring to be
            in the cabin below, which was crowded and insufferably close. We arrived at Atfeh before
            daybreak, and the fog on the river did not clear away till some hours after sunrise.
            Shortly after leaving <name type="place" ref="#alexandria">Alexandria </name>, we heard
            a great splashing in the canal, and much stir and vociferation on board the steamer,
            which caused us novices some alarm, as we imagined that a man had fallen overboard; it
            turned out to be only the landing a passenger, which was accomplished by his divesting
            himself of every article of clothing, then jumping overboard and swimming ashore, his
            wardrobe, previously made into a bundle, being flung after him. Our starting point on
            the Mahmoudeh Canal was about two miles from the hotel; the canal itself is of great
            width, and a wonderful undertaking, when one considers that it was finished through its
            entire length of about fifty miles, within a twelvemonth: but the reflection that the
            convenience to travellers derived from it was owing to a terrible exercise of arbitrary
            power, and attended with a fearful sacrifice of human life, became the predominant
            feeling at the sight of it.</p>

         <p>Night soon closed in and hid the country from view, but that part of it which we saw on
            quitting <name type="place" ref="#alexandria">Alexandria </name> was pretty in its way,
            the banks of the canal being diversified with white villas, gardens, and small
            cultivated fields of maize, melons, and different kinds of vegetables, with fine
            sycamore and acacia trees planted along the roads. The night passed slowly and
            disagreeably owing to the thick wet fog on deck, and the stifling closeness of the cabin
            below, where, however I could have slept away the hours well enough, had there been room
            to lie down, but every place, even to the tables was occupied by recumbent passengers,
            Turks, Italians, Greeks, and non-descripts of all nations, by some of whom it would not
            have been prudent or agreeable to have bivouacked, and the cabin smelt strongly of
            tobacco, and odours less refined even than that. We had one distinguished person on
            board, of no less rank than a Pasha, I think he was called Kheredden Pasha, or something
            very like it, a stout middle-aged, jovial personage, with a round good humoured
            countenance, and jet black beard, who fared like any of the other passengers, and spent
            his time in smoking and playing cards. He wore the insignia of a Pasha, a crescent and
            star of diamonds on the vest in front, and the dress of a Turkish field officer and
            admiral, as he belongs to both services, and was present at the battle of Navarino. I
            understand that he contracts to furnish the Transit administration with butchers' meat,
            which is not thought derogatory to the high dignity he has attained. A day or two after
            this arrangement was made, he invited all the officers of the administration to a dinner
            in <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>, at which, I am told that the cham-
            pagne, which is his Highness' pet beverage, flowed without scant. The diamond decoration
            of the star and crescent is conferred with the rank, but is only lent so long as the
            Pasha continues in favour; at his death, or deposition, it reverts to the Sultan, but
            may be purchased like any other jewel by the family. No ceremony was observed towards
            him while on board; he ate 3 drank, talked, and smoked, like all the rest, and his
            Highness favoured us with his company in an omnibus expedition on the Desert, which he
            appeared to enjoy as much as any of us. I fancy however that Khereddin Pasha holds a
            sort of brevet rank, as I understand he has no province to rule over: he is said to be a
            man of great energy and some talent: he certainly is marvellously inclined to good
            fellowship, and I think were he in power, could never prove a harsh or tyrannical
            governor, to judge from his countenance only.</p>

         <p>During the whole of the 24th we had a good view of the Delta through which we passed.
            The features are very tame, and monotonously uniform. The yellow turbid Nile flowing
            between crumbling banks of brown alluvial soil, which offers nothing but a perfect dead
            level over which large towns and villages are thickly dispersed, each an assemblage of
            the most miserable hovels of mud or unburnt brick, with here and there a tenement or two
            of rather better description, perhaps the residence of the sheyk, or chief man of the
            village. Many of these places are of considerable size, and all have one or more
            mosques, the minarets of which are the only buildings that have the smallest pretension
            to anything like architectural design or skill. Of these towns or large villages, no one
            but the Arab knows the names, so that could I have remembered them 3 there was no
            possibility of learning their different designations: some of them were doubtless on the
            sites of ancient places of celebrity. Groves of date-palms which here shoot up to fifty,
            sixty, and seventy feet, usually surround these places, with here and there a spreading
            sycamore or acacia. A most oppressive tax of three piastres annually is levied on every
            date tree, which, when their great number is considered, and the extreme poverty of the
            inhabitants, must be a cruel impost, but I have great doubts of the correctness of the
            statement, as a tax of rather more than sixpence on every tree, where these amount to
            many hundreds, perhaps even thousands, is more than I can well conceive so destitute a
            population able to pay, being mainly, if not entirely made up of fellahs or cultivators
            of the soil, a wretched, half clad race, of coarse, ugly features, and squalid to the
            last degree. Camels, dromedaries, donkeys, and huge buffaloes, with a few dark brown
            sheep, are their chief possessions; the buffaloes may be seen continually lying in mid
            river, with their noses alone out of the water, or swimming across to the opposite bank,
            quiet inoffensive animals, used both for draught and burden. We remarked many persons
            ploughing with a camel and a buffalo yoked together in most ill assorted fellowship.
            Dovecotes swarming with myriads of pigeons, rose high above the houses in some of the
            larger towns,, of a conical shape, like immense haystacks, and pierced with innumerable
            holes for the birds to enter in and come out. Pigeons are a great article of consumption
            in Egypt, where poultry takes the place of butchers' meat in a great measure. These
            Egyptian towns have the same light brown colour as the soil; there is nothing to break
            the uniformity of their aspect, no contrast of colouring; the only arborescent
            vegetation is the date palm dispersed in groups, or forming groves, but giving no shade,
            which can only be had under an occasional acacia, sycamore, or nabr, a gigantic but
            common species of buckthorn, the small fruit of which is eaten by the Arabs : while the
            unvarying glare, and sameness of splendour in the sky, must soon fatigue and satiate the
            eye that has no diversity of scenery or of objects to turn to for relief on the earth
            beneath. The flats of Holland have more to interest than the Delta of the Nile; for
            there one sees a population flourishing in plenty and comfort: here, nothing but a
            people in the lowest condition as regards civilization, poor, and oppressed beyond that
            of any other country. I was coniderably disappointed in the verdure of the Delta, of
            which one hears so much: the cultivation, such as it is, appears to occupy patches; a
            great part of the river banks is still untilled, and either bare of vegetation, or
            producing coarse herbage, the nature of which I could not determine, but it is most
            monotonous in its character, and we were seldom near enough to the shore to ascertain
            the kind of crop with certainty. Maize seemed to be one of the most important
            productions, and I remarked sugar and tobacco occasionally, as also cotton, but many of
            the crops were only now springing up, the Nile having so lately begun to subside. From
            the low level of the steamer's deck no extensive view of the Delta can be obtained. Not
            even from the flat roof of this hotel, which is of very considerable height, nor from
            the still loftier elevation of the citadel, which offers one of the most magnificent
            panoramas in the world, can I descry anything of that lake-like appearance the country
            is said to present at the season of u hio-h Nile." I had fine views of the Delta from
            the skirts of the desert on the way to <name type="place" ref="#suez">Suez </name> two
            days ago, but at an elevation much too low, and with a sky too hazy to distinguish
            objects clearly. The effect was that of a Dutch landscape by one of the old masters,
            with much of that indistinctness which age gives to an oil painting, of a couple of
            centuries ago.</p>

         <p>We passed the Barrage, where the Nile is prevented by strong embankments from subsiding
            in the Delta till the irrigation of the land is complete; and our approach to <name type="place" ref="#boulak">Boulak</name>, the port of <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>, did not take place till 10, p.m. of the 25th. We landed amidst a
            confused hubbub of camels, donkeys, and vociferous and quarrelsome Arabs, and found Mr.
            Sheppard, the proprietor of the English Hotel at which I am staying, ready, with two or
            three omnibuses, to whirl us away along an excellent road bordered with thriving acacias
            to his establishment in this magnificent Square, the Usbekeih, about a mile and a half
            distant from <name type="place" ref="#boulak">Boulak</name>.</p>

         <p>November 1st. This place is immeasurably above <name type="place" ref="#alexandria">Alexandria </name> in point of interest, as regards variety, comfort, and beauty;
            from the flat roof of this hotel I have a splendid view of the city, with its thousand
            mosques and minarets; and above all, conspicuous in the distance to the S.S.W,, yet
            seemingly close at hand, the mighty pyramids of Ghizeh, appearing like mountains against
            the pale blue sky; but with my invaluable companion at my side, the telescope, I can
            distinctly bring all the ranges of stone composing them into view. Below me is a waving
            sea of foliage, from rows of fine acacias, ( Acacia Lebbek ), sycomores of scripture,
            (Ficus Sycomorus), and other trees, with which the fine esplanade is thickly planted,
            but there is not an atom of turf, scarcely a blade of grass, or weed of any kind beneath
            the trees; all is bare ground, as in the desert — a poor, thin, wiry grass is only seen
            here and there in spots artificially irrigated.</p>

         <p>My delight is to mount the roof about sun-set, and watch the departing rays, bringing
            out the pyramids in stronger and stronger relief as darkness approaches, till at length
            they can just be discerned as two dark masses like little mountains on the skirts of the
            desert. I have witnessed one or two splendid sunsets since my arrival in Egypt, but more
            frequently they have been dull and vapoury, the sky pale and milky by day, with dim
            starlight by night.</p>

         <p>To day, November 2nd, the heavens are quite overspread with a thin veil of white vapour,
            with a faint blue sky, streaked and speckled with fleecy clouds, (^mackerel sky), here
            and there. We have had little else but south and south east winds lately, most
            unfavourable for travellers going up the Nile. Accounts have just been received from the
            Red Sea of the cholera having committed most dreadful ravages at Jeddah, the port of
               <name type="place" ref="#mecca">Mecca</name>, among the pilgrims now assembled there.
               <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name> is at present quite free from the
            visitation. All residents with whom I have conversed, on the subject, are unan- imous in
            asserting that the season of greatest heat in <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>, (that is, from July to September inclusive), is the freest of all the
            four from sickness of every kind, al- though inducing much personal discomfort; and that
            the winter is in fact the time looked upon by the inhabitants as the least healthy, on
            account of the comparative dampness of the air, and the vicissitudes of temperature.
            Although the cool season has commenced, the heat is still very considerable. I have not
            seen it under 80° night or morning, and at mid-day in my room I have noted it as high as
            83 '. As the sun now sets before half-past five, the union of such short days with such
            long hot nights makes one feel as if one was between the tropics, as the temperature
            just now is as high and as agreeable as in the West Indies. It was at 90°, I understand,
            at <name type="place" ref="#alexandria">Alexandria </name> a few days ago. This house is
            quite modern, indeed almost new, with very thick stone walls, but from the bad clumsy
            fitting, and want of finish about the woodwork and painting, which last is never
            "renewed after the first application, you would suppose the building to be a century
            old. The room I occupy is a large, airy apartment, with whitewashed walls, coarsely
            coloured in fresco below in a sort of imitation of panel wainscoting of a slate colour,
            bordered with dark red brown, above which is a sort of fleur-de-lys pattern impressed on
            the walls in flaming scarlet ! The room, which has a south aspect, is nearly a square of
            about twenty-four feet, and has an alcoved roof, very little, if at all, less in height
            from the well laid stone floor, and finished in a cornice and oval of unpainted wood,
            pierced in an open pattern, displaying neither taste nor skill in design. Three very
            large glazed sash windows nearly fill up the front side, which looks on the Uzbekeih,
            and immediately below them runs a raised stone dado, covered with luxurious cushions or
            divans, of blue printed calico, which with window curtains to match, a light iron
            bedstead with mosquito curtains of thin muslin, &amp;c. &amp;c. complete the furniture
            of my domicile, which is very comfortable at this season, but I suspect, must prove cold
            in the winter. Mr. Sheppard is fitting up new premises on a more extensive scale than
            these, with every convenience for English travellers. The charges are forty piastres per
            diem, six shillings and eight-pence, if by the week; or fifty piastres, eight shillings
            and four-pence, for a less time. This includes lodging and board, which last consists of
            a most substantial breakfast at half-past eight, luncheon, with fruit, at one, dinner,
            (excellent), at half-past six, with a cup of coffee afterwards; but no tea, unless
            required, and paid for as an extra.</p>

         <p>I find <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name> an extremely amusing place, and from
            its great size, its novelties are not soon exhausted. The population is variously
            stated, from eighty thousand to two hundred and fifty thousand, and together with old
               <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name> and <name type="place" ref="#boulak">Boulak</name>, which may be called suburbs, the extent of ground it covers is very
            great. For five piastres, or one shilling, I can get a donkey, (of which animal the
            choice is inexhaustible), for the whole day, on which, or sometimes on foot, I thread
            the inextricable labyrinth of crooked streets, lanes and alleys, of which the city is
            made up, trusting to chance to bring me into some familiar street, or open place from
            whence I can direct my steps homewards again. No one who has not visited <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name> can form an adequate idea of these strange
            thoroughfares, from the published views made from drawings by the cleverest artists;
            because none that I have seen, convey any just notion of the extreme dinginess and
            dilapidation that everywhere meet the eye. The worst parts of London cannot be compared
            with the residences of even the respectable class of Cairenes. The houses are solidly
            built of stone, at least as high as the basement story, which is commonly pierced with
            low doorways, gates, and iron barred windows, sometimes having quaint carvings or Arabic
            inscriptions above them, but mostly very dungeon -like in appearance, and opening into
            receptacles for dust and rubbish, or into square courts, which give light and air to the
            residents on the next and succeeding stories, — for the basement is seldom or never, I
            believe, inhabited, unless it may be by the poorer classes. The part of the house above
            the basement usually projects forward on timber beams, and presents a confused mass of
            plaster, with windows glazed, or more commonly with a cagelike projection, carved or
            rather pierced in elaborate patterns of brown unpainted wood. Some, however, of the
            principal thoroughfares are more regular, in better repair, and wider, and the city
            exhibits a variety of architecture that appears absolutely inexhaustible. You come at
            almost every step to some mosque, arched gate, or passage covered with tracery, or
            painted in various colours, and with Arabic inscriptions in fresco, or sculptured on the
            stone, for the most part in miserable taste and execution, but at other times in a style
            of elegance and finish, that surprises you by the taste and artistic skill displayed,
            and by the strange contrasts of the decorations on perhaps the same building. Some of
            the lanes or alleys are so narrow that there is barely room for a single donkey to
            squeeze himself through, but these are not either common or much frequented: very few of
            the streets are wider than the narrowest alley in London, and are always thronged with
            pedestrians, donkeys and their riders, with horses, camels, and occasionally with
            carriages and carts. I had been led to suppose that much caution and circumspection were
            required in riding through the streets and lanes of <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>, to avoid accidents from collision with camels and wheeled carriages,
            but I find it the easiest and safest thing in the world to pass through the narrowest
            and most densely crowded thoroughfares, both on foot and on a donkey. In the latter case
            the animal seems to know how to save you the trouble of guiding him, and threads his way
            through the crowd with an adroitness that is surprising, even at a full trot or amble,
            their only serious defect being that they are apt to come down with you sometimes, (an
            accident which has not yet happened to me), and when it does occur, is in general only a
            subject for laughter. The pace of the camel is so extremely slow, that though noiseless,
            there is very little difficulty in avoiding; a string of these animals on meeting them,
            but there is a possibility of their coming against you unawares from behind, since
            unless furnished with bells, which is not always the case, their tread is quite
            inaudible, and you might be swept off your donkey by the enormous loads which project
            from their sides: but I have not witnessed or heard of such an occurrence. The approach
            of a carriage is always announced in time to avoid it, by a courier on foot, who cracks
            a ponderous whip to clear the way. Every one of rank amongst the natives, on driving, or
            riding out on horseback, is preceded by a running footman, attired with sash or girdle,
            bringing to mind the act of Elijah girding up his loins, and running before the chariot
            of Ahab to the entrance of Jezreel. The donkeys have been called the cabs of <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>, and truly the comparison holds both as to
            their number and convenience. These animals literally swarm, as they are used equally by
            high and low, and you can never be at a loss for one in whatever part of the town you
            may chance to find yourself, but you will have to contend against a host of donkey boys,
            each endeavouring with loud vociferations to force his own donkey upon your notice as
            super-eminent for all valuable asinine qualities above its fellows. Fortunately these
            creatures are not much given to kicking, otherwise, it might fare ill with the
            pedestrian whilst making his selection from a dozen or more, all hustling and jostling,
            head and heels turned towards himself, (the centre of the group), indifferently. Their
            pace, whether amble, trot, or gallop, is extremely easy, and the saddles are famously
            padded; the pommel is very high and stuffed like a cushion, which in the event of a
            tumble must be a great advantage. The donkey boy accompanies you, to urge on the animal
            with his stick, and constant cry of "oai, oai," without which appliances, an Egyptian
            donkey could no more be incited to active locomotion than his English brethren by those
            of similar import, from whom I was surprised to find them, after what I had heard of
            their qualities, capabilities and appearance, differ so little. English donkeys that
            have been well treated and looked after, I do not think are inferior to those of Egypt
            in any points of importance. The race here is generally of rather slighter make, the
            legs longer, and flanks thinner than at home, indicating as we should say, more of blood
            ; they are perhaps also more active, but are not superior in size, and require as much
            urging to make them go, when not accompanied by their drivers, as ours usually do. Still
            they are admirable little animals for the service they have to perform, that of winding
            their way through over crowded streets, where horses could not find a passage in equal
            numbers, or with equal safety. I saw a donkey the other day with dark stripes across the
            legs, as if a cross with the Zebra; but as that creature does not inhabit Egypt or
            Northern Africa, the darker markings may have had some other origin.</p>

         <p>With kindest regards to all our friends, Believe me, Your affectionate Brother, William
            Arnold Bromfield. </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>