<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sheppard's Hotel, Usbekieh, <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>, November 7th, 1850.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from https://archive.org/details/lettersfromegypt00brom</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/william-arnold-bromfield/letters/4">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/160825459">William Arnold
                  Bromfield</name>
               <name type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/360630">Sheppard's Hotel, Usbekieh,
                     <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name></name>
               <date when="1850-11-07">7 November 1850</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person">Eliza Bromfield</name>
               <name type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/2638911">Ryde</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>My dear <name type="person" ref="#eliza_bromfield">E</name></p>

         <p>Having returned from an expedition to the Pyramids yesterday, I hasten to give you a
            narrative of our proceedings to and from those wonderful structures, and the impression
            they made on my mind, whilst quite fresh from the visit. Amongst the passengers by the
            Austrian Lloyds vessel from Trieste, which arrived at <name type="place" ref="#alexandria">Alexandria </name> on the 3rd, was a gentleman with whom I got into
            conversation at the table d'hote here, and who proved to be an intimate friend and
            neighbour of Mr. L. V. H — — , and whom I recollect having met at W. D. a few years
            back. ( He and his son were intending to see the Pyramids if possible before leaving
               <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>, and proposed my joining them, an
            arrangement to which I readily assented, and we agreed to set off the same afternoon,
            and taking a tent and provisions with us, to bivouack at the Pyramids that night, and
            rise fresh for their examination at daybreak. Our train consisted of four donkeys for
            our party of three, and the dragoman, besides a spare donkey, and their attendant
            drivers, and a horse for carrying the tent, some spare clothing, thick horse cloths
            instead of mats, a large chest or box for provisions, knives, forks, glasses, &amp;c;
            the provisions consisting of cold chicken, a cold goose, ditto roast shoulder of mutton,
            bread, cheese, coffee, sugar and eggs, a few bottles of pale ale, one of water, and
            another of brandy. We mounted our donkeys about half-past four, a great deal too late in
            the day for a journey of eighteen miles, which is the distance of the Pyramids from
               <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name> during the time of high Nile, or the
            season of inundation; but we had been riding about the city, to the citadel, and
            elsewhere all the morning, and Mr, W had engagements that detained him till late in the
            afternoon, leaving us only an hour before sunset, which in this latitude, and in the
            beginning of November, happens at half-past five o'clock, and the twilight afterwards is
            not of very long duration. Our route lay through Old <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>, (which stands on the site of the fortress of Babylon), we then crossed
            the Nile in a ferry boat to the large and populous village of Geezeh or Ghizeh, (Arabic
            names are spelt in various ways, and the g is either hard or soft according to the
            dialect), from whence these Pyramids take their names. The views on the Nile at Old
               <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name> and Geezeh are very pretty, white
            houses, on either side of the broad river, being interspersed everywhere with trees,
            gardens, date groves, and the island of Rhoda, clad in rich cultivation, occupying the
            centre of the Nile. The way from Old to New <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>
            is a fine broad road, planted with trees, and through one continuous garden of olive,
            fig, mulberry, castor, or prickly pear, &amp;c, beneath which grow all the kinds of
            esculent vegetables for which Egypt was formerly renowned, as leeks, onions, garlic,
            lentils, lettuce, beans, melons, and many others. After leaving Geezeh the daylight
            began to fail us, but the twilight lasted us still for a few miles farther, and when the
            new moon set, the Evening star shone with such brilliancy as to supply her place nearly
            as well. The roads at this season of the inundation ran over the broad embankment
            between the now inundated fields, which give the country the aspect of a vast inland sea
            or lake, studded with islands^ and intersected with isthmuses and long promontories. The
            night was beautifully clear, and deliciously cool, and the Pyramids were always in view,
            seen in deep relief against the sky, but for a long time we never seemed to approach any
            nearer to them. At length we unexpectedly came to a spot where the weight of the w r
            ater had forced a passage through the embankment in two places, and made it impossible
            for our donkeys to proceed further, and we began to fear that we should have to pass the
            night on this narrow causeway, between two inundated tracts of land; but our dragoman
            comforted us with the assurance, that by shouting, and shewing our lantern, (which we
            did by perching the dragoman on the horse's back, and making him a living Pharos), a
            sailing boat would put off to the breach from the shore beneath the Pyramids, or from a
            village near at hand, which we could dimly descry. We had, however, to wait about an
            hour before the boat arrived, during which time the dew fell, and the air began to be
            chilly; but to this, our half naked Arabs did not appear to be in the least degree
            sensible. We amused ourselves with getting the provision chest unloaded from the horse,
            and making a good supper upon the contents, the chest itself serving for table and
            chairs. When the boat came, we put our tent, clothes, and the above mentioned chest into
            it, and proceeded with our dragoman, who was also our cook, (Mohammed by name), over
            inundated fields, destined to become in a few month's time, dry and verdant with the
            fruits of the East — but now the habitation of innumerable frogs, and myriads of water
            fowl, — to the landing place beneath the Pyramids, which we reached about ten o'clock,
            p.m. The horse, donkeys, and donkey boys, remained under the open canopy of heaven at
            the broken down embank- ment till our return, about two, p.m., the next day, with no
            other covering than the scanty clothing they had on, which is very frequently not even
            as much as strict decency requires.</p>

         <p>The ascent from the usual landing place towards the Pyramids is long and steep. We
            arrived at a row of tombs, hewn out of the rock, still much below the Pyramids, close in
            front of which we soon found ourselves, and pitched our tents on the soil composed of
            debris of sepulchres, pottery, &amp;c, mixed with sand and stones, and were immediately
            visited by the Shekh of the village, and his posse of chattering Arabs, whose
            vociferations never ceased for a moment, till the picturesque guard was set for the
            night, when they subsided into low gossiping tones that continued audible till I fell
            asleep on my horse cloth, which with a thick pilot cloth great coat and flannel under
            garments, in addition to the ordinary upper ones of coat, &amp;c, I found insufficient
            wholly to ward off the cold of the desert air, even under the shelter of a tent, for the
            wind blew in upon us from under it all night, though not with any great violence. A
            French traveller and his party were encamped in another tent near us, having the tri-
            coloured flag displayed.</p>

         <p>The next morning we were up a little before sun-rise, (about half-past six), and saw
            that luminary emerge, and light up a beautiful and singular landscape, the rich
            inundated valley of the Nile, with the villages rising like islands out of the watery
            expanse, which teems with incredible numbers of geese and other water birds at this
            season. From our elevated position, looking northwards, we distinctly saw <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name> with its lofty citadel, and the magnificent
            mosque of Mohammed Ali crowning all; the Pyramids were behind us, high above our heads,
            and even their tops concealed by the steep intervening hills of coarse sand and gravel,
            stones of all sizes, angular blocks of basalt, reddish granite, and soft white limestone
            rock on which the Pyramids stand, and of which they are mainly composed, pebbles of
            agate, rounded by attrition, fragments of pottery, (coarse red earth er ii ware ), ibis
            vases, human and other bones, and a strange assemblage of debris, belonging to different
            epochs and formations, amongst which is one having a volcanic appearance like lava or
            tufa, and very decomposable, whilst portions of the white limestone which is soft enough
            to be cut with a knife, are a complete mass of shells. I also picked up near the
            Pyramids of Cephrenes fragments of a hard rock of a violet or even puce colour, of which
            I saw no block of any size. As soon as the sun had risen we toiled up to the base of the
            greater pyramid. To say that it came up to, or fell short of, or exceeded my
            expectations of its magnitude, would not express the impression I received from its
            contemplation, and that of the whole group, so unlike did I find the reality to all the
            representations I have seen of these enormous structures. Their exterior is far more
            rude and rugged, from time and wilful spoliation than I had any conception of; and I can
            compare them, on a close approach, to nothing so much as to the products of some vast
            stone quarry, shaped into roughly squared blocks, broken and chipped in the process, and
            piled into a huge pyramid for convenience of transport, or use upon the spot. So great
            is their magnitude, that at a very moderate distance, say half a mile or less, the
            dilapidation of the courses of stone becomes almost invisible, and the pyramidal outline
            stands forth in all the symmetrical regularity which these structures possessed when
            their casing was entire, and as they appear in drawings and prints of them taken from a
            distance. They are chiefly built of a greyish or yellowish white limestone, easily cut
            with a knife, and approaching in texture to indurated chalk of the Freshwater cliffs,
            not indeed quite so soft, but almost as white, and of different degrees of hardness,
            often full of shells. I brought away pieces of the great pyramid of Cheops, and
            specimens of the mortar or cement used to unite them, which is harder than the stone
            itself. Mr. W — — , who seems quite an antiquary, could see nothing in the Pyramids but
            what was matter for wonder and astonishment, and like the rest of his brethren,
            professed to find deep skill and science in the architectural details. To myself, they
            seem very inartificial structures, requiring only a knowledge of the common principles
            of levelling, and the application of the most ordinary mechanical means, to rear them.
            With the exception of the vast granite blocks that form the entrance and the walls of
            the interior chambers, the extreme softness of the limestone offered great facility to
            the workmen employed on that material for the courses; and as to the raising and placing
            these blocks in situ, I had, long before I saw them, doubted the supposed difficulty of
            that process, on which people are so fond of expatiating. In this doubt I am more than
            ever confirmed, by observing on the spot the great inferiority of these blocks in regard
            to size, to the exaggerated accounts usually given by travellers of their enormous
            dimensions, which are in truth, no greater than those of similar blocks in ordinary use
            for our own solid public works, and vastly smaller than the gigantic masses employed in
            the Breakwater at Plymouth. It would not be fair to charge the manifest inequality of
            size as a defect in stones intended to be hidden from view by a solid exterior casing,
            such as there seems no doubt, once encrusted the Pyramids, and of which a part still
            remains in good preservation about the summit of the second pyramid, or that of
            Cephrenes; but this casing would appear to have been after all, but a mere coating of
            stucco or concrete. The cement has worked Out from between most of the blocks, leaving
            them in a degree disconnected, and numbers of them are displaced wholly or partially, or
            have fallen to the bottom, and have shivered into those fragments which compose the very
            soil for a great distance around the base of the Pyramids. No one will contend that
            there is any beauty whatever in these structures; even when perfect, they could have had
            none, and yet they must be objects of surpassing interest to any person possessing a
            spark of imagination.</p>

         <p>At first we contented ourselves with such a glance at them as could be got by ascending
            the steep hill on which that of Cheops and Cephrenes stand; for being on the point of
            commencing the ascent, the keen morning air reminded us that we had not breakfasted: so
            in spite of the vociferations of the Arabs who act as guides, and who hovered around us
            like a swarm of bees, worrying us at every step with their impertinent importunities, we
            returned to our tent, where we found our trusty Mohammed busily engaged in preparing a
            substantial breakfast of omelettes and excellent Mocha coffee, which being dispatched,
            we returned to the great Pyramid to make the ascent in earnest, having before only stood
            on the lowermost course or two of stones, and satisfied ourselves of the truth of the
            assertion, that the vast size of the Pyramids is only apparent when you are in actual
            contact with them; at the distance of even a few hundred yards they lose half of their
            really gigantic proportions. Another peculiarity about them, and which I have not seen
            noticed by any traveller, is, that when you approach within a hundred yards or less of
            the Pyramid, the fore-shortening of the sloping face of the side you are looking on, has
            the curious effect to the eye of a perpendicular wall of rough masonry, tapering to a
            point of course, but all idea of its forming one side of a pyramid is dispelled by this
            illusive appearance. Excepting from their extremely dilapidated condition, the Pyramids
            convey no impression of antiquity: for in this climate, no moss or lichen seems capable
            of existing, and the stones might have been piled up within the memory of a child, for
            any of those indications of age which the lower tribes of vegetation in damper regions
            impart to masonry through lapse of time; the colour of the stone is as light and fresh
            as if just quarried.</p>

         <p>I had no idea that the Pyramids stood on so elevated a site; I do not know the
            elevation, but you look down from the table land at their base into the plain of the
            Nile below, as if from the summit of a very high cliff; indeed, their situation was one
            of the points on which my pre-conceived notions were completely at variance with the
            fact, nor have I ever seen any drawings that give a just idea of the position of the
            Pyramids and the scenery around them. The deeply undulating surface exhibits a scene of
            utter desolation, not a blade of grass springs upon, nor does the faintest tint of green
            enliven the pale brownish white waste, composed of debris and coarse sandy gravel, mixed
            with fragments of pottery, and human bones thrown out from the tombs. The ascent and
            descent of the great Pyramid has often been described as an arduous undertaking; it is
            certainly somewhat tiring, but I found both going up and coming down, very far easier
            than I expected, and excepting perhaps for ladies, it is no achievement at all. With by
            no means a strong head for climbing dizzy heights, I found I could look down from any
            part of the ascent without the least feeling whatever of giddiness, and should
            infinitely have preferred being allowed to scale the Pyramids unattended, and to have
            taken my own time in the ascent; but that, the officious importunate Arabs would never
            allow strangers to do, as they would thereby lose a chance of getting Bakscheesh from
            him, were he simple enough to comply with their demands, which are almost incessant from
            the moment he arrives, to the instant he leaves the Pyramids. To a person in good
            health, the chief, if not the only source of fatigue in ascending, consists in the
            rapidity with which he scrambles to the summit, urged on by the Arabs, who will not
            allow him a moment's rest, but continue pulling and pushing him up the successive
            courses of stones; when if he were allowed quietly and deliberately to select his own
            footing, he might reach the summit nearly as fresh as when he began to mount. The ascent
            is generally made at the north east angle, and the blocks are mostly so broken and
            disjointed, that in the space of a few yards of every course, there is seldom wanting a
            place for the feet to enable the climber to get on to the course next above him, without
            being obliged to raise himself up the whole height of the block, and wear out his knees
            in planting them on the top of the range: but the Arabs insist on taking you up partly
            by this exertion on your own side, partly by the pulling and pushing process on theirs,
            under the idea that your vanity will be gratified by arriving at the platform before any
            other of your companions. A considerable portion of the angle is broken away about
            two-thirds from the top, and here travellers generally halt for a few minutes to take
            breath, if the guides will let them, before completing the ascent. The descent, often
            pictured as quite formidable compared with the ascent, I found mere child's play, and
            arrived at the entrance of the pyramid some minutes before my two companions, by jumping
            off each course to the one beneath, where a broken part did not present a convenient
            step for the foot. The day was, as every day has been, uninterrupted sunshine ; the cool
            season had just set in, and has since continued, after a summer of unpre- cedented heat
            and duration, up to the present date, (November 8th); a fine north breeze blew freshly
            the whole day, and my two companions allowed that they felt no fatigue or oppression in
            several hours rambling on the arid shadeless soil, in the full blaze of the sun, so
            temperate were his rays.</p>

         <p>The view from the top of the great pyramid, lighted up by a bright sun, which is rarely
            obscured for a moment, is glorious. From north to south, and at our feet, stretched the
            broad green valley of the Nile, its surface like a sea with promontories and isthmuses,
            shooting into and across it, with villages, palm groves, and exuberant tracts of
            cultivation rising from the bright placid surface which is alive with countless
            multitudes of wild fowl, geese, cranes, ibises, pelicans, &amp;c. over which numerous
            birds of prey, falcons, kites, and vultures, with which Egypt pre-eminently abounds, are
            constantly soaring. Beyond the limits of the inundation, and on either side of the river
            stretched the great Lybian desert, its unbounded and unvaried surface of brownish white
            sand raised by the wind into long ridges, or broken into shorter undulations, and the
            whole resembling a vast ocean in every thing but colour, agitated and swelling into
            billows. I ought however to add, that ranges of hills of white limestone, the same as
            that of which the Pyramids are built, are visible on the north and south, being part of
            a chain terminating in the Bed Sea at <name type="place" ref="#suez">Suez </name>, and
            of which the Mokattan hills also behind <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name> are
            a portion. These hills seem to run parallel with the Nile and its principal branches on
            the side of the desert, and were possibly at one period its boundaries. We remained on
            the top for perhaps an hour or more, during all which time our guides would hardly allow
            us a moment's peace, through the reiterated clamour for Baksheesh, and to have the word
            given for descending from this, and mounting to the top of the adjoining pyramid of
            Cephrenes in five minutes, which one of them actually accomplished in four minutes and a
            half, in our sight. The distance between the two Pyramids, which are of nearly equal
            height, appears to be about two hundred yards, and the angles of each are exactly
            opposite one another. Two of our most active Arabs, on promise of a few piastres as
            Baksheesh, started for the race, running down the angle of the vast incline like cats,
            and quickly disappeared from view, till on gaining the base, they were again seen
            coursing over the rough stony ground, during which run, one of them divested himself of
            every fragment of his scanty clothing, and in a few moments of time was scaling the
            second pyramid, and was reduced by distance to so pigmy a size that I repeatedly lost
            sight of him if I took my eyes off him for a moment, and I always had much difficulty to
            find him again, although he never could for an instant be hidden by any intervening
            object. The apex of the pyramid is covered with the remains of the original casing, yet
            over this comparatively smooth surface the man contrived to clamber with the facility of
            a cat, and a moment after was seen waving his arms on the summit. He then descended the
            second Pyramid, and re-ascended the first, and as rapidly joined us again on the
            platform. The extreme softness of the stone offers great facility to those aspirants to
            such fame as can be secured through after ages by the simple agency of an inscription,
            and I am ashamed to say that I yielded to the national propensity, and found time to
            carve in large and deep letters the initials W. A. B. on the face of one of the
            altar-like blocks that occupy the centre of the platform, but could not add the date
            before our party proposed descending to view the interior.</p>

         <p>The entrance may be perhaps at one third of the total height of the pyramid from the
            ground, and the descent into the passage leading to the great chamber, and the
            subsequent ascent to the latter, is the only arduous part of the undertaking, and it may
            justly be termed so; as for ladies, it is really a serious affair, and rather an awkward
            one for any person. The descent to the mouth of the passage is itself exceedingly steep
            and slippery, being composed of huge granite blocks inclining inwards and downwards at a
            pitch as sharp as the roof of any house, and nothing to hold on by. The first part of
            the passage is extremely low and narrow, but it widens and increases greatly in height,
            becoming at the same time, so excessively steep, that the combined support of the guides
            is required to prevent your sliding back, an event which would prove fatal, as the
            length of the incline is so great that a light at either end appears to be a star, as in
            the gallery of a mine, and at the lower extremity of this inclined passage is a sudden
            perpendicular fall of at least six feet, I should say, seven or eight, with very rugged
            sides, which I found a nervous business to surmount on returning, as the guides could
            hardly find footing for themselves whilst having to support each person of our party,
            and literally to lift him down. In one part of the incline you have to walk along a
            narrow ledge for several yards, not above a foot wide from the perpendicular face of the
            wall, and having a deep, rugged, and very slanting way below you on the right hand. On
            this ledge the Arabs enable you to walk by holding you by the arms, but I could not
            altogether overcome the feeling of insecurity, as there is not any projection whatever
            to lay hold of, and the stone you tread on is quite smooth, which with the precipitous
            character of the ascent, gives the appearance of some danger to the undertaking. I would
            strongly advise no nervous lady, and perhaps I might add, no nervous man, to attempt
            visiting the interior of the great pyramid, for after all, there is very little to be
            seen, and that little can be conveyed by description nearly as well as by a personal
            view. The lights furnished by our Arab guides were utterly insufficient to show us the
            size, proportions, and colours of the chamber in which the sarcophagus stands. We could
            only see by shifting our position, portions of the walls, and a dim discovery of the
            roof by holding up the candles: all else was one deep black vacuity of darkness; with a
            stagnant suffocating atmosphere, never under 80°, and never renewed by ventilation: the
            only changes of air coming in and going out by the same long confined passage, which is
            the sole entrance to this sepulchral chamber. We found no bats in it, at least if there
            were any, they did not show that they were at all disturbed by our entrance, and we
            noticed nothing of their remains, at which I was surprised, having heard that they
            abounded so much in the interior of the great Pyramid; but we found them in swarms in
            the adjoining sepulchral grottos hewn in the rock that forms the area around the second
            Pyramid. We saw so little of the first or lowest chamber, and found the dust and
            closeness so disagreeable and oppressive, and the incessant importunities of the Arabs
            for Baksheesh, at this stage of their conductorship, so intolerable, that we agreed not
            to visit the second or upper chamber, as not likely to repay the toil of the ascent.
            Whilst looking, or rather, groping about in the chamber, I inadvertently stepped into an
            opening leading downwards from the floor to some passage below, and had not an Arab
            guide been most providentially close at my elbow, (no doubt teasing me at the moment for
            Baksheesh), who caught me by the arm, and just saved me in time, my fall would have been
            a most serious, if not fatal one. The light held over the spot disclosed a very awkward
            looking cavity, sloping down at an abrupt angle, which the pitchy darkness prevented me
            entirely from seeing. I gave the old Arab a special token of my gratitude for his timely
            succour in the hour of danger ; but from the moment of the accident, till we quitted the
            pyramid, he showed constant fear that his services would be unrequited^ (as by an Arab,
            they certainly would have been), and continued to remind me of the aid he had rendered,
            till I was sick of hearing about it. We made it a rule to reserve all payments and
            gratuities for our return to the tent, and to the very last moment before striking it,
            and to shew not even a para to the guides, as their importunities for Baksheesh would
            have been redoubled at the sight of the smallest coin. As regards robbery by open
            violence, or even intimidation, there is not the slightest danger in visiting the
            Pyramids noiv, whatever risk there might have been formerly; the shewing these
            structures being at the present day carried on in a perfectly systematic manner, the
            right being a vested one of doing so, and the Shekh, or chief of the village, being
            answerable to government for the security of visitors; but pilfering may happen, and
            should be guarded against, by keeping watch on the pockets, and by having a trustworthy
            dragoman always about the personal baggage, &amp;c. On leaving the great Pyramids of
            Cheops, we proceeded to view (the exteriors only), those of Cephrenes, Belzoni, and the
            fourth and far smaller one of Colonel Yyse, a description of which is of course
            unnecessary. This examination occupied us several hours, and we did not start for <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name> till 2 p.m. The day was heavenly, and though
            the sun shone out unclouded, not one of us felt his rays, to which we were fully
            exposed, in the least degree oppressive, even after all our climbing, and disturbed rest
            the night before.</p>

         <p>The Pyramid of Cephrenes stands in the centre of a vast square or court, two sides of
            which are nearly perfect and form a series of tombs hewn in the solid rock with many
            curious inscriptions in hieroglyphics, besides bas-reliefs, some of which are in
            excellent preservation, and the figures of a few, representing oxen and other animals,
            extremely well designed. The two other sides of the square are distinctly traceable, but
            much encumbered by mounds of rubbish, and consist of arched tombs and sepulchres of
            solid masonry, here and there in very good preservation; but the pyramid they surround
            is in as dilapidated a state as that of Cheops, excepting the small portion of casing
            which remains at the top tolerably entire. The third pyramid, that called after Belzoni,
            is of very inferior size, but at the base it is partly cased with red granite in
            excellent preservation, and around it lie many granite blocks, together with fragments
            of columns, and sculptured stones, which must have been the remains of some building of
            wholly different architecture. The interior of this Pyramid has been opened up and
            examined by Belzoni. The fourth Pyramid is of very much smaller dimensions, and is
            surrounded by, or at least stands in a court or enclosure of tombs like that of
            Cephrenes, and its interior, Dr. Abbott tells me, is very interesting in an antiquarian
            point of view. All around the Pyramids are deep mummy pits, and about mid-way between
            the Pyramid of Cephrenes and the Sphinx, we saw lying on the sand two lids of sarcophagi
            sculptured as mummies, one of which was in the most beautiful preservation imaginable,
            and covered with hieroglyphics: they were both of blue or dove coloured marble, the
            second somewhat injured. We also saw a very large tomb which had been excavated from the
            drift sand and rubbish by Colonel Vyse, but we could not gain access to it.</p>

         <p>The Sphinx I found with the features much more mutilated than is generally represented
            in public accounts; indeed, very few lineaments of the human face remain, and viewed
            from behind, the head has a grotesque, almost ludicrous aspect, like an immense bob wig
           : but the front view of this wonderful structure is very striking: it is wonderful only
            however from its colossal size, for the stone is the same with that composing the
            Pyramids, and extremely soft. I searched carefully for some small memorial of antiquity,
            a scarabaeus, or mummy of glass or earthenware, but could pick up nothing, although the
            Arabs have innumerable relics of the kind for sale at very low prices, which Dr. Abbott
            says are really genuine in most cases, and not, as asserted, manufactured in England on
            speculation.</p>

         <p>Believe me, always, Your affectionate Brother, William Arnold Bromfield. </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>