<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Cairo, November 11th,
               1850.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from https://archive.org/details/lettersfromegypt00brom</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/william-arnold-bromfield/letters/5">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/160825459">William Arnold
                  Bromfield</name>
               <name type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/360630">
                        <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>
                    </name>
               <date when="1850-11-11">11 November 1850</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person">Eliza Bromfield</name>
               <name type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/2638911">Ryde</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>My dear <name type="person" ref="#eliza_bromfield">E</name>
            </p>

         <p>I am afraid there will be but little chance of any letter reaching you from me for
            perhaps four months to come; I have arranged to form one of a party of three to go up
            the Nile at the end of this week; we propose to pass up at least as high as the second
            cataract, and should we find it practicable, to ascend the river still higher in <name type="place" ref="#nubia">Nubia</name>. We calculate on being absent from <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name> three or four months.</p>

         <p>My companions are Lieutenant Pengelly, and a young naval friend of his, Mr. Lakes, both
            on leave of absence for health. We have bargained for an excellent boat, with the owner,
            an Englishman of the name of Page, who has consented to let us have it at £ 22 per
            month. We take a crew of eight Arabs, including the cook, and the Reis or captain, a
            trusty man in Page's employ, who has been up the river at least a dozen times. Our
            expenses during the voyage, hire of boat, and living included, will be about £ 10 or £
            12 per month, each, which is cheaper than we can live for at this hotel, where the
            charges are about £15 per month, exclusive of out door expenses. Our boat has just been
            newly painted and repaired, and made perfectly clean, which might not have been done by
            an Arab or Egyptian owner; the three cabins are very nicely fitted up with soft divans,
            glazed windows and Venetian blinds, and there is a small apartment in the stern. We rode
            down on Saturday to <name type="place" ref="#boulak">Boulak</name> to inspect it, and
            were much pleased with its appearance. I expect to be close upon, and most likely
            within, the tropics before the shortest day, and so escape the cold of <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>, which every one agrees in saying, is severely
            felt at mid-winter from the ill construction of the houses, the want of fire places, and
            the comparatively humid atmosphere. At present the climate is glorious, the cool season
            has regularly succeeded the unusually protracted heat, and the thermometer is now in my
            apartment at, or a little under, 70° at 8 a.m., or ten degrees less than it was a week
            ago, whilst the mornings and evenings are: too cool to be quite pleasant. I find
            additional bedclothes necessary, and many of the natives have put on their winter
            garments. Still, the weather is quite warm through the day, fogs and mists arising about
            sunset, which chill the air, and dispose to colds and coughs. Barring a slight cold in
            the head, picked up I suppose in the tent at the Pyramids, I am remarkably well, and
            enjoy the delightful warmth and perpetual sunshine amazingly.</p>

         <p>I have made several very agreeable acquaintances in this city; Mr, Leider, of the Church
            Missionary Society, Mr. Trail, late of the Rhodes Gardens, who is very kind and
            attentive; Dr. Abbott, a zealous Egyptian antiquary, by whom I was invited to come and
            dine a la Turc, but which mode of eating a dinner, I never wish to repeat. Mr. Trail
            introduced me to the reading room of the Egyptian Society, where there is a valuable
            collection of books relating to Egypt, which I can go and consult at any time. <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name> itself is an endless source of amusement, and
            I have not yet seen a hundredth part of its interminable lanes, courts, alleys, and
            picturesque buildings. I have been in three mosques, where ten or fifteen years ago, a
            christian could hardly have found access without a special firman, and might then have
            been insulted when he entered; now, things are so altered, that they do not in all the
            mosques even insist on the infidels taking off their shoes at the entrance, although
            that is rigorously kept up as respects moslems, in the more especially tidy ones. In
            most mosques large loose slippers are kept for visitors to put on over their shoes. Two
            days ago, we went to see the dancing dervishes practise their ludicrous religious
            ceremonies in their mosques, which they do every Friday. Each moslem who entered
            scrupulously left his shoes at the door, whilst we, giaours, who formed a large party,
            were permitted to desecrate the holy pavement with our boots and shoes, and stranger
            still, two or three unveiled English ladies went with us, and were quietly permitted to
            take their places with the gentlemen, while not a single native woman was on the floor
            of the mosque, but they might be seen in numbers peering through the bars of the small
            windows in the dome upon the devotees and heretics assembled 1 there.</p>

         <p>
                <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>, November 15th, We are fast getting every!
            thing ready on board the boat that is to be our floating 1 home for the next three
            months, and expect to commence our voyage on Wednesday the 20th. We trust to escape the
            disagreeable, though not intense cold of a Cairene winter. I find sudden changes of
            temperature here in the mornings and evenings, from 80° to 60°, or lower in the open
            air, and two days back with a smart shower, succeeded by drizzling mist. Although the
            Nile water has ceased to disagree with me, I cannot join in the encomiums bestowed on
            it, as being the most delicious water in the world, for independently of its thickness,
            it has to me, even when filtered, a sensible taste, which the <name type="place" ref="#alexandria">Alexandria </name>n had not, and which is not improved, either in
            reality or ideally by transportation in the unsavoury looking skin, (that of the entire
            animal, the head excepted), in which it is carried to the consumer's premises. Such
            bottles are usually said to be goat skins, but from the great size of many, I suspect
            they are as often those of donkeys, if not of other animals, very disgusting looking
            vehicles for one's daily drink, but use has already reconciled me to the thought that
            every drop of water I swallow has been in contact with these primitive casks, <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name> is an exceedingly entertaining place, and the
            absolute certainty of scarcely a day's interruption to the bright sunny weather greatly
            enhances the enjoyment of perambulating it. The 11th ultimo was the first day that was
            completely overcast, like a November day at home; the rest were bright and clear, as
            usual.</p>

         <p>If you have not read Lane's " Modern Egyptians," pray do, it is an admirably minute and
            correct picture of the Cairenes, so esteemed at least by every one here. Will you set
            Wacey to work to procure for me a most admirable lithograph<note>The great Pyramid from
               the North East taken by the Camera Lucida, and done on stone by Edward Lane, 1830,
               folio, lithograph, coloured, published by J. Dickenson, 114, New Bond Street.</note>
            of the great Pyramid of Cheops, it is so exact a likeness of that structure, that I
            shall be very glad to have it hang up for a remembrance.</p>

         <p>Believe me, Your affectionate Brother, William Arnold Bromeield.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>