<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>On board the Mary Victoria, Off Ekhmim Upper Egypt, December 12th
               1850.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from https://archive.org/details/lettersfromegypt00brom</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/william-arnold-bromfield/letters/8">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <name type="person" ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/160825459">William Arnold
                  Bromfield</name>
               <name type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/361661">Akhmim</name>
               <date when="1850-12-12">12 December 1850</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <name type="person">Eliza Bromfield</name>
               <name type="place" ref="http://www.geonames.org/2638911">Ryde</name>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>My dear <name type="person" ref="#eliza_bromfield">E</name></p>

         <p>Since my last, dated December 6th, was finished, we have advanced, as far as the town
            opposite to which I am now writing, towards the great centre of our Nilotic aspirations,
               <name type="place" ref="#thebes">Thebes</name>, which we may confidently expect io
            iedon in a weeK at iariiiesi. Our voyage progresses merrily, if not rapidly, but we all
            heartily wish the weather warmer in the mornings and evenings, for it is now so cold
            that we cannot remain up with comfort, even in our snug cabin, unless very warmly-clad.
            To day, we have been shivering in a north wind, even at noon, and sitting out in the
            forepart of the boat has hardly been practicable at any hour, nor indeed have we been
            able for some days past to enjoy the evening breeze at and after sunset; whilst the
            mornings, till nine o'clock at least, are so cold, that the water we wash in makes our
            fingers almost numb when dipped into it. The whole of this day the sky has been without
            a cloud: the strong northern breeze blowing directly against the course of the stream,
            has raised its broad expanse into minature billows, on which our little craft rocks as
            if at sea, and sometimes heels over in a manner rather alarming to nervous landsmen,
            under the pressure of the gale on her huge lateen sail. This obliquity of position is
            very well during the day, when every door is open fore and aft, and in case of
            capsizing, a chance of escape would be offered by clinging to the hull should she float,
            or of being rescued by the Arabs, who are all expert swimmers, from a watery grave; but
            at night it is far from pleasant to feel oneself vibrating alternately between the two
            extremities of an inclined plane, with the multifarious impediments of bedclothes,
            musquito curtains, and two pairs of folding cabin doors bolted on the outside,
            interposed to bar free egress in an attempt to gain the open deck, the only part where
            assistance and safety could be looked for should a sudden flaw of wind from the lofty
            hills that now hem in the valley of Egypt, lay our little floating tenement on her beam
            ends. Our crew would gladly make fast to the bank every night at sunset, and after
            having tired themselves out with singing to the darrabatakako or small drum of the
            country, which we jocosely call the Arabian night's entertainment, quietly turn in, or
            rather lie about on deck, for the night; but we are so anxious to reach the second
            cataract in the hope of being able to penetrate into Nubia, that we have issued standing
            orders to the Keis to make sail at all times of the night when the wind serves. The
            present cold weather is agreeable neither to ourselves, nor to our Nubian boatmen, and
            the desire of getting into warmer latitudes is shared by every one on board, each one of
            us looking forward with satisfaction to the prospect of passing the coldest part of the
            winter between the tropics, which we shall probably enter before the new year dawns upon
            us. Today has been the only one hitherto that could be called really disagreeable; for
            though brilliantly clear, the sun had little power to temper the chilliness of the high
            northerly wind, which whilst it blew so keenly as to render exercise indispensable
            during exposure to it, raised clouds of sand from the adjoining desert like mist from
            the river, which annoyed us when ashore by getting into our eyes, and powdering our
            clothes all over.</p>

         <p>Ekhmim, the ancient Panopolis, is a considerable town to all appearance, for we did not
            land there, as we ran past it with a cold north wind on the evening of this day,
            reserving our visit to its lions till our return. It was once celebrated amongst the
            cities of Egypt for its temples to Pan, and in later times for a line of powerful
            princes. The hills forming the abrupt termination of the table-land of the desert on
            either side of the Nile, are here very bold; and on the eastern bank rise immediately
            behind the city of Ekhmim, which with its palm-groves and the broad river now washing
            its very walls, once a quarter of a mile distant from the banks, has a very picturesque
            appearance. The scenery of the Nile in Upper Egypt is far bolder and more romantic than
            I could have supposed, and appears to become more and more so as we advance. In one
            place, the mountain verge of the eastern desert is actually washed by the river; the
            western desert (the Lybian) is mostly much more distant, and looks like a majestic wall,
            behind which the sunsets, in cloudless skies, are truly magnificent.</p>

         <p><name type="place" ref="#girgeh">Girgeh</name>, December ISth. This, almost the last
            town of any considerable size before reaching the cataracts, derives its name from St.
            George, the tutelar saint of the Copts, and is not on the site of any ancient place of
            note. We arrived here early in the morning, when Mr. P. and myself accompanied by Ameen,
            went into the town to lay in a stock of bread, and other articles of consumption which
            are beginning to run low. <name type="place" ref="#girgeh">Girgeh</name> forms no
            exception to other Egyptian towns, which are all pretty exact counterparts of one
            another in the main points of dirt, dust, dogs and squalidness, although many of the
            villages are very pretty, embowered as they mostly are in groves of date-palms and
            acacias, Acacia nilotica. Marketing in an Egyptian town is at once a very amusing and
            difficult business, involving a vast waste of time and words in the purchase of goods
            not amounting perhaps to sixpence in value. In another place I shall hope to give you
            some account of our bargains for flour, bread, charcoal, mishmish (dried apricots,) and
            sundry other articles, mostly comestibles, some of which we find are always needed, or
            on the point of being exhausted. At <name type="place" ref="#girgeh">Girgeh</name> we
            bought four fine live turkeys at sixteen and nineteen piastres the pair, or a at a rough
            estimate, in English money, two shil- shillings and eightpence and three shillings and
            twopence.</p>

         <p>We hope to be at <name type="place" ref="#thebes">Thebes</name> in a few days, probably
            on the 18th, if we can get a wind to take us; for at present we have only calms, and
            light baffling breezes, with occasionally a brisk and favourable wind from the northward
            for a few hours; and even this is often made of little avail, or rendered contrary, by
            the turnings and curves in the river, or in rounding the numerous islands and sand
            banks.</p>

         <p>When marketing in the <foreign xml:lang="ar">bazaar</foreign>s and shops of <name type="place" ref="#girgeh">Girgeh</name>, (where by the bye, as well as at <name type="place" ref="#siout">Siout</name>, there are one or two elaborately designed
            minarets to the principal mosques,) we were beset by the natives offering us antique
            coins for sale, amongst which was an English farthing of Queen Victoria ! and stranger
            still, the top of a green glass bottle with the name of the liquor it contained or that
            of the vendor cast on it, such as we so often see upon these vessels in England. As the
            poor fellows who offered us these curious samples of antique numismatics, were wholly
            unable to read the inscriptions on them, I cannot doubt that the farthing and bottle
            label, were both proffered in perfect singleness of heart, with the genuine coins, of
            which several were purchased by Mr. P. for a few paras each. These were mostly Roman or
            Greek, and I believe were truly what they appeared to be; as Dr. Abbott of <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name> tells me that coins and other relics of
            ancient times are commonly found at the present day, and that those offered for sale,
            may in general be depended on as genuine antiques; but that articles of real interest or
            value are, as they ever have been, rare, and for the most part find their way into the
            hands of those who know how to turn their possession to advantage.</p>

         <p>December 10th, bmce leaving Eknmim, our progress has been exceedingly slow from the want
            of wind, the turnings of the river, and the numerous shoals and sand banks amongst which
            we have to work our way. Still, our voyage has not been without great interest, from the
            bold and beautiful scenery of the valley of the Nile in this part, and from the
            appearance during the last few days of a couple of Egyptian memorabilia, the Doum or
            Thebaic palm (Cucifera Thebaica), and Crocodiles. The first of these lions of the Nile,
            shewed itself in a solitary specimen w T hich caught the eye in a grove of date trees a
            few miles on this side of Ekhmim, which city is close upon the northern limit of the
            Theban palm, beyond which it is only seen occasionally in a cultivated condition.
            Yesterday, however, (December 14th,) we came upon them growing in plenty along the
            eastern bank of the river between <name type="place" ref="#girgeh">Girgeh</name> and
            Farshoot, whilst taking our evening ramble; the trees bore plenty of fruit, but still
            unripe. The Cucifera Thebaica is a small palm, at least I have not as yet seen any
            exceeding twenty-five or thirty feet in height, and is remarkable amongst the trees
            composing this numerous family, for having the stems repeatedly branched at top in a
            forked manner, the branches terminating in a tuft of large fan shaped leaves, with
            prickly foot stalks. The fruit which is produced in long clusters, is of the size of a
            good large apple, and of a russet brown when ripe, consisting, like the cocoa nut, of a
            central nucleus, surrounded by a tough, fibrous outer coat,, which when chewed has a
            sweet taste, compared with truth to that of gingerbread, which it resembles almost
            exactly; but the outer coat, although eatable, is so dry and husky, and withal so
            sparing in quantity, and difficult to separate from the nut it encloses, that as a fruit
            tree, this palm can never rival the date, and whoever has tasted one of the fruits, will
            I think hardly be at the trouble of eating a second. Perhaps the only ripe specimens I
            have seen, which were in the market at <name type="place" ref="#cairo">Cairo</name>,
            might not have been the best of their kind; but the fact that the fruit of the Doum palm
            is but occasionally brought from Upper to Lower Egypt, and is eaten only by the
            peasantry, and poorer classes in the towns, proves the little estimation in which it is
            held, and which is probably equal to its real merit in its best state of perfection. At
            the time I am writing, (Monday evening, December 15th,) we have passsd Farshoot, and the
            Doum palm now mixes with the more majestic date tree everywhere along the river banks,
            and in some places grows by itself, or is the prevailing species.</p>

         <p>The scenery at this part of our voyage is extremely bold and picturesque, the banks of
            the river are very steep, and basaltic rock has appeared in some places cropping out at
            the Avater's edge, whilst the cliffs that bound the valley on the east present a
            magnificent aspect from their mountainous elevation, and the vast sanddrifts that fill
            every nook and hollow from the deserts at their back; and especially beautiful do they
            look when their bare yellow sides reflect the rays of the setting sun, which for some
            days past, has gone down in a glowing and cloudless, but cold sky. Nearly coequal with
            the limits of the Doum palm, is the line that bounds the distribution of the crocodile
            northwards, at the present day; for in ancient times it would appear to have ranged much
            lower in the Nile, and it is said to have even inhabited the Delta, and Lower Egypt
            properly so called. In our day, the crocodile is said first to make its appearance at or
            near Osiout, but we saw none of them during our short stay at that city; but on Sunday
            morning (December 14th,) on arriving about a quarter of a mile from a sand bank, which
            we learned from our boatmen was a favourite resort of these reptiles, and which is a
            little beyond <name type="place" ref="#girgeh">Girgeh</name>, between that town and
            Farshoot, we had the great gratification of seeing a whole herd, if I may use the term,
            of these river monsters emerge one by one from the stream as the sun gained power, and
            assemble on the sand bank, where we soon counted no less than sixteen of various sizes,
            huddled together, and evidently enjoying the warmth of the bright and unclouded
            morningray. The smallest of those we saw, as we watched them through our telescopes,
            seemed to be at least eight or nine feet in length, and several were absolute leviathan
            monsters, as hideous and terrific as can well be imagined, not less certainly than
            sixteen or eighteen feet long, with bodies as thick as that of a horse; the huge jaws of
            some gaping wide apart as they lay listless and motionless on the sand, or occasionally
            dragged themselves forth from the water to he along like huge logs or trunks of palm
            trees, to which they have no inconsiderable general resemblance in the rough and scaly
            covering of their unwieldy forms, knotted with crested protuberances. We were so near
            them, that by aid of our telescopes, we could perfectly watch their motions, and
            discover their minutest cha- racters, longing all the time to be amongst them with our
            guns, and planning an attack we intend making on their strong hold when we return down
            the river. We propose to throw up a masked battery of sand the day previous to our
            attack, and landing on the beach before daybreak the following morning, to open fire on
            them from behind our temporary fort as they come up out of the river to bask in the sun.
            We have furnished ourselves with balls of hardened lead expressly for the purpose, and
            trust to be able to achieve the feat ot shooting a crocodile, and carrying off his jaws
            and scull as trophies of our campaign against the ancient monster deities of Egypt's
            river. The young specimens of the crocodile of the Nile that are occasionally brought
            alive to England, give no idea whatever of the hideous deformity, and ferocious aspect
            of the full grown animal. A more revolting creature does not exist; yet I believe that
            to man they are seldom, if ever, dangerous, being extremely watchful and timid, waddling
            slowly down to, and sliding into the water, on the too near approach of any person; and
            we observed the sand banks occupied by numbers of aquatic birds, geese, cranes,
            pelicans, &amp;c, walking about the outstretched monsters as if possessed with a feeling
            that they were in no peril of their lives in the society of these ugly reptiles. A boat,
            in rounding the bank, fired a gun at the crocodiles, but not within range, which had the
            effect of sending them all pell mell into the water, but in a few minutes afterwards the
            noses of one or two might be seen emerging, and soon the sand bank became repeopled with
            the fugitives. We little expected at this season to find crocodiles half so numerous,
            seeing how cold the morn- ings are now, and how low the temperature of the Nile is,
            compared with that which it attains a few months later or earlier than the present.</p>

         <p>Always my dear <name type="person" ref="#eliza_bromfield">E</name>., Your affectionate Brother, William Arnold Bromfield.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>