<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter 6: On board the Nile boat, Mary Victoria, On the river, 20 or 30 miles
               South of Cairo, Tuesday, November 26th, 1850</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from https://archive.org/details/lettersfromegypt00brom</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/william-arnold-bromfield/letters/6">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/160825459">William Arnold Bromfield</persName>
               <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/360630">Cairo</placeName>
               <date when="1850-11-26">26 November 1850</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName>Eliza Bromfield</persName>
               <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2638911">Ryde</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>My dear E</p>




         <p>I am now fairly afloat with Lieutenant Pengelly and Mr. Lakes in our aquatic habitation,
            and probable domicile for three or perhaps four months to come. We feel already quite at
            home, and exceedingly comfortable in the Mary Victoria, and hitherto have had very
            little experience of the usual annoyances which travellers on the Nile complain of. To
            our great joy we have escaped the insect disturbers of rest, though we have received
            terrific accounts of their numbers and prowess on the Nile, and the only intruders on
            our domestic peace, are a small family of rats, and a colony of cockroaches, both
            confining themselves to the lockers and timbers of the boat, and never appearing, at
            least by day, in any part of the vessel where their presence would be a source of
            personal annoyance, and our well arranged mosquitoe curtains would effectually exclude
            these, and every other nocturnal visitor from the beds. We found in Mr. Page, the owner
            of the boat, a very fair dealing and honourable man, who has spared no pains to render
            our voyage comfortable as far as the appointments of the Mary Victoria are concerned,
            and we consider ourselves as very fortunate in not having had to deal with an Arab
            owner, with whom a contract drawn up in very express terms in Arabic, and signed at the
            Consulate, would have been absolutely necessary; a proceeding both troublesome and
            attended with some expense, and one which rarely effects the purpose in view, of
            obviating any dispute or misunderstanding between the contracting parties, as the Arab
            boat proprietors seldom stand by the written engagement, but are ever ready to seize an
            opportunity of evading the conditions to which they have subscribed, and to take every
            advantage in their power of the ignorance and inexperience of tourists. We have a very
            young crew or eight men, (including the Keis or captain, and the steersman), docile,
            good humoured fellows from Nubia or Ethiopia, with mild, honest countenances, who seem
            as happy as kings, and amuse us with their simple boat song, or rather chant, and
            performances on the small drum of the country, and on the tambourine^. We have each of
            us a servant, having dispensed altogether with our dragoman, who is almost invariably a
            dishonest, or at least imposing fellow, very consequential, and unmanageable, and who
            requires many times the amount of wages given to a single Arab domestic. Saad, my own
            man, acts as cook on board, and serves us in that capacity very creditably; his wages
            are 200 piastres or about £2 per month for his double official duties, finding himself
            in food, and every thing besides during the voyage. These, with our three selves compose
            a little community of fourteen, Lieutenant P. assuming the supreme command of the crew
            and vessel, subject to the advice and opinion of the Eeis on matters relating to local
            navigation; the latter, notwithstanding his extreme youth, conducting himself towards
            his people with wonderful dignity of deportment, never mixing in their games or songs,
            but generally sitting retired at the head of the boat, watching her progress, and ready
            to give his orders when necessary.</p>

         <p>Mr. Lakes not being well enough to accompany Mr. Pengelly and myself to the Barrage — a
            vast undertaking of the late Mohammed Ali, for damming up the waters of the Nile when at
            their height, and retaining them on the irrigated lands of the Delta longer than the
            time of their natural subsidence would allow of, — that gentleman and myself left Cairo
            in the boat on the 21st for the junction of the Kosetta and Damietta branches of the
            Nile where the above works are situated. We caught sight of them before sunset, but
            could not examine them till the next day: they are on a scale of great magnitude, but
            their ultimate completion, from the enormous expenses already incurred, and the sum
            which wall be required to finish the undertaking, is considered very doubtful,
            particularly when the careless, unenterprising character of Abbas Pasha is taken into
            account, as another impediment to carrying out his predecessor's grand conception. The
            Barrage is as its name imports, a vast dam of masonry, stretching across the two
            principal branches of the Nile, (those of Kosetta and Damietta), just at their point of
            junction with, or confluence into the main stream which forms the apex of the Delta. It
            is in fact an immense bridge of numerous slightly pointed arches, and with towers at its
            extremities, the arches are to be closed with flood gates to admit the Nile freely
            during the period of its rise, but, as I understand it, are to be partially closed when
            the inundation is at its height, and the river begins to fall; when the water in that
            part of the valley of the Nile above the Barrage w T ill be longer retained on the
            irrigated lands, the fertility of which it is supposed will thereby be much augmented.
            But it is doubted by many competent judges, whether any barrier, however solidly
            constructed, can resist the enormous pressure to which it must inevitably be subjected,
            especially during the period of the high Nile or inundation. It is feared that no
            sufficiently good foundation can be made in the bed of soft alluvium, even should the
            superstructure itself prove firm enough to stem the current, and the weight of
            accumulated water when the sluices are closed. The works are not yet half completed, but
            are slowly going on by forced and ill paid labour, as in all other Government
            undertakings of the kind in this country. Having inspected the Barrage, we set off on
            our return to Cairo, and passing the port of Boulak, we took up our position under the
            beautiful island of Rhoda, with its fine, but now half ruined gardens, over which I was
            not long since conducted, by the late curator, Mr. James Trail. Rhoda is reputed to be
            the spot where the daughter of Pharoah went to wash herself at the river when she
            discovered the infant Moses; the island lies partlyopposite to Old Cairo, and
            consequently nearly on the site of ancient Memphis, and has the Nilo-meter on its
            smaller extremity. The tradition carries plausibility with it, since Rhoda was,
            probably, from time immemorial a garden residence, and from its retired situation well
            suited for the ablutions of a king's daughter.</p>

         <p>Mr. L. joined us on the 23rd, and the next day, we were fairly on our long voyage up the
            " river of Egypt," which has hitherto proved most prosperous and agreeable. My two
            companions are perfect gentlemen, quiet, and yet very cheerful, disposed to make the
            best of every thing, and anticipating great enjoyment for the future. We all feel as
            much at home in our little floating castle, as if we were ashore, or in Old England; the
            winds have hitherto been propitious, enabling us to make sail during the night, and to
            steal softly into ever increasing warmth, at least by day; for the mornings, evenings,
            and nights, are very cold: but the glorious sun is never obscured except for a brief
            interval, perhaps once in a week, by some fleeting cloud, shining else unceasingly over
            our watery path. Within, we are amply protected from the cold of the night, by good
            bedding, clothing, and folding doors, and when the mosquitoe curtains, whose nominal
            office is now quite a sinecure, are arranged by our trusty squires, Saad, Mohammed, and
            Ameen, for the night, each sleeping place is as private and retired as if we slept in
            separate apartments. I have the utmost cause for self gratulation in having brought out
            a gun with me: it has proved an admirable adjunct to our trip, not merely from the
            amusement derived from shooting, but as a means of replenishing our larder, daily, with
            every variety of excellent fowl; while our stock of poultry on board is reserved against
            the failure of game, and we are not, as we should otherwise be, condemned to that kind
            of food almost exclusively. It is only occasionally, on arriving at the towns or larger
            villages, that we can hope for the luxury of butchers' meat, mutton, kid, or as a great
            rarity, beef, all of inferior quality to what we are accustomed to at home. Without our
            guns, we never set foot on shore, and invariably return from our walks through the palm
            groves and fertile fields of Egypt, with the materials for our morrow's breakfast and
            dinner. The spoils of the chase have hitherto been confined to wild pigeons, wild geese,
            ducks, and larks, which last are as common as in England, and exactly identical in
            species with our skylark, which we should hold it a sin to shoot at home; but here, we
            find it expedient to cast away all such scruples in providing for our daily mess. The
            crew are delighted with our foraging, as we are enabled to supply the second table as
            well as our own with game, which is a welcome addition to their simple and frugal diet
            of bread, lent el soup, (the red pottage of Esau), or certain messes of vegetables,
            leeks, onions, cabbage, with rice, or corn of various kinds; the Nile water being their
            only beverage. We invariably land at the Egyptian villages, many of which are large and
            populous, to shoot doves and pigeons; the former abound in the extensive palm (date)
            groves, in the vicinity of the cultivated lands, and they commit great depredation on
            the maize and guinea corn: the latter are domesticated in huge pigeon houses, of which I
            have before spoken. I am sorry to say our travelling countrymen do not always observe
            the rights of property, but make a practice of shooting pigeons, heedless of the
            remonstrances of the pacific inhabitants, who are afraid of making more energetic
            demonstrations of disapprobation. We never molest the pigeons in the villages, but to
            shoot any stray birds outside, however near to the houses, is considered perfectly fair,
            and is never objected to by the people, who invariably behave to us with civility, as we
            stroll amongst their huts of mud or unburnt brick. The children it is true, sometimes
            run away at the sight of us giaours, and the dread of the evil eye is occasionally
            manifested by an expression of impatience from the women, if we indulge in a stare of
            curiosity or speculation at them or their occupations, but the dread and dislike of the
            Frank is fast wearing away, not in Cairo only, but all along the river; and the
            probability is, that before many years shall have elapsed, the British voyagers on the
            Nile will be regarded by the dwellers along its banks, as their best, and certainly
            their most profitable friends.</p>

         <p>It is said that the ultimate occupation of Egypt by the English is looked forward to
            with considerable confidence by the Cairenes, and that they express much satisfaction at
            the prospect. It is certain we shall never relinquish the hold we have on their country
            without a struggle, and that we can never permit any of the great European powers,
            France, Russia, or Austria, to gain a footing in Egypt, as the safety of our Indian
            empire would be fearfully compromised by foreign occupation of this country, if it did
            not eventuate in its loss.</p>

         <p>Minieh, lat. 28. 7. December 2nd. A week's sailing with light airs and calms, and an
            occasionally favourable breeze, has brought us thus far on our voyage, nearly half way
            to the great centre of attraction, Thebes; a degree of progress we owe to the unwearied
            exertions of our willing and light hearted crew of Nubians, in tracking during the day;
            for at night we generally now make fast to the banks till daybreak, unless the wind
            should be propitious, when we keep under sail all night, or a part of it.</p>

         <p>December 5th, Left Minieh this forenoon with a favourable breeze from the northwards,
            having been detained much longer than we intended by an accident to Mr. Lakes, who, when
            shooting very early on Tuesday morning with a Maltese gentleman, received a shot from
            the latter intended for a snipe, 27 corns entering in various parts of his person, and
            one striking the left eye, and wounding the white, a very short distance only from the
            transparent cornea, which happily escaped an injury that must have infallibly destroyed
            the sight of that eye. The pain at the moment, Mr. Lakes describes as so intense, that
            he imagined the shot had pierced his brain, and he fell involuntarily on receiving it.
            On recovering, he found that he could not see at all with the wounded eye: he managed to
            reach the boat, a distance of several miles from the spot where the accident occurred,
            partly on foot, partly on a donkey, and presented himself before us whilst we were at
            breakfast, informing us, with a smile on his countenance, of what had happened, and
            exhibiting to Mr. Pengelly and myself, an alarming appearance, his face being perforated
            with several shot, and the left eye closed. Fortunately Minieh is the residence of a
            European district surgeon, who being a friend of the Maltese, whose mal-adroitness
            caused this distressing event, was immediately in our boat, and on examination, found
            the eye wounded as above related. He prescribed a lotion of acetate of lead, constantly
            applied, and then a poultice of linseed, intending to bleed his patient, should
            inflammatory symptoms shew themselves: but most fortunately, the previously lowered
            system of Mr. Lakes was little disposed to take such inflammatory action, and contrary
            to all expectation, he passed the night free from any pain worth speaking of, and has
            ever since been going on as well as could be wished. The sight of the eye is much
            obscured, but it is to be hoped that in a few days, the troubled humours in the ball
            will be absorbed, and replaced by others of the usual transparency, there being no
            reason to apprehend the smallest injury to the optic nerve. Mr. Lakes is sufficiently
            well to allow us to pursue our voyage* his eyes are of course bandaged, and he cannot
            employ himself for some days to come, but we have the greatest reason to be thankful
            that things were no worse. Mr. Lakes might have suffered the loss of his eye, and we
            must have returned in the boat with him to Cairo.</p>

         <p>We are now, thank God, again stemming the broad bosom of old Nile, to the wild music of
            our Arab, or rather, Berber crew, (the Berbers are a tribe of central Nubia), under a
            glorious, never ceasing sunshine, now so mild in its refulgence, that you would suppose
            yourself in England, were it not for the plague of flies, countless hosts of which have
            invaded our watery domicile since we moored our little bark alongside the town of
            Minieh; the plague of fleas has also commenced, and begins to be troublesome to us at
            night. Ihe banks oi the river swarm with gigantic rats, which never fail to come on
            board whenever we stop, but they seem to content themselves with running about the boat
            during the night, and gnawing the timbers, as we have not yet discovered that we are
            sufferers by their visits to our store lockers, or poultry crate, which is a matter of
            astonishment, considering the facility of access they have to any article of food on
            board, and their numerical force and rapacity. We have two cats, (as yet only kittens),
            and a rat trap on board, but cannot entirely succeed in expelling our unwelcome
            visitors.</p>

         <p>With kind regards to all our friends at Ryde, and elsewhere, Believe me, always, Your
            affectionate Brother, William Arnold Bromfield.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
