<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
    schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter 9: On Board the Mary Victoria, Near Kenneh, opposite Dendereh, December
               16th, 1850.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from https://archive.org/details/lettersfromegypt00brom</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/william-arnold-bromfield/letters/9">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/160825459">William Arnold Bromfield</persName>
               <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/350550">Qina</placeName>
               <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/358422">Dandarah</placeName>
               <date when="1850-12-16">16 December 1850</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName>Eliza Bromfield</persName>
               <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2638911">Ryde</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>My dear E</p>

         <p>I gladly avail myself of the opportunity afforded me by the place we are now
            approaching, of posting these sheets at the last town in Egypt from whence letters can
            be dispatched to Cairo with any certainty or regularity. I am not without hopes of
            finding one from you at Kenneh, where, if the wind does not fail us, we shall arrive to
            day or early to morrow; at all events, I trust to have tidings from you on our return
            from Nubia. Will you be so kind as to let Mr. Lawrence have the two little packets of
            seeds of Egyptian plants; he will no doubt raise them in pots, and keep them carefully
            from frost: it is very probable that both may be planted out in the summer. I am
            collecting everything in the shape of seeds I can find, but there are not many of the
            native plants at present in flower, much less in seed; and I fancy I shall reap a richer
            harvest in this way on our return voyage, than in the ascent of the river.</p>

         <p>Tuesday Evening, December 16th. A brisk wind is fast wafting us to Kenneh on the
            opposite bank of the river, near to which stand the magnificent ruins of Dendereh, on
            which we hope to feast our longing eyes to-morrow. The weather is gloriously serene and
            sunny ? and were it not for the coldness of the nights and morn- ings, would be perfect,
            for the temperature even at midday is that of the mildest summer weather: however this
            night it is somewhat warmer, and our merry hearted Nubians are amusing themselves, and,
            as they would fain believe, us also with their native Berber songs, with drum
            accompaniments; a species of musical entertainment we could well dispense with at this
            moment when we are engaged in making up our budgets for home, but we cannot find it in
            our hearts to stop this noisy, but innocent mirth; for no boat's crew could behave
            better than ours have done, poor fellows!</p>

         <p>I shall look out carefully for small antiquities among the ruins of Dendereh, Thebes,
            &amp;c, and believe that I can be put in the way of taking casts of the smaller
            inscriptions and hieroglyphics, as you take the brasses in a church, as Mr. P. has just
            shewn me one taken off on common paper by himself.</p>

         <p>Pray remember me most kindly to all our friends at Ryde, Believing me, always, Your
            affectionate Brother, William Aenold Bkomfield. </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>