<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter 17: On Board the Mary Victoria Nile Boat, Between Guineh and Girzeh, Upper
               Egypt, May 12th, 1851.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from https://archive.org/details/lettersfromegypt00brom</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/william-arnold-bromfield/letters/17">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/160825459">William Arnold Bromfield</persName>
               <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/350550/qina.html">Guineh (Qina)</placeName>
               <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/355026">Girga</placeName>
               <date when="1851-05-12">12 May 1851</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName>Eliza Bromfield</persName>
               <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2638911">Ryde</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>Dear E</p>

         <p>We continue slowly but steadily advancing towards the Egyptian capital, having left
            Assouan, the most southerly frontier town of this country, on the first of this month.
            Our progress has been delayed by the necessary stoppages at that, and the other
            considerable towns along the river, for the purpose of recruiting our nearly exhausted
            supplies of rice, sugar, coffee, &amp;c, as also to visit our good friends the Fox's at
            Ernout, and take a farewell view of Luxor, Karnac, and other lions, and finish the
            campaign by visiting the few that yet remained unseen by us.</p>

         <p>The weather since leaving Assouan has not increased in heat, the wind still keeping to
            some northerly point, with no appearance at present of the regular and much dreaded
            Khamseen from the southward. It is nevertheless quite as warm as is agreeable, and
            rather more so during the middle of the day. By ten o'clock the thermometer lias
            attained 90° or 95°, when it continues rising very slowly but regularly till one or two
            p.m. at which time it has stood froin 98° to 103° for some weeks past, remaining at or
            near that point till four or five p.m. when the heat declines, and during the evening
            falls to 90° or a little lower; in the early morning the mercury has usually descended
            to 84° or 85°, which is now to our feelings a delightfully cool and refreshing
            temperature. Although the heat is not at this time of the year so great here as in the
            upper part of the valley of the Nile at Dongola, Berber, and especially on the desert,
            it is more felt in Upper Egypt than in Nubia, as the air begins though slightly, to
            participate in the moisture of the Mediterranean to the northward, in addition to the
            natural evaporation from the great river on which we are afloat; and as water does not
            part, by radiation, with the heat it has received from the sun during the day, at all as
            readily as the bare sand does, the nights on board are much hotter than on shore, where
            we should therefore encamp every evening for coolness, could we escape molestation from
            mosquitoes, and also from the dogs and natives. We have moreover exchanged the dark
            primitive granite rocks above Assouan, for the newer white limestone of the Theban
            mountains, whose bare craggy sides glow like the walls of a furnace in the fierce glare
            of the noontide sun, and send back the north wind in stifling puffs, causing ever and
            anon huge columns of sand to move in dark vortices across the country, and towering to a
            vast height in the air like pillars of smoke from the crater of a volcano, their summits
            expanding into a cone of a pale yellow, which gradually deepens to a dark dun red or
            brown near the earth, according to their position with regard to the sun. When at Philae
            on the 30th of April, we experienced a strong sand-storm, which filled the air with
            impalpable dust mingled with coarse sand, and gave the landscape the appearance of being
            enveloped in fog; the sky at the same time was covered with dark angry looking clouds,
            from which fell a few heat drops, the utmost effort to produce anything like a
            refreshing shower of which this parched climate is capable; excepting at very distant
            intervals indeed, when a deluge of rain occasionally pours down on the Thebaid and Lower
            Nubia for a day or two.</p>

         <p>When crossing the great desert of Korosko we had, on a close calm cloudy night, several
            vivid flashes of sheet lightning, but neither thunder nor rain accompanied these silent
            and innocent coruscations. I may remark that falling stars are extremely common, and
            remarkably large and brilliant in the clear nights of Nubia and Egypt: we saw several in
            our desert wanderings of startling size and splendour traverse a considerable space in
            the heavens with extreme velocity, and then disappear without noise.</p>

         <p>The most serious inconvenience we experience from this torrid weather, is the great
            difficulty of keeping one of our staple articles of diet, milk, for a few hours, by
            boiling and preserving it in a vessel wrapped in wet cloths, and placed in the coolest
            part of the boat. As we cannot always procure fresh milk at this season from the
            herdsmen and villagers on shore, we are often deprived of it altogether, our stock taken
            on board in the morning becoming unfit for use before dinner time; and the evening
            supply is often precarious. Our way of procuring it in the wilds of the upper country
            above Dongola &amp;c, by chasing the goats to milk them when the owners were not at hand
            to do so for us, w^ould amuse you in the recital.</p>

         <p>We found our good friends Mr. and Mrs. Fox (the first English faces we have seen for
            months), at Ernout, quite well, and the immense sugar works belonging to Mustapha Bey, a
            minor, rapidly progressing towards completion: already the huge chimneys of the engine
            and boiling houses have risen within sight of the pylons, obelisks, and colossal pillars
            of Luxor and Karnac, which they far overtop in height, if they do not rival them in
            beauty and celebrity. This hospitable pair wished us to stop some days at the works, the
            machinery for which, on a scale of great magnitude, is all from England, and is erected
            here by native workmen from Cairo, under the sole instruction and superintendence of Mr.
            Fox.</p>

         <p>I saw there one living, and several dead specimens of the terrific scorpion spider or
            galleode of Egypt and the adjacent countries; the latter were found drowned in a large
            tank for supplying the engines; the former was captured in the house by Mr. Fox. The
            outstretched legs of the largest specimen measured about eight inches in the span. The
            general aspect of this hideous animal, is that of a gigantic spider, w T hich it
            resembles in the great length of its hairy legs, the oblong livid body, jointed like
            that ot the scorpion, is destitute ot any sting, instead of which the head is furnished
            with a formidable pair of sharp and very prominent pincers, capable of inflicting an
            extremely painful, though I believe not very venomous bite. It is a nocturnal animal,
            frequenting out-houses, and deserted apartments, running with incredible speed, and
            fearlessly attacking any object that is opposed to it. Mr. Fox's Arab servant hearing a
            mouse squeaking in the room one night as if in distress, was induced to ascertain the
            cause, when he found one of these galleodes had fastened upon it, but whether with the
            intention of making the mouse its prey, or from accidental offence given by the latter,
            Mr. Fox could not say. The natives regard its bite as not dangerous, and rather
            encourage it, as a noted destroyer of its first cousins, the scorpions. I have several
            of the above specimens (including the largest) in spirits, which I hope to send home
            with my plants &amp;c. from Alexandria.</p>

         <p>We bade adieu to Ernout on the 7 th May at 10 p.m. and rose at dawn the next morning to
            visit the ruins of Medinet Habou; the two Colossi (one of which is the famous supposed
            statue of Memnon); the temple, (or perhaps palace) of Rameses II. called the Memnonium;
            and lastly, the tombs of the kings; but the latter, we were obliged to postpone till the
            following day (9th) on account of the increasing morning heat after 9 or 10 o'clock.</p>

         <p>The first of these remains, the temple of Medinet Habou, is situated near the foot of
            the limestone range, as are likewise the Colossi and Memnonium, all three being within
            half or three quarters of an hour's ride of each other. The remains of Medinet Habou,
            are imposing, and very extensive, but belong to different epochs; and like many other
            Egyptian ruins are sadly encumbered with heaps of rubbish, mounds, and paltry hovels of
            crude brick, in which they are half buried, and their proportions concealed or
            destroyed. Although certainly possessing much grandeur, these ruins are not of a
            character to strike the non-antiquarian visitor as do the magnificent temples of
            Dendereh, Esneh, Edfou, and Abou Simbal (Ipsambul), all of which are also in a more
            perfect state.</p>

         <p>The great temple-palace of Rameses II. commonly known as the Rameseum or Memnonium, must
            have been when entire, a magnificent structure, and even in its present shattered and
            razed condition, it may lay claim to that character, and is less encumbered than most of
            the Egyptian temples with Roman, Christian, or Arab dwellings of hideous unburnt brick.
            But the most remarkable object in the Memnonium, is the stupendous statue of Rameses II.
            the founder; unquestionably the most gigantic of ancient or modern times. This now
            prostrate and shattered colossus is of grey syenitic granite; I find no account of its
            height when entire; but Sir Gr. Wilkinson gives its estimated weight at 887 tons. I must
            say however that viewed as it now lies, the proportions of the statue convey but an
            indifferent idea of the artistic skill of the sculptor; to myself, it appeared a sadly
            coarse and clumsy piece of workmanship both in design and execution; but if originally
            of a single piece, as really seems to have been the case, its transportation from the
            very distant quarry to its temple abode, reflects great credit either on the patience,
            or the engineering skill of the ancient Egyptians, I do not know which; but I believe
            the praise should be equally awarded to both.</p>

         <p>The two ill-shaped, stiff, and much mutilated sitting statues, one of which has acquired
            such world wide notoriety as the vocal Memnon, are rather objects of wonder for their
            magnitude, than of admiration for their beauty; and except that they possessed nothing
            of the same life and spirit, they put me greatly in mind of two figures of Tarn
            O'Shanter and Souter John which I recollect to have seen many years ago in London, the
            production of the self taught Scottish artist, Thorns, who was justly admired for his
            talented conception of the heroes of Burns' s tale. Poor Memnon, in particular, has been
            sadly knocked about since his singing days were over; and has been so clumsily repaired
            above the waist with unshapely blocks of sandstone (which is not the material of which
            the rest of his person is composed), as to look more like the fragment of an old wall,
            than a delineation in stone of the human form divine. In the huge lap of this statue,
            which is only accessible, by climbing, to persons gifted with a stronger head than mine,
            is a stone which emits a ringing sound when struck, and behind this is a cavity in which
            Sir G. Wilkinson thinks a person was in the habit of concealing himself, in order to
            produce the sound attributed by superstitious belief to the rays of the sun impinging on
            the figure at his rising, or as Sir G. Wilkinson states, an hour or two afterwards. One
            of our donkey boys climbed into the lap, and struck the stone repeatedly; but with all
            my desire to hear what I was prepared to listen to, a deep, sonorous, bell like tone, I
            could only distinguish a dull tinkling like that which any mason's trowel would elicit
            from an ordinary block of marble or freestone. The feet and throne of the so-called
            Memnon, (through confusion of names with the Egyptian Miamun), are covered with
            inscriptions, chiefly Greek, of great antiquity. The fellow statue is in better
            preservation, though of less celebrity, but the faces of both are so disfigured, that
            the features are scarcely traceable.</p>

         <p>The next morning at dawn we again started for the tombs of the Kings, attended by two
            servants, a guide with candles, our donkey boys, and some half dozen little fellows
            bearing gullahs, or porous earthern bottles filled with water; to the mouths of which
            ever and anon, we were glad to apply our parched lips. These famous grottos are
            excavated in the most solitary and intricate recesses of the Theban mountains. After
            quitting the plain, the way leads through winding defiles between hills and rocks of
            white limestone, and coarse conglomerate, the former extremely white, and approaching
            very nearly in hardness and appearance to the indurated chalk of our own country. Not a
            tree, shrub, or blade of grass finds a habitation upon these bare and sunburnt
            mountains, on which a drop of water from heaven either as rain or dew rarely falls, save
            only the transient devastating floods of sub-tropical storms. J ackals, wolves, and
            hyenas are the inhabitants; birds are few; but Mr. Pengelly brought down at one shot, a
            pair of magnificent horned owls, of great size, and with most formidable beaks and
            talons.</p>

         <p>The distance from our moorings on the western or Lybian side of the Nile opposite Luxor
            to these tombs, is about six miles. Their number is very considerable, but since their
            general plan, sculptures, and painting, are much the same in all, and so minute a survey
            could only interest the professed and zealous antiquary, we contented ourselves with
            viewing those marked by Sir G. Wilkinson on the face of their respective entrances Nos.
            9, 11, 17, called the tomfcs of Memnon (Miamun Rameses V.) Brace's or the Harper's, and
            Belzoni's tomb. These grottos lie scattered about in the sides of hills at irregular
            distances; the entrances are by unadorned rectangular openings, and the passage for some
            distance is always descending, and sometimes very steep, thickly strewed with fragments
            of the rock, beyond which, the tombs present an extraordinary collection of passages,
            halls, and chambers, elaborately adorned with sculptures and paintings, in endless
            variety and in endless repetition.</p>

         <p>A dispassionate view of Egyptian art, such as I have now had an opportunity of taking,
            in regard to its chief and most elaborate monuments, has led me to the conviction that
            with much that is worthy of the highest admiration, there is a vast deal that is not
            merely below mediocrity, but absolutely poor and paltry to the last degree, all
            strangely co-existing in the same edifice or excavation, and made the more conspicuous
            by the sharpness of the contrast. I have often been astonished and delighted by the
            gracefulness, elegance, and admirable execution of the sculptures in the various
            temples, tombs and pyramids, as at Napata and Meroe, which I have visited: and have been
            grieved as much to see the miserable scratches or scores intended to represent similar
            objects, that most frequently were to be found defacing the very walls on which such
            fine skill and taste were displayed. An extraordinary inequality of design and execution
            seems the prevailing characteristic of Egyptian sculpture and architecture. As for the
            paintings in the tombs, and on the roofs and ceilings of the temples, I must confess
            that with very few exceptions indeed, I never saw any that, to my eye, looked superior
            to vile daubs, such as a countrysign painter might feel ashamed to have executed. Some
            of the figures of men and animals in processions &amp;c. are tolerably pourtrayed,
            chiefly in their peculia subdued red, or Etruscan vase colour; but wheneve they attempt
            flowers, fruit, foliage, a scroll, or an complicated object required strong shading or
            relief, I have seen nothing but utter failure, — flat, gaudy, ungraceful designs. I know
            it is the fashion in England to talk of the extraordinary brilliancy and durability of
            these colours, as being inimitable in these degenerate days, by the loss of the mode of
            their preparation, one of the pretended secrets of ancient art; but this assertion, I
            have learnt to class with the customary ravings about Eastern skies, sunlights, shadows,
            moons, flowers, and fruits. I do not deny that the colours in the tombs and temples of
            Egypt have stood well, and retained most, if not the whole, of their original brilliancy
            (such as it was) through the lapse of many centuries; but I beg to observe that this
            holds true only in those edifices or excavations which have been hermetically sealed by
            the artificial closing up of the entrance, or by accumulation over them of the sands of
            the desert. From the more exposed buildings the painting has been either wholly effaced
            by the weather, or, as at Esneh and Edfou, some of the capitals of the columns retain
            mere traces of a disagreeable verdigris green: the dark blue studded with stars on the
            ceilings of some of these structures, as at Dendereh, has stood better, but even that is
            in a great degree blotched and obscured by age, and by the damp of the river.</p>

         <p>The Egyptians knew nothing of oil paints, and all their water colours that I have seen
            on the stucco or stone of their walls, whether in tombs or temples, have an opaque,
            earthy, or (what I believe artists call) muddy appearance, which argues no great skill
            or knowledge of the materials best adapted for yielding bright clear colours, similiar
            to those furnished by substances which modern chemistry has brought to hVht, and made
            subservient to modern art. Analysis indeed has proved that the water colours used by the
            ancient Egyptians for the decoration of their temples, were obtained from substances
            identical with those that yield the cheapest and most ordinary hues to the house
            painters of modern days, as yellow and red ochre, verdigris, lamp black, &amp;c. Our
            brilliant smalt, chrome yellow, Prussian blue, and other modern pigments of varied
            intensity, were to them unknown. Indigo, they were doubtless acquainted with; this has,
            I believe, been demonstrated by chemical analysis of some of their colours from the
            tombs and temples; several species of indigo I found abundant in the southern deserts,
            and along the banks of the Nile; and one native species, Indigofera argentea, is to this
            day universally used in Egypt for dying the common blue cloth of the country.</p>

         <p>The effect of the colouring in the tombs of the Kings is much injured by the often
            tasteless disposition of the various hues in parallel lines or stripes along the walls,
            the interstices between the stripes being crowded with vilely daubed hieroglyphics,
            mixed with grotesque figures, and every monstrous combination of living forms, that a
            depraved ingenuity could suggest to the artist. All harmonious blending or contrast of
            colours seems to have been generally overlooked, or disregarded in the sepulchral
            decorations of the Egyptians; green, red, blue, black, and yellow, are mixed, or laid on
            in close contact upon the stuccoed walls and roof, with the garish brush of a painter of
            children's toys, rather than with the sober and chastened pencil of a genuine artist.
            Yet, amidst this mass of confused figures, gaudy tints, and rude designs, there is a
            great deal worthy of admiration in these receptacles of the royal dead, figures traced
            with vast freedom and grace occasionally meet the eye, which causes the more regret to
            see them associated with so much that is poor and mean. The noble halls covered with
            sculptures and hieroglyphics, are wonderfully imposing from their fine size and
            proportions, as well as from the interest attaching to them on account of their high
            antiquity, and as depicting the manners and customs of the times in which they were
            constructed.</p>

         <p>The walls of this vast Necropolis bear witness to the presence within them of the great
            and illustrious as well as of the little and vain of every age and clime: we read the
            names of most of the celebrated explorers of Egyptian antiquities, Belzoni, Irby, and
            Mangles, Burckhard, and if I recollect right, of Champollion, and of others of the
            French savans. Amongst those of the more renowned but unlettered visitors to these
            sepulchral chambers, we read the names of Mohammed Ali in Arabic and European
            characters. We were greatly amused at the very uncomplimentary remarks and addresses
            inscribed on the walls of the first tomb we explored (No. 17, or that of Memnon so
            called), to Dr. Lepsius, a celebrated living antiquary of Germany, deprecating his
            appropriation of choice morsels of sculpture and hieroglyphics which he had detached
            from the wall, and carried away on a late archaeological razzia amongst these venerable
            remains of by-gone times. We were however indebted to this same Teutonic rifler of
            tombs, for our acquaintance with an exquisite little sepulchral grot, which he had the
            good fortune to light upon and dis-inter last year I believe, and throw open to the
            inspection of travellers like ourselves.</p>

         <p>The heat within the tombs of the kings was not nearly so great as I had anticipated, and
            the walls and roofs had the appearance of the most parching dryness i nevertheless the
            paintings in the tomb we first visited had suffered as it is said from the percolation
            through the absorbent limestone-rock of those violent floods which even visit the
            burnt-up hills of the Thebaid at distant, but uncertain periods.</p>

         <p>On quitting the tombs of the kings, we arrived in the plain by another and shorter
            route, passing by a very steep path across the highest peaks of the Theban mountains,
            and then descending precipitously their eastern escarpment, right glad to have done so
            at the expence of a toilsome clamber in the now burning sun on foot as far as the
            summit, our donkeys following us as best they might. The view was glorious, the vast
            plain of Thebes on our right, mapped out with the ruins of Medinet Abou, Karnak, the
            Colossi, the Memnonium, &amp;c, on the left the winding and sparkling river, on the
            furthest banks of which, the eye ranged over Luxor, Karnak, and the great plain beyond,
            bounded by a rampart of limestone like that from which we were looking down, and
            beholding the vast ruins reduced to the size of models under our feet. On our way down
            we passed the village and grottos of Assaseef, in one of which, during our occupation of
            its friendly shelter from the scorching sun, while we discussed a large bowl of goat's
            milk, I noticed some beautifully designed and finely executed sculpture, of some of
            which I caused impressions to be taken on coarse paper, by a native of the place who had
            acquired the art from Dr. Lepsius, and, for a piastre a sheet, performed the task very
            fairly, though on the whole rather unequally.</p>

         <p>Towards sunset of the 9th (having crossed over and moored our bark to the shore at Luxor
            during the day), we started on donkeys to take a second and farewell view of the ruins
            at that place, and, acting on the advice given me by Mrs. H. at Assouan, to pay our
            visit to the latter by moonlight. Arriving at Karnak just before the sun went down, and
            passing the noble, and still nearly perfect propylon that stands at the entrance to the
            ruins from Luxor, we mounted immediately behind that magnificent gateway to the roof of
            the temple which is formed by huge blocks laid across from column to column, and
            formerly united as in modern structures by iron clamps and lead. From this elevated
            position we sat enjoying a fine view of the great temple, the obelisks, and other ruins,
            collectively known as those of Karnak, whilst our trusty little Nubian Mohammed kindled
            a charcoal fire by our side, in the deep groove formed between two disjointed colossal
            blocks, which made an excellent grate, on which our tea kettle was merrily singing, and
            enabled us to continue leisurely sipping our tea, and chatting till twilight had
            vanished entirely from the western horizon, and had given place to that of the moon,
            then at the end of her first quarter, when we descended, and made the best of our way to
            the vast mass of ruins still in front of us. The effect on entering the grand hall, amid
            the forest of colossal pillars, which once supported as massive a roof, was quite what
            Mrs. H. had described to me — it was awfully grand, almost unearthly. The night was
            clear (and it is very rarely indeed otherwise in Upper Egypt), but a few fleecy clouds
            occasionally psssed across the moon, which being only half way to the full, threw a more
            solemn, dusky, and delusive shadow, than if she had been shining in perfect glory. Every
            part of the vast pile seemed magnified, whilst all its architectural defects were
            effectually concealed; nothing but the gigantic outlines of the serried ranks of
            tower-like columns were visible, half buried in black shade, half revealed in pale
            uncertain light; some few, leaning towards one another, with an alarming inclination,
            seemed actually to be toppling over as the few thin clouds, flying before the moon,
            apparently transmitted their own motion to these Titanean masses, many of which are
            crowned in addition to their vast capital with enormous blocks, which some mighty agency
            has strangely thrown into every imaginable position of threatening danger to such as
            explore this wonderful temple. Some of these architraves are actually hanging in mid
            air, totally unsupported except by a small part of their imbedded extremity, the
            unsupported end lowered to an angle, sometimes nearly approaching the perpendicular: yet
            this mighty weight hangs still, and doubtless has done so for ages. The two noble
            granite obelisks of one solid block, that still adorn Karnak, shew to admirable
            advantage by moonlight, and the same remark may be with truth extended to every part of
            the ruins, of which I would not for the world have missed taking the view by night.</p>

         <p>The aspect of Karnak by day, I still think undeserving the extravagantly high flown
            encomiums of antiquaries, and picturesque-hunting travellers and artists. With a vast
            deal that is poor, tasteless, and barbarous in design and execution, there is still very
            much amongst these remains to call forth feelings of admiration at their sublimity, and
            no one can reasonably doubt that in the days of their entirety, the general effect of
            this vast group of edifices must have been splendid beyond belief. I find fault only
            with that class of prepossessed travellers who can see nothing but perfection (often
            purely imaginary) in such ancient relics; overlooking or denying the most obvious and
            glaring defects, or even setting them down, as so many positive beauties.</p>

         <p>The ruins of Karnak abound in scorpions; and a small, dirty, but picturesque village
            bearing the name of the temple, occupies the space in front of the grand entrance to the
            ruins, but happily has not yet encroached upon any part of the latter, as is the case at
            Edfou and Esneh, where the miserable hovels of the fellahs are crowded together on the
            very roofs of these fanes, as if upon a solid rock. We had a pleasant ride home by
            moonlight to our boat at Luxor; and on arriving there, we immediately cast loose from
            the shore, and dropped down the river on our return voyage to Cairo.</p>

         <p>Sunrise on the morning of the 10th found me trotting over the halfeh-grass-covered-plain
            on a gallant Egyptian neddy, bent on paying my respects once more to the truly
            magnificent temple of Dendereh; I had only with me our late friend Mr. Lakes' Arab
            servant, Ahmeed. I had another object in again stopping at Dendereh, namely, to procure
            a cluster of the fruit of the Doum Palm for the Botanical Museum at Kew, agreeably to a
            request from Sir William Hooker that I would do so if possible. In this I have fully
            succeeded, and so, whilst the villagers were engaged in cutting me off a proper sized
            cluster from the forest of this palm which adorns the approach to the temple from the
            river, I pushed on for the latter, returning with rather increased than diminished
            admiration of so beautiful, and elaborately-adorned a structure. The profusion of
            sculptures and hieroglyphics finely executed in relief and in vast square panels, with
            which the walls are absolutely covered, has an extraordinarily rich effect, greatly
            superior to the same sculptures and emblematic writing in intaglio. The air was
            delightfully cool and fresh, like that of a May morning at home, and this cool character
            the mornings have hitherto preserved since we left Khartoun, but the earlier part of the
            nights is now sultry, although quite pleasant after two or three o'clock a.m. So rapid
            is the dissipation of heat by nocturnal radiation in this unclouded clime, that the
            languid enervated Africans are secure of a few hours before and after sun-rise of
            sufficiently low temperature to brace their unstrung frames, at nearly, if not at all
            times of the year; and in winter, the mornings are cold enough to make a European, much
            more a native, shiver, even far within the tropics.</p>

         <p>Siout, or Assiout, Upper Egypt, May 18th. Continued northerly winds, and (so unlike
            their former selves), a lazy apathetic crew, whom neither threats nor persuasion can
            induce to pull at the oars lustily, unite to render our return voyage down the Nile, a
            very tedious one: we having been already eighteen days from Assouan, with a prospect
            before us of not being at Cairo before the end of the month at our present rate of
            going. We are the more desirous of reaching Cairo speedily, as my fellow traveller's
            health is suffering materially from the heat, and he is complaining of daily increasing
            languor and debility. Sir G. Wilkinson tells us that from April to October favourable
            winds for ascending the Nile are not to be expected, the prevailing ones during that
            season being from some southerly quarter, or in other words down the river. Hitherto
            however, the wind has constantly come from the north, and so far has fulfilled the
            assertion of Sir (jr. Wilkinson, of being unfavourable | but in our case, for precisely
            the reverse of the reason he gives, since we are on our return from, and not on our
            passage to Upper Egypt, and should in truth expect to have the wind in our favour coming
            down. Mr. Pengelly tells me that his former experience of the weather during summer in
            Egypt is in accordance with the present, that northerly winds have ever been more
            general than southerly, and from the account of many persons with whom I have spoken on
            the subject, these would seem to preponderate greatly over breezes from other quarters
            throughout the year.</p>

         <p>This northerly wind, however, has the advantage of keeping the temperature lower than a
            southerly one, but its breezes are still very hot, and impart no feeling of freshness as
            they pass over us, we therefore exclude them and the sun together, by keeping the
            Venetian blinds of our boat shut during the middle of the day. We would gladly put up
            with a higher temperature in being blown merrily down to Cairo by a red hot Khamseen
            wind in preference to our present slow progress with a comparatively cool one
            perpetually against us. The temperature continues pretty steady, neither increasing nor
            diminishing in any material degree; and its distribution through the twenty-four hours
            may be thus stated. Between sunrise and eight a.m. from 80° — 85°, by ten a.m. it has
            generally reached 90°, from which time it continues slowly rising till one or two p.m.
            being at noon 98° — 100°, and two p.m. 102°, continuing at this point till at or near
            sunset, when it sinks slowly to 90° or 92°, which is the usual height of the thermometer
            at midnight; from this time the mercury gradually falls to between 80° and 70°, the
            ordinary heat just before sunrise. But some abatement of the mid-day heat both in
            intensity and duration, is beginning to manifest itself as we advance northwards, and,
            gaining a flatter and more open country, leave the narrower part of the Nile valley
            behind us shut in by the bare heated limestone mountains of the Thebaid, the hot blasts
            of which we are beginning to exchange for cool currents of air from the Mediterranean.
            The temperatures given above are taken on board in the cabin with as much attention to
            keeping that place cool as possible. For six weeks or two months past, the thermometer
            has, I believe, hardly ever been below 100° at noon, sometimes several degrees above
            that point: but within these few days, it has not been so high until an hour or two
            after the sun has passed the meridian. In spite of being thus exposed during twenty out
            of the twenty-four hours to a heat of 90° — 102°, and sleeping under close drawn
            mosquito curtains of fine muslin, I am perfectly well in health, and suffer no other
            inconvenience from the inordinate temperature than frequent thirst, and some loss of
            what little adipose covering I possess by nature: this is certainly not the weather for
            any one to grow stout in, however much disposed thereto by constitution.</p>

         <p>Minieh May 24th. We arrived here yesterday afternoon, and lucky it was that we did so,
            as a furious gale from the northward set in after dark, and continued to blow unabatedly
            all night, and though at this moment reduced to a fresh breeze, the weather holds out no
            prospect of our getting away for many hours at least. The Nile lashed into foam, is
            rolling like the troubled ocean, and seems resolved to deserve its Arab appellation of
            El Bahr, which signifies the sea or any large body of water. The temperature to day is
            very cool and pleasant at this time (one p.m.); the thermometer in the strong fresh
            current of wind through our boat, as she lies moored under the bank in a direction north
            and south, is 88°; we have had nothing so low as this at the same hour by twelve or
            fourteen degrees for two months past, but we must not expect its continuance when the
            gale is over.</p>

         <p>For the last two days the sky has been partly overcast with tolerably thick clouds, a
            thing rarely seen even so low down as this town is in latitude 28°, and still seldomer
            higher up. I cannot understand why it is the custom for English travellers to speak in
            such raptures of the transparent azure of the Egyptian sky, and of its unrivalled
            brilliancy: to my vision, it has always, excepting at particular moments, shewn itself
            as strikingly deficient in both these attributes. The sky of Egypt is certainly
            deserving enough of praise in so far as the absence of clouds is concerned, although it
            is not seldom that it is wrapped in a veil of dull, thin vapour, especially towards
            evening, when the sunsets are frequently extremely tame, hazy, and colourless. I have
            studied the phases of the African sky with great attention for eight months, and can
            confidently assert that brilliancy and transparency are not its habitual every day
            attributes. A white, milky, or whey-like opacity, is the almost constant characteristic
            of the heavens in the land of the Pharoahs, and thence southward into the tropical
            regions of Nubia and Abyssinia; becoming more and more marked, as the summer or warm
            season advances; the sky assuming a more diaphanous aspect in the winter, or at least in
            the cooler season. In general the nights are clearer than the days, and the star-light
            is often extremely brilliant, but not more so I am sure, than on many a fine winter's
            night in England; and frequently the night sky is as nebulous, or nearly so, as the day,
            and a dim lustreless star-light, which people at home are apt to suppose is unknown in
            these southern climes, is all the traveller enjoys on his nocturnal journeyings for his
            guidance. I might say that the sky of Egypt (including that of Nubia to the termination
            of the valley of the Nile at Khartoun), is but in keeping with the land and its
            products, over which its arch is hung; a sunlit, and sunburnt, region of colourless, or
            rather sadness-tinted landscapes, with little contrast of light and shade; the very
            verdure of its scanty and monotonous native vegetation 5 greyish, and unrefreshing to
            the eye; the animals, birds, reptiles, and insects, seldom arrayed in any but the
            plainest garb, in which like that of the people themselves and their earthen
            habitations, some shades of brown are the prevailing hue; the uniformity of which is
            only broken by the occasional passage across the expanse of a few clouds too transparent
            and colourless to give tone and richness to the firmament. I have seen beautiful
            sun-sets (and on my desert travels), fine sun-rises too; but the gorgeous tints that
            accompany them in climates of greater humidity, are but their occasional concomitants in
            this arid region; and I have remarked that whilst the sun usually rises from an
            unclouded horizon, his setting is often obscured by a dull haze.</p>

         <p>Always, my dear E., Your affectionate Brother, William Arnold Bromfield.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
