<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter 7: On board the Mary Victoria, Nile boat, Between Minieh and Manfalout,
               Central Egypt; December 6th, 1850.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from https://archive.org/details/lettersfromegypt00brom</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/william-arnold-bromfield/letters/7">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/160825459">William Arnold Bromfield</persName>
               <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/360686">Al Minyā</placeName>
               <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/352913">Manfalūţ</placeName>
               <date when="1850-12-06">6 December 1850</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName>Eliza Bromfield</persName>
               <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2638911">Ryde</placeName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>My dear E</p>

         <p>A charming breeze is wafting us merrily up the Nile, and the plague of flies has ceased
            for the present, as by dint of brushing them out of the cabin with flyflaps and towels,
            we have succeeded in reducing their numbers within the limits of moderation, and so long
            as we continue in mid-channel, we may reckon safely on enjoying freedom from one of the
            most serious annoyances to which travellers in Egypt are exposed. The nights are now
            always chilly, and the early mornings, till about nine o'clock, or even later, quite
            cold. Even in this quarter of the world, the tendency to extremes, evinced by the
            climates of the Eastern side of all large tracts of land, is manifested; for Mr.
            Headland, the superintendent of the sugar factory at Rhodah, told me this morning, that
            the canes are occasionally much injured by frost in this latitude, 28°, and that in
            January sharp hoar frosts are not un frequent, ice having been formed last winter there
            one fourth of an inch in thickness.</p>

         <p>Minieh is one of the largest provincial towns of Central Egypt, and has a garrison of
            800 troops, the depot of four regiments of cavalry. Like all other towns in this
            country, it is a confused assemblage of narrow streets and alleys, made up of dirt and
            rubbish, and dilapidation; the abodes of the lower classes mere mud hovels, and those of
            the higher, pigsties on a larger scale. We had letters to M. Mounier, who has the
            management of a very extensive sugar manufactory close to the town, belonging to the
            eldest son of Abbas Pasha, a boy of twelve years of age. M. Mounier received us with
            great politeness, and conducted us over the works, which are very complete, where the
            sugar undergoes every process, from its extraction from the cane, to its refinement as
            loaf sugar. The evaporation of the cane juice is carried on in vacuo, as in the great
            English refineries, and the purification is effected by animal charcoal, obtained from
            immense neaps ot bones, calcined on the spot in proper furnaces. The machinery is of the
            most complete description, and consists not only of the sugar mills, &amp;c, required
            for refining, but of powerful English steam engines for driving them, and pumps of great
            calibre for irrigating the land, of which 1500 acres are planted with canes. The labour
            in this, and another sugar manufactory at Rhodah, a few miles further up, is forced; and
            the poor workmen, to whom no day of rest is allowed, (not even Friday, the Moslem
            sabbath), are paid their scanty earnings in kind, never in money, and this payment
            consists of molasses or the refuse sugar, the delivery of which is often withheld from
            them for weeks, whilst they are driven to the work chained together like convicted
            felons. The accounts we hear from persons of the highest respectability of the
            oppressive exactions and barbarities of the Egyptian government, and of the venality,
            falsehood, and dishonesty of every official in its employ, would appear incredible, did
            not every thing we see around us bear witness to their truth. The fearful picture of the
            desolation of Egypt drawn by the prophet Ezekiel, chap. 29 to 31, is a vivid
            representation of what she is at the present moment, and a signal instance of the
            fulfilment of Scripture prophecy. Between Minieh and Manfalout we stopped to deliver
            letters and newspapers to Mr. Headland, at Ehodah, (which word signifies in Arabic a
            garden), the property of Ismael Bey. We saw there a steam pump, &amp;c, for irrigation,
            and others in course of erection; the works are extensive, but the sugar is sent from
            the manufactory to Cairo to be refined, by a large English firm in that city. The
            appearance of tall factory chimneys vomiting out smoke, and huge boilers emitting clouds
            of steam, not to mention an occasional steam-boat puffing and splashing against the
            turbid stream, that has its sources in the heart of a barbarous and unknown land,
            divests, it must be owned, the valley of the Nile of some of that romance which early
            associations have attached to it, and perhaps speaks in significant language of its
            restoration at no very distant day to more than its ancient glory and prosperity. Mr. H.
            received us with great civility, and would have shewn us the works, had we not declined
            his offer on the plea that we were anxious to profit by the then favourable wind for
            continuing our voyage upwards; besides which, w r e had no desire to see a second sugar
            manufactory, similar to, but less complete, than that which we had so lately visited,
            and with the details of which we were so well acquainted. We contented ourselves
            therefore, ( I mean Mr. Pengelly and myself, for Mr. Lakes could not of course accompany
            us), with walking over the gardens of the governor of the district, in which Mr.
            Headland keeps a fine young lion, just five months old, and already nearly as large as a
            mastiff, lately brought from Nubia, and intended, I believe, as a present for Abbas
            Pasha. The beast is allowed to roam at large over the garden, and although now only
            exhibiting the amiable traits of leonine juvenility, he gives evidence in his rough
            play, of great strength, and when feeding, of some ferocity; tokens, it will be well to
            attend to in time, as in a few more months, the unrestrained liberty he now enjoys, may
            be perverted to the harm of those about him.</p>

         <p>Manfalout, December 7th. We arrived at this place, the ancient Crocodilopolis, about
            noon, and have now completed the half of our voyage between Cairo and Thebes. The wind
            has been exceedingly variable, and often, none at all, which has obliged us to get on by
            polling and tracking; but on the whole, we have made thus far a fair average passage for
            the time of year, for the month of December is always considered unfavourable for
            ascending the river, from the unsteadiness and uncertainty of the wind, which as often
            blows from the south as from the north, and calms, or very light airs are constantly
            intervening. We went ashore at every large town or village on our way. Manfalout is a
            small place compared with Minieh, and like every other Egyptian town, is principally
            built of unburnt brick. There are two handsome minarets belonging to the principal
            mosques, which last, with the residence of the governor or other principal officer of
            the district, are the only buildings at all distinguishable in the cities of this
            country, from the mass of dirty, dilapidated, or half finished habitations which compose
            them.</p>

         <p>A pretty little Egyptian boy, about ten or eleven years of age, volunteered to conduct
            us where doves were to be found, on which gentle bipeds, I am ashamed to say, we have
            been satiating our carnivorous appetites for this fortnight past, for which I can only
            plead by way of excuse, their delicate flavour, so superior to that of domestic poultry,
            and the means their death affords us of economising, or rendering the purchase of the
            latter almost unnecessary. The little fellow failed to find us many birds, but gambolled
            and frolicked along with us outside the town, perfectly at his ease with the giaours,
            and at last bade us adieu at the door of his mother's house. Mr. Pengelly took such a
            fancy to him, that he fain would have taken him away with us up the river, an
            arrangement we should all have been equally charmed with, and to which the boy shewed no
            sort of repugnance; but his mother told us when we made the proposition, that she could
            not bear to part with him, although she had tour other children at home, of which he was
            the eldest, and she appeared to entertain no distrust of our intentions. At parting, Mr.
            Pengelly gave him a small silver coin, value a quarter piastre, or about a halfpenny
            sterling, no despicable baksheesh to a child in this poverty stricken country. The poor
            little fellow looked at it, and seemed for a moment as if hesitating to accept it, then
            deposited it, on our encouraging him to do so, in a fold of his vesture, with an air of
            shame at becoming the recipient, which astonished us in a country where avarice is the
            ruling passion from the highest to the lowest, and where a present or remuneration is
            demanded by every man, woman, and child, for the smallest service.</p>

         <p>Manfalout boasts a tolerable bazaar, where, during our visit we were much amused by the
            curiosity of the rude Arnout soldiery, some of whom are quartered here, in inspecting
            our fire arms, my highly finished double barrelled gun exciting their greatest
            admiration, especially the strength and mechanism of the percussion lock, the principle
            of which the Oriental gunsmiths are but imperfectly acquainted with, and cannot yet
            imitate. The fineness of our English powder too astonished them exceedingly, and we
            parted with these intractable warriors on the best of terms. We find the people in every
            town and village we enter extremely well disposed towards us, ready to give every
            information in their power, and to shew us where any game is to be found; only
            disagreeable when a bargain for meat, vegetables, bread, charcoal, fec, is negotiating,
            when their disposition to over-reach and haggle about a para seldom fails to shew
            itself: but this unpleasant intercourse we find it on every account best to leave to Mr.
            L's Nubian (Berber) servant, Ameen, who speaks the language, and knowing the value of
            the various articles we consume, conducts the greater part of our marketing, rendering
            us an account of the money disbursed every day or two. Ameen is brother to the Nubian
            attendant on the hippopotamus in the Zoological Gardens, who accompanied the animal from
            its native country to England, where he still is. Ameen sometimes receives letters from
            his brother, who wishes him to join him at the gardens, and says he has got money in a
            Savings bank. He occasionally finds means of sending his brother Ameen little presents,
            such as an English penknife, but the latter does not seem to relish the idea of quitting
            Egypt for England, as from his known respectability at Cairo, Ameen is sure of a
            comfortable livelihood, as servant or dragoman to travellers going up the Nile. Ameen is
            much pleased at my offer to become the bearer of a letter to his brother on my return
            home next year.</p>

         <p>The scenery for several days past has been interesting, the left, or eastern bank of the
            Nile, being uniformly bounded by a lofty limestone ridge, increasing in height and
            boldness as we advance southward, sometimes receding to a distance of several miles from
            the river banks, and at other times almost skirting the shore, and often jutting out
            into bold headlands, or occasionally rising into peaks of considerable elevation. This
            ridge, which now (at Siout, Dec. 9th,) begins to close in on the valley of the Nile on
            both sides like a vast and magnificent wall, is a continuation of the Mokattan chain
            which commences at the Red Sea, and is already of respectable height at Cairo, but here
            assumes quite a mountainous aspect. The range is the boundary of the great western
            (Lybian) and eastern deserts, and is perfectly devoid like them of even a blade of
            grass; it now" quite shuts out by its continuous elevation every glimpse of the desert,
            which before, (at least on the east side) often discovered its ocean-like expanse of
            sand billows as we held on our course; now, we see only the nearlyperpendicular and
            stratified face of its abrupt, cliff-like terminations, below which, is a broad or
            narrow strip of land diversified with rich crops of maize, guinea-corn, sugar, clover,
            wheat, colewort, beans, peas, carrots, cotton, and various garden esculents, as onions,
            garlic, cabbage, ochras, fennel, coriander, Corchorus olitorius, &amp;c. blended at
            short intervals with villages standing amidst extensive date groves, full of doves and
            wild pigeons, and with here and there a lovely grove of 6e Sant" (Acacia Nilotica), Gum
            tree (Acacia vera), which in Nubia and Abyssinia yields the Gum Arabic of commerce. Both
            these trees are now loaded with all their sweet scented flowers closely compacted into
            globose heads like little golden balls. The single fields of guinea-corn especially, are
            of incredible extent, and afford food and shelter to wild boars, and harbour packs of
            jackalls that nightly serenade us with their melancholy noise, a whining kind of
            barking, much like that of a fox, but louder, and more disagreeable. Mr. Lakes shot the
            other day with his rifle, a very large jackall, when we were out together looking for
            game, and we anticipate fine sport during the moonlight nights, now coming on, amongst
            the ruins of Karnac and Luxor, where we hope to eat a pic-nic dinner on Christmas day,
            and to feast on plum pudding made by the hands of Saad, the only christian, by the way,
            of our party, besides our three selves, and who has proved a most able cook, in addition
            to his character as a steady, and we believe too, an honest servant. I cannot say as
            much for his skill as a laundress, for the display of which, did he possess it, our very
            limited means afloat afford him little opportunity; for we quite forgot to add a board
            and smoothing irons to our outfit on leaving Cairo. We dress in linen, which has only
            been washed over, and hastily dried in the sun and air; the fronts are all puckers, and
            the collars the same, and without a particle of starch in them. Shaving we have quite
            abjured in these wild regions as a tedious and unnecessary toilette operation: so we are
            all decorated with black bushy beards and moustaches of three week's growth, and since
            we have adopted the tarboosh, a close cap of scarlet cloth, with a huge tassel of dark
            blue silk, worn over another small skull cap of cotton, called a takeelzel, we are half
            moslem in appearance, if not in creed. I am sure our friends at home would laugh were
            they to see us, nor am I certain that they would not envy us our river life, and river
            home in this most splendid and rainless climate.</p>

         <p>The soil of the valley of the Nile, particularly that part left dry by the now receding
            waters, is a sandy loam of a deep brown colour, and of the consistence nearly of paste,
            so that like that, it is quite plastic, and can be kneaded with the fingers as dough. It
            is an error to suppose that the soil of the Nile is slime: it can hardly even be called
            mud when in its state of softest consistence; and its aspect conveys the impression of
            its exuberant fertility, which might be still further increased by the use of manures,
            and a proper rotation of crops, of which the Egyptian farmers have no idea. The towns
            and villages are constructed of unburnt brick made of the alluvial earth, and
            consequently present the same colour as that of the ground they stand upon, while the
            skins of the inhabitants are of a hue very closely approaching that of their native
            soil, and the scanty clothing of the fellahs or agricultural labourers, as well as that
            of the greater part of the poor in the towns and villages, is a single wrapper of a very
            coarse and thick cloth, also of a deep brown, made probably of the undyed wool of the
            native sheep, whose fleeces are exactly of that colour, white sheep being seldom seen in
            this country; hence, brown is the prevailing colour in an Egyptian landscape; the
            desert, the river, the people, the cattle, the houses, are all brown, or of a tint in
            which brown is the chief constituent; it is a swart land of grave and sombre colours,
            even the green of the few species of trees indigenous to, or cultivated in Egypt, is of
            a deep and dark, rather than of a light and lively shade, that of the date palm and
            olive is greyish or glaucous; of the acacia, mimosa, and sycamore, either dark or dull,
            viewed in the mass. I have seen nothing as yet like the verdure I was led to expect from
            the descriptions usually given by travellers in this country; there is no lack of green
            it is true, but it is in strips or patches, intersecting which the native brown of the
            soil is ever presenting itself in strong contrast. No vegetation adorns either bank of
            the Nile along any part of the vast distance I have yet traversed from Alexandria hither
            (to Osiout); its shores gradually increase in height as we advance, and although of a
            rocky character in a few places, are for the most part composed of a soft dark brown
            alluvium, which is constantly crumbling, and falling into the stream, often in masses
            from a few hundred weight to several tons at a time, by which the course of the river is
            constantly undergoing alteration: so that even were it navigable for vessels of any
            great burden, which the innumerable shallows and shifting banks preclude, any survey
            would in a few years be wholly obsolete and useless.</p>

         <p>Siout, Esiout, or Osiout, December 9th. We arrived at this place, at present the capital
            of Upper Egypt, and the ancient Lycopolis, after a tedious passage from Manfalout, owing
            to the wind failing us entirely. As we propose stopping a day or two here on our return
            voyage, to visit the tombs and grottos in the mountains behind the town, I will not now
            attempt a description of a place imperfectly seen by us as yet, but will only give a
            slight sketch of its situation, which is the most picturesque of any town we have yet
            visited in Egypt. The valley of the Nile is here exceedingly broad, and the range of
            lofty limestone hills which shuts it out from the desert, recedes from both banks,
            leaving a wide plain of great fertility, and in a high state of cultivation between the
            river banks and the hills. The town is the third in size of those in Egypt, and is
            stated to have a population of 20,000 souls. Like Cairo, it is walled round, and the
            bazaars rank next to those of that city for the variety of goods they display. Siout is
            noted for its manufactures of pipe bowls, some of which we inspected, and were surprised
            at the elegance of the designs of the better kinds, and the finish of the workmanship.
            The limestone ranges on the western, or Lybian side of the valley, assuming here quite a
            mountainous character, are pierced with innumerable tombs quite visible from the plain
            below. The approach to Siout from the small village of El Khamra, which may be called
            its port, and about the same distance from the town as Boulak is from Cairo, is
            exceedingly pretty, passing along a broad raised causeway planted with willows, and
            running across fertile fields and gardens to the very gate of the town. We rode to the
            city on excellent donkeys to make purchases, followed by the greater part of our
            Nubians, decked out in their best attire, Ameen in particular, and our boy Mohammed, far
            outshining the others in the taste and gaiety of their costume, and bent like ourselves,
            on marketiog at the last town where coffee, tobacco, and other requisites can be
            obtained of good quality. Having spent an hour or two in visiting the bazaars and the
            few other objects of interest it presents, we took leave for a time of the capital of
            Upper Egypt, and returned to our boat at El Khamra.</p>

         <p>Believe me, Dear E Your affectionate Brother, William Arnold Beomfield.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
