<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>October 28, 1865: Mrs. Austin, ALEXANDRIA, October 28, 1865.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>I am truly grieved to hear of your wrist and to see your writing look cramped. I arrived
            here on Thursday after a splendid passage and was very comfortable on board. I found M.
            Olagnier waiting for me, and Omar, of course, and am _installé_ at Ross’s till my boat
            gets done which I am told will be in six days. She will be remarkably comfortable. Omar
            had caused a sort of divan with a roof and back to be constructed just outside the
            cabin-door where I always sat every evening, which will be the most delightful little
            nest one can conceive. I shall sit like a Pasha there. </p>
         <p> My cough is still very harassing, but my chest less tight and painful, and I feel less
            utterly knocked down. The weather is beautiful here just now—warm and not nearly so damp
            as usual. </p>
         <p> Lord Edward St. Maur was on board, he has much of his aunt’s pleasantness. Also a very
            young Bombay Merchant—a Muslim who uttered not one syllable to any one but to me. His
            talk was just like that of a well-bred and intelligent young Englishman. I am glad to
            say that his views of the state of India were very encouraging—he seemed convinced that
            the natives were gradually working their way up to more influence, and said ‘We shall
            have to thank you for a better form of government by far than any native one ever would
            have been’—he added, ‘We Muslims have this advantage over the Hindus—that our religion
            is no barrier at all, socially or politically—between us and you—as theirs is. I mean it
            ought not to be when both faiths are cleared of superstition and fanaticism.’ He spoke
            very highly of Sir Bartle Frere but said ‘I wish it were possible for more English
            _gentlemen_ to come out to India.’ He had been two years in England on mercantile
            business and was going back to his brother Ala-ed-deen much pleased with the English in
            England. It is one of the most comforting _Erscheinungen_ I have seen coming from
            India—if that sort of good sense is pretty common among the very young men they
            certainly will work their way up. </p>
         <p> I should like to see Bayley’s article though I am quite sick of my book—it is very
            ungracious of me, but I can’t help it.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
