<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>February 7, 1886: Mrs. Austin, Tuesday, 7 Ramadan.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST MUTTER, </p>
         <p> I have just received your letter of Christmas-day, and am glad to answer it with a
            really amended report of myself. I had a very slight return a week ago, but for the last
            five or six days the daily flushing and fever has also ceased. I sent for one of the
            Arab doctors of the Azizeeyeh steamer to see Omar, and myself also, and he was very
            attentive, and took a note of medicines to send me from <placeName ref="Cairo"
               >Cairo</placeName> by a _confrère_: and when I offered a fee he said, ‘God forbid—it
            is only our duty to do anything in the world for you.’ Likewise a very nice Dr. Ingram
            saw some of my worst cases for me, and gave me good advice and help; but I want better
            books—Kesteven is very useful, as far as it goes, but I want something more
            _ausführlich_ and scientific. Ramadan is a great trouble to me, though Sheykh Yussuf
            tells the people not to fast, if I forbid it: but many are ill from having begun it, and
            one fine old man of about fifty-five died of apoplexy on the fourth night. My Christian
            patient is obstinate, and fasts, in spite of me, and will, I think, seal his fate; he
            was so much better after the blistering and Dr. Ingram’s mixture. I wish you could have
            seen a lad of eighteen or so, who came here to-day for medicine. I think I never saw
            such sweet frank, engaging manners, or ever heard any one express himself better: quite
            _une nature distinguée_, not the least handsome, but the most charming countenance and
            way of speaking. </p>
         <p> My good friend the Maōhn spent the evening with me, and told me all the story of his
            marriage, though quite ‘unfit to meet the virtuous eyes of British propriety—’ as I read
            the other day in some paper apropos of I forget what—it will give you an idea of the
            feelings of a Muslim _honnête homme_, which Seleem is through and through. He knew his
            wife before he married her, she being twenty-five or twenty-six, and he a boy; she fell
            in love with him, and at seventeen he married her, and they have had ten children, all
            alive but two, and a splendid race they are. He told me how she courted him with glasses
            of sherbet and trays of sweatmeats, and how her mother proposed the marriage, and how
            she hesitated on account of the difference of age, but, of course, at last consented:
            all with the naïvest vanity in his own youthful attractions, and great extolling of her
            personal charms, and of her many virtues. When he was sent up here she would not, or
            could not, leave her children. On the Sitt’s arrival his slave girl was arrogant, and
            refused to kiss her hand, and spoke saucily of her age, whereupon Seleem gave her in
            marriage to a black man and pays for her support, as long as she likes to suckle the
            child he (Seleem) had by her, which child will in due time return to his house. _Kurz_,
            the fundamental idea in it all, in the mind of an upright man, is, that if a man ‘takes
            up’ with a woman at all, he must make himself responsible for her before the world; and
            above all for the fate of any child he may have by her (you see the Prophet of the Arabs
            did not contemplate ladies _qui savent nager_ so well in the troubled waters of life as
            we are now blessed with. I don’t mean to say that many men are as scrupulous as my
            excellent friend Seleem, either here or even in our own moral society). All this was
            told with expressions quite incompatible with our manners, though not at all _leste_—and
            he expatiated on his wife’s personal charms in a very quaint way; the good lady is now
            hard upon sixty and looks it fully; but he evidently is as fond of her as ever. As a
            curious trait of primitive manners, he told me of her piety and boundless hospitality;
            how when some friends came late one evening, unexpectedly, and there was only a bit of
            meat, she killed a sheep and cooked it for them with her own hands. And this is a
            Cairene lady, and quite a lady too, in manners and appearance. The day I dined there she
            was dressed in very ragged, old cotton clothes, but spotlessly clean; and she waited on
            me with a kind, motherly pleasure, that quite took away the awkwardness I felt at
            sitting down while she stood. In a few days she and her husband are to dine with me, a
            thing which no Arab couple ever did before (I mean dine out together), and the old lady
            was immensely amused at the idea. Omar will cook and all male visitors will be sent to
            the kitchen. Now that I understand all that is said to me, and a great deal of the
            general conversation, it is much more amusing. Seleem Effendi jokes me a great deal
            about my blunders, especially my lack of _politikeh_, the Greek word for what we should
            call flummery; and my saying _lazim_ (you must, or rather _il faut_), instead of humble
            entreaties. I told him to teach me better, but he laughed heartily, and said, ‘No, no,
            when you say _lazim_, it is _lazim_, and nobody wants the stick to force him to say
            _Hadr_ (ready) O Sheykh-el-Arab, O Emeereh.’ </p>
         <p> Fancy my surprise the other day just when I was dictating letters to Sheykh Yussuf
            (letters of introduction for Ross’s inspecting agent) with three or four other people
            here, in walked Miss North (Pop) whom I have not seen since she was a child. She and her
            father were going up the second cataract. She has done some sketches which, though
            rather unskilful, were absolutely true in colour and effect, and are the very first that
            I have seen that are so. I shall see something of them on their return. She seemed very
            pleasant. Mr. North looked rather horrified at the turbaned society in which he found
            himself. I suppose it did look odd to English eyes. </p>
         <p> We have had three days of the south wind, which the ‘Saturday Review’ says I am not to
            call Samoom; and I was poorly, and kept in bed two days with a cold. Apropos, I will
            give you the Luxor contribution towards the further confusion of the Samoom (or Simoom)
            controversy. I told Sheykh Yussuf that an English newspaper, written by particularly
            clever people, said that I was wrong to call the bad wind here ‘Samoom,’ (it was in an
            article on Palgrave’s book, I think). Sheykh Yussuf said, ‘True, oh lady, no doubt those
            learned gentlemen’ (politely saluting them with his hand) ‘thought one such as thou
            shouldest have written classical Arabic (_Arabi fossieh_), and have called it “_al
            Daboor_;” nevertheless, it is proper to write it “Samoom,” not, as some do “Simoom,”
            which is the plural of _sim_ (poison).’ I shook my head, and said, I did not recollect
            _al Daboor_. Then my Reis, sitting at the door, offered his suggestion. ‘Probably the
            English, who it is well known are a nation of sailors, use the name given to the land
            wind by _el-baharieh_ (the boatmen), and call it _el-mereeseh_.’ ‘But,’ said I, ‘the
            clever gentlemen say that I am wrong altogether, and never can have seen a _real_
            Samoom, for that would have killed me in ten minutes.’ Hereupon Sheykh Mohammed
            el-Abab’deh, who is not nearly so polished as his brother Hassan, burst into a regular
            bedawee roar of laughter, and said, ‘Yah! do the _Ganassil_ (Europeans) take thee for a
            rat, oh lady? Whoever heard of _el Beni Adam_ (the children of Adam) dying of the wind?
            Men die of thirst quicker when the Samoom blows and they have no water. But no one ever
            died of the wind alone, except the rats—they do.’ I give you the opinion of three
            ‘representative men—’ scholar, sailor, and bedawee; if that helps you to a solution of
            the controversy. </p>
         <p> We have just had a scene, rather startling to notions about fatalism, etc. Owing to the
            importation of a good deal of cattle from the Soudan, there is an expectation of the
            prevalence of small-pox, and the village barbers are busy vaccinating in all directions
            to prevent the infection brought, either by the cattle or, more likely, by their
            drivers. Now, my maid had told me she had never been vaccinated, and I sent for Hajjee
            Mahmood to cut my hair and vaccinate her. To my utter amazement the girl, who had never
            shown any religious bigotry, and does not fast, or make any demonstrations, refused
            peremptorily. It appears that the priests and sisters appointed by the enlightened
            administration of Prussia instil into their pupils and penitents that vaccination is a
            ‘tempting of God.’ _Oh oui_, she said, _je sais bien que chez nous mes parents pouvaient
            recevoir un procès verbal, mais il vaut mieux cela que d’aller contre la volonté de
            Dieu. Si Dieu le veut, j’aurai la petite-vérole, et s’il ne veut pas, je ne l’aurai
            pas_. I scolded her pretty sharply, and said it was not only stupid, but selfish. ‘But
            what can one do?’ as Hajjee Mahmood said, with a pitying shake of his head; ‘these
            Christians are so ignorant!’ He blushed, and apologized to me, and said, ‘It is not
            their fault; all this want of sense is from the priests who talk folly to them for
            money, and to keep them afraid before themselves. Poor things, _they_ don’t know the
            Word of God.—“Help thyself, oh my servant, and I will help thee.”’ This is the second
            contest I have had on this subject. Last year it was with a Copt, who was all _Allah
            kereem_ and so on about his baby, with his child of four dying of small-pox. ‘Oh, man,’
            said Sheykh Yussuf, ‘if the wall against which I am now sitting were to shake above my
            head, should I fold my feet under me and say _Allah kereem_, or should I use the legs
            God has given me to escape from it?’ </p>
         <p> I had a visit the other day from a lady who, as I was informed, had been a harlot in
            Siout. She has repented, and married a converted Copt. They are a droll pair of
            penitents, so very smart in their dress and manner. But no one _se scandalise_ at their
            antecedents—neither is it proper to repent in sackcloth and ashes, or to confess sins,
            except to God alone. You are not to _indulge_ in telling them to others; it is an
            offence. Repent inwardly, and be ashamed to show it before the people—ask pardon of God
            only. A little of this would do no harm in Europe, methinks. </p>
         <p> Here is a pretty story for you from the _Hadeth en-Nebbee_ (sayings of the Prophet).
            ‘Two prophets were sitting together, and discoursing of prayer and the difficulty of
            fixing the attention entirely on the act. One said to the other, “Not even for the
            duration of two _rekahs_ (prayers ending with the prostration and _Allah akbar_) can a
            man fix his mind on God alone.” The other said, “Nay, but I can do it!” “Say then two
            _rekahs_,” replied the elder of the two; “I will give thee my cloak.” Now he wore two
            cloaks—a new handsome red one and an old shabby blue one. The younger prophet rose,
            raised his hands to his head, said _Allah akbar_, and bent to the ground for his first
            _rekah_; as he rose again he thought “Will he give me the red cloak or the blue, I
            wonder?”’ It is very stupid of me not to write down all the pretty stories I hear, but
            this one is a capital specimen of Arab wit. Some day I must bring over Omar with me,
            Inshallah, to England, and he will tell you stories like Scheherazade herself. A jolly
            Nubian Alim told me the other night how in his village no man ever eats meat, except on
            Bairam day: but one night a woman had a piece of meat given her by a traveller; she put
            it in the oven and went out. During her absence her husband came in and smelt it, and as
            it was just the time of the _eshé_ (first prayers one hour after sunset), he ran up to
            the hill outside the village, and began to chaunt forth the _tekbeer_ with all his
            might—_Allah akbar_, _Allah akbar_, etc. etc., till the people ran to see what was the
            matter. ‘Why, to-day is Bairam,’ says he. ‘Where is thy witness, O man?’ ‘The meat in
            the oven—the meat in the oven.’</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
