<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>February 22, 1866: Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, LUXOR, February 22, 1866.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK, </p>
         <p> The weather here is just beginning to get warm, and I of course to get better. There
            has been a good deal of nervous headache here this Ramadan. I had to attend the Kadee,
            and several more. My Turkish neighbour at Karnac has got a _shaitan_ (devil), _i.e._
            epileptic fits, and I was sent for to exorcise him, which I am endeavouring to do with
            nitrate of silver, etc.; but I fear imagination will kill him, so I advise him to go to
               <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>, and leave the devil-haunted house. I have
            this minute killed the first snake of this year—a sign of summer. </p>
         <p> I was so pleased to see two Mr. Watsons—your opposite neighbours—who said they saw you
            every morning go down the street—_ojala_! that I did so too! I liked Mr. and Mrs. Webb
            of Newstead Abbey very much; nice, hearty, pleasant, truly English people. </p>
         <p> There have not been above twenty or thirty boats up this year—mostly Americans. There
            are some here now, very nice people, with four little children, who create quite an
            excitement in the place, and are ‘mashallahed’ no end. Their little fair faces do look
            very pretty here, and excite immense admiration. </p>
         <p> Seyd has just come in to take my letter to the steamer which is now going down. So
            _addio_, dearest Alick. I am much better but still weakish, and very _triste_ at my long
            separation.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
