<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>April 13, 1863: To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, CAIRO, April 13, 1863.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK,</p>

         <p>You will have heard from my mother of my ill luck, falling sick again. The fact is that
            the spring in Egypt is very trying, and I came down the river a full month too soon.
            People do tell such lies about the heat. To-day is the first warm day we have had; till
            now I have been shivering, and Sally too. I have been out twice, and saw the holy
            Mahmaal rest for its first station outside the town, it is a deeply affecting sight—all
            those men prepared to endure such hardship. They halt among the tombs of the Khalìfah,
            such a spot. Omar’s eyes were full of tears and his voice shaking with emotion, as he
            talked about it and pointed out the Mahmaal and the Sheykh al-Gemel, who leads the
            sacred camel, naked to the waist with flowing hair. Muslim piety is so unlike what
            Europeans think it is, so full of tender emotions, so much more sentimental than we
            imagine—and it is wonderfully strong. I used to hear Omar praying outside my door while
            I was so ill, ‘O God, make her better. O my God, let her sleep,’ as naturally as we
            should say, ‘I hope she’ll have a good night.’</p>

         <p>The Sultan’s coming is a kind of riddle. No one knows what he wants. The Pasha has
            ordered all the women of the lower classes to keep indoors while he is here. Arab women
            are outspoken, and might shout out their grievances to the great Sultan.</p>

         <p>_April_ 15.—I continue to get better slowly, and in a few days will go down to
            Alexandria. Omar is gone to <placeName ref="Boulak">Boulak</placeName> to inquire the
            cost of a boat, as I am not fond of the railroad, and have a good deal of heavy baggage,
            cooking utensils, etc., which the railway charges enormously for. The black slave girl,
            sent as a present to the American Consul-General, is as happy as possible, and sings
            quaint, soft little Kordofan songs all day. I hope you won’t object to my bringing her
            home. She wails so terribly when Omar tells her she is not my slave, for fear I should
            leave her, and insists on being my slave. She wants to be a present to Rainie, the
            little Sitt, and laughs out so heartily at the thought of her. She is very quiet and
            gentle, poor little savage, and the utter slavishness of the poor little soul quite
            upsets me; she has no will of her own. Now she has taken to talking, and tells all her
            woes and how _batal_ (bad) everyone was at Khartoum; and then she rubs her little black
            nose on my hand, and laughs so merrily, and says all is _quyis keteer_ (very good) here,
            and she hugs herself with delight. I think Rainie will like her very much.</p>

         <p>I am going to visit an old Muslim French painter’s family. He has an Arab wife and
            grown-up daughters, and is a very agreeable old man with a store of Arab legends; I am
            going to persuade him to write them and let me translate them into English. The Sultan
            goes away to-day. Even water to drink has been brought from Constantinople; I heard that
            from Hekekian Bey, who formerly owned the eunuch who is now Kislar Aghasy to the Sultan
            himself. Hekekian had the honour of kissing his old slave’s hand. If anyone tries to
            make you believe any bosh about civilization in Egypt, laugh at it. The real life and
            the real people are exactly as described in the most veracious of books, the ‘Thousand
            and One Nights’; the tyranny is the same, the people are not altered—and very charming
            people they are. If I could but speak the language I could get into Arab society here
            through two or three different people, and see more than many Europeans who have lived
            here all their lives. The Arabs are keenly alive to the least prejudice against them,
            but when they feel quite safe on that point they rather like the amusement of a
            stranger.</p>

         <p>Omar devised a glorious scheme, if I were only well and strong, of putting me in a
            takterrawan and taking me to Mecca in the character of his mother, supposed to be a
            Turk. To a European man, of course, it would be impossible, but an enterprising woman
            might do it easily with a Muslim confederate. Fancy seeing the pilgrimage! In a few days
            I shall go down to Alexandria, if it makes me ill again I must return to Europe or go to
            Beyrout. I can’t get a boat under £12; thus do the Arabs understand competition; the
            owner of boats said so few were wanted, times were bad on account of the railway, etc.,
            he must have double what he used to charge. In vain Omar argued that that was not the
            way to get employment. ‘Maleesh!’ (Never mind!), and so I must go by rail. Is not that
            Eastern? Up the river, where there is no railroad, I might have had it at half that
            rate. All you have ever told me as most Spanish in Spain is in full vigour here, and
            also I am reminded of Ireland at every turn; the same causes produce the same
            effects.</p>

         <p>To-day the Khamseen is blowing and it is decidedly hot, quite unlike the heat at the
            Cape; this is close and gloomy, no sunshine. Altogether the climate is far less bright
            than I expected, very, very inferior to the Cape. Nevertheless, I heartily agree to the
            Arab saying: ‘He who has drunk Nile water will ever long to drink it again’; and when a
            graceful woman in a blue shirt and veil lifts a huge jar from her shoulder and holds it
            to your lips with a hearty smile and welcome, it tastes doubly sweet. _Alhamdulillah_!
            Sally says all other water is like bad small-beer compared to sweet ale after the Nile
            water. When the Khamseen is over, Omar insists on my going to see the tree and the well
            where Sittina Mariam rested with Seyidna Issa {55} in her arms during the flight into
            Egypt. It is venerated by Christian and Muslim alike, and is a great place for feasting
            and holiday-making out of doors, which the Arabs so dearly love. Do write and tell me
            what you wish me to do. If it were not that I cannot endure not to see you and the
            children, I would stay here and take a house at the Abbassieh in the desert; but I could
            not endure it. Nor can I endure this wandering life much longer. I must come home and
            die in peace if I don’t get really better. Write to Alexandria next.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
