<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>November 21, 1863: Mrs. Austin, CAIRO, November 21, 1863.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST MUTTER,</p>

         <p>I shall stay on here till it gets colder, and then go up the Nile either in a steamer or
            a boat. The old father of my donkey-boy, Hassan, gave me a fine illustration of Arab
            feeling towards women to-day. I asked if Abd el-Kader was coming here, as I had heard;
            he did not know, and asked me if he were not _Achul en-Benàt_, a brother of girls. I
            prosaically said I did not know if he had sisters. ‘The Arabs, O lady, call that man a
            “brother of girls” to whom God has given a clean heart to love all women as his sisters,
            and strength and courage to fight for their protection.’ Omar suggested a ‘thorough
            gentleman’ as the equivalent of Abou Hassan’s title. Our European _galimatias_ about the
            ‘smiles of the fair,’ etc., look very mean beside ‘Achul en Benàt,’ methinks. Moreover,
            they carry it into common life. Omar was telling me of some little family tribulations,
            showing that he is not a little henpecked. His wife wanted all his money. I asked how
            much she had of her own, as I knew she had property. ‘Oh, ma’am! I can’t speak of that,
            shame for me if I ask what money she got.’ A man married at Alexandria, and took home
            the daily provisions for the first week; after that he neglected it for two days, and
            came home with a lemon in his hand. He asked for some dinner, and his wife placed the
            stool and the tray and the washing basin and napkin, and in the tray the lemon cut in
            quarters. ‘Well, and the dinner?’ ‘Dinner! you want dinner? Where from? What man are you
            to want women when you don’t keep them? I am going to the Cadi to be divorced from you;’
            and she did. The man must provide all necessaries for his Hareem, and if she has money
            or earns any she spends it in dress; if she makes him a skullcap or a handkerchief he
            must pay her for her work. _Tout n’est pas roses_ for these Eastern tyrants, not to
            speak of the unbridled license of tongue allowed to women and children. Zeyneb hectors
            Omar and I cannot persuade him to check her. ‘How I say anything to it, that one child?’
            Of course, the children are insupportable, and, I fancy, the women little better.</p>

         <p> A poor neighbour of mine lost his little boy yesterday, and came out in the streets, as
            usual, for sympathy. He stood under my window leaning his head against the wall, and
            sobbing and crying till, literally, his tears wetted the dust. He was too grieved to
            tear off his turban or to lament in form, but clasped his hands and cried, ‘Yah weled,
            yah weled, yah weled’ (O my boy, my boy). The bean-seller opposite shut his shop, the
            dyer took no notice but smoked his pipe. Some people passed on, but many stopped and
            stood round the poor man, saying nothing, but looking concerned. Two were well-dressed
            Copts on handsome donkeys, who dismounted, and all waited till he went home, when about
            twenty men accompanied him with a respectful air. How strange it seems to us to go out
            into the street and call on the passers-by to grieve with one! I was at the house of
            Hekekian Bey the other day when he received a parcel from his former slave, now the
            Sultan’s chief eunuch. It contained a very fine photograph of the eunuch—whose face,
            though negro, is very intelligent and of charming expression—a present of illustrated
            English books, and some printed music composed by the Sultan, Abd el Aziz, himself. _O
            tempera_! _O mores_! one was a waltz. The very ugliest and scrubbiest of street dogs has
            adopted me—like the Irishman who wrote to Lord Lansdowne that he had selected him as his
            patron—and he guards the house and follows me in the street. He is rewarded with scraps,
            and Sally cost me a new tin mug by letting the dog drink out of the old one, which was
            used to scoop the water from the jars, forgetting that Omar and Zeyneb could not drink
            after the poor beast.</p>

         <p>_Monday_.—I went yesterday to the port of <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>,
               <placeName ref="Boulak">Boulak</placeName>, to see Hassaneyn Effendi about boats. He
            was gone up the Nile, and I sat with his wife—a very nice Turkish woman who speaks
            English to perfection—and heard all sorts of curious things. I heard the whole story of
            an unhappy marriage made by Leyla, my hostess’s sister, and much <placeName ref="Cairo"
               >Cairo</placeName> gossip. Like all Eastern ladies that I have seen she complains of
            indigestion, and said she knew she ought to go out more and to walk, but custom _e
            contra il nostro decoro_.</p>

         <p>Mr. Thayer will be back in Egypt on December 15, so I shall embark about that time, as
            he may want his house here. It is now a little fresh in the early morning, but like fine
            English summer weather.</p>

         <p>_Tuesday_.—Since I have been here my cough is nearly gone, and I am better for having
            good food again. Omar manages to get good mutton, and I have discovered that some of the
            Nile fish is excellent. The _abyad_, six or eight feet long and very fat, is delicious,
            and I am told there are still better; the eels are delicate and good too. Maurice might
            hook an _abyad_, but how would he land him? The worst is that everything is just double
            the price of last year, as, of course, no beef can be eaten at all, and the draught oxen
            being dead makes labour dear as well. The high Nile was a small misfortune compared to
            the murrain. There is a legend about it, of course. A certain Sheykh el-Beled
            (burgomaster) of some place—not mentioned—lost his cattle, and being rich defied God,
            said he did not care, and bought as many more; they died too, and he continued
            impenitent and defiant, and bought on till he was ruined, and now he is sinking into the
            earth bodily, though his friends dig and dig without ceasing night and day. It is
            curious how like the German legends the Arab ones are. All those about wasting bread
            wantonly are almost identical. If a bit is dirty, Omar carefully gives it to the dog; if
            clean, he keeps it in a drawer for making breadcrumbs for cutlets; not a bit must fall
            on the floor. In other things they are careless enough, but _das liebe Brod_ is
            sacred—_vide_ Grimm’s _Deutsche Sagen_. I am constantly struck with resemblances to
            German customs. A Fellah wedding is very like the German _Bauern hochzeit_ firing of
            guns and display of household goods, only on a camel instead of a cart. I have been
            trying to get a teacher of Arabic, but it is very hard to find one who knows any
            European language, and the consular dragoman asks four dollars a lesson. I must wait
            till I get to Thebes, where I think a certain young Said can teach me. Meanwhile I am
            beginning to understand rather more and to speak a very little. Please direct to me to
            Briggs and Co. at <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>; if I am gone, the letters
            will follow up the river.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
