<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>January 5, 1864: Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, Tuesday, January 5, 1864.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>We left Siout this afternoon. The captain had announced that we should start at ten
            o’clock, so I did not go into the town, but sent Omar to buy food and give my letter and
            best salaam to Wassef. But the men of Darfoor all went off declaring that they would
            stop, promising to cut off the captain’s head if he went without them. Hassan Effendi,
            the Turk, was furious, and threatened to telegraph his complaints to <placeName
               ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> if we did not go directly, and the poor captain was in
            a sad quandary. He appealed to me, peaceably sitting on the trunk of a palm-tree with
            some poor _fellaheen_ (of whom more anon). I uttered the longest sentence I could
            compose in Arabic, to the effect that he was captain, and that while on the boat we were
            all bound to obey him. ‘_Mashallah_! one English Hareem is worth more than ten men for
            sense; these Ingeleez have only one word both for themselves and for other people:
            _doghree_—_doghree_ (right is right); this Ameereh is ready to obey like a memlook, and
            when she has to command—whew!’—with a most expressive toss back of the head. The bank
            was crowded with poor _fellaheen_ who had been taken for soldiers and sent to await the
            Pasha’s arrival at Girgeh; three weeks they lay there, and were then sent down to Soohaj
            (the Pasha wanted to see them himself and pick out the men he liked); eight days more at
            Soohaj, then to Siout eight days more, and meanwhile Ismail Pasha has gone back to
               <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> and the poor souls may wait indefinitely,
            for no one will venture to remind the Pasha of their trifling existence. _Wallah_,
            _wallah_! </p>
         <p> While I was walking on the bank with M. and Mme. Mounier, a person came up and saluted
            them whose appearance puzzled me. Don’t call me a Persian when I tell you it was an
            eccentric Bedawee young lady. She was eighteen or twenty at most, dressed like a young
            man, but small and feminine and rather pretty, except that one eye was blind. Her dress
            was handsome, and she had women’s jewels, diamonds, etc., and a European watch and
            chain. Her manner was excellent, quite _ungenirt_, and not the least impudent or
            swaggering, and I was told—indeed, I could hear—that her language was beautiful, a thing
            much esteemed among Arabs. She is a virgin and fond of travelling and of men’s society,
            being very clever, so she has her dromedary and goes about quite alone. No one seemed
            surprised, no one stared, and when I asked if it was _proper_, our captain was
            surprised. ‘Why not? if she does not wish to marry, she can go alone; if she does, she
            can marry—what harm? She is a virgin and free.’ She went to breakfast with the Mouniers
            on their boat (Mme. M. is Egyptian born, and both speak Arabic perfectly), and the young
            lady had many things to ask them, she said. She expressed her opinions pretty freely as
            far as I could understand her. Mme. Mounier had heard of her before, and said she was
            much respected and admired. M. Mounier had heard that she was a spy of the Pasha’s, but
            the people on board the boat here say that the truth was that she went before Said Pasha
            herself to complain of some tyrannical Moodir who ground and imprisoned the
            _fellaheen_—a bold thing for a girl to do. To me she seems, anyhow, far the most curious
            thing I have yet seen. </p>
         <p> The weather is already much warmer, it is nine in the evening, we are steaming along
            and I sit with the cabin window open. My cough is, of course, a great deal better.
            _Inshallah_! Above Keneh (about another 150 miles) it will go away. To-day, for the
            first time, I pulled my cloak over my head in the sun, it was so stinging hot—quite
            delicious, and it is the 5th of January. _Poveri voi_ in the cold! Our captain was
            prisoner for three years at Moscow and at Bakshi Serai, and declares he never saw the
            sun at all—hard lines for an Egyptian. Do you remember the cigarettes you bought for me
            at Eaux Bonnes? Well, I gave them to the old Turkish Effendi, who is dreadfully
            asthmatic, and he is enchanted; of course five other people came to be cured directly.
            The rhubarb pills are a real comfort to travellers, for they can’t do much harm, and
            inspire great confidence. </p>
         <p> Luckily we left all the fleas behind in the fore-cabin, for the benefit of the poor old
            Turk, who, I hear, suffers severely. The divans were all brand-new, and the fleas came
            in the cotton stuffing, for there are no live things of any sort in the rest of the
            boat. </p>
         <p> GIRGEH, _January_ 9, 1864. </p>
         <p> We have put in here for the night. To-day we took on board three convicts in chains,
            two bound for Fazogloo, one for calumny and perjury, and one for manslaughter. Hard
            labour for life in that climate will soon dispose of them. The third is a petty thief
            from Keneh who has been a year in chains in the Custom-house of Alexandria, and is now
            being taken back to be shown in his own place in his chains. The _causes célèbres_ of
            this country would be curious reading; they do their crimes so differently to us. If I
            can get hold of anyone who can relate a few cases well, I’ll write them down. Omar has
            told me a few, but he may not know the details quite exactly. </p>
         <p> I made further inquiries about the Bedawee lady, who is older than she looks, for she
            has travelled constantly for ten years. She is rich and much respected, and received in
            all the best houses, where she sits with the men all day and sleeps in the hareem. She
            has been in the interior of Africa and to Mecca, speaks Turkish, and M. Mounier says he
            found her extremely agreeable, full of interesting information about all the countries
            she had visited. As soon as I can talk I must try and find her out; she likes the
            company of Europeans. </p>
         <p> Here is a contribution to folk-lore, new even to Lane I think. When the coffee-seller
            lights his stove in the morning, he makes two cups of coffee of the best and nicely
            sugared, and pours them out all over the stove, saying, ‘God bless or favour Sheykh
            Shadhilee and his descendants.’ The blessing on the saint who invented coffee of course
            I knew, and often utter, but the libation is new to me. You see the ancient religion
            crops up even through the severe faith of Islam. If I could describe all the details of
            an Arab, and still more of a Coptic, wedding, you would think I was relating the
            mysteries of Isis. At one house I saw the bride’s father looking pale and anxious, and
            Omar said, ‘I think he wants to hold his stomach with both hands till the women tell him
            if his daughter makes his face white.’ It was such a good phrase for the sinking at
            heart of anxiety. It certainly seems more reasonable that a woman’s misconduct should
            blacken her father’s face than her husband’s. There are a good many things about hareem
            here which I am barbarian enough to think extremely good and rational. An old Turk of
               <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>, who had been in Europe, was talking to an
            Englishman a short time ago, who politely chaffed him about Mussulman license. The
            venerable Muslim replied, ‘Pray, how many women have you, who are quite young, seen
            (that is the Eastern phrase) in your whole life?’ The Englishman could not count—of
            course not. ‘Well, young man, I am old, and was married at twelve, and I have seen in
            all my life seven women; four are dead, and three are happy and comfortable in my house.
            _Where are all yours_?’ Hassaneyn Effendi heard the conversation, which passed in
            French, and was amused at the question. </p>
         <p> I find that the criminal convicted of calumny accused, together with twenty-nine others
            not in custody, the Sheykh-el-Beled of his place of murdering his servant, and produced
            a basket full of bones as proof, but the Sheykh-el-Beled produced the living man, and
            his detractor gets hard labour for life. The proceeding is characteristic of the
            childish _ruses_ of this country. I inquired whether the thief who was dragged in chains
            through the streets would be able to find work, and was told, ‘Oh, certainly; is he not
            a poor man? For the sake of God everyone will be ready to help him.’ An absolute
            uncertainty of justice naturally leads to this result. Our captain was quite shocked to
            hear that in my country we did not like to employ a returned convict. </p>
         <p> LUXOR, _January_ 13, 1864. </p>
         <p> We spent all the afternoon of Saturday at Keneh, where I dined with the English Consul,
            a worthy old Arab, who also invited our captain, and we all sat round his copper tray on
            the floor and ate with our fingers, the captain, who sat next me, picking out the best
            bits and feeding me and Sally with them. After dinner the French Consul, a Copt, one
            Jesus Buktor, sent to invite me to a fantasia at his house, where I found the Mouniers,
            the Moudir, and some other Turks, and a disagreeable Italian, who stared at me as if I
            had been young and pretty, and put Omar into a great fury. I was glad to see the
            dancing-girls, but I liked old Seyyid Achmet’s patriarchal ways much better than the
            tone of the Frenchified Copt. At first I thought the dancing queer and dull. One girl
            was very handsome, but cold and uninteresting; one who sang was also very pretty and
            engaging, and a dear little thing. But the dancing was contortions, more or less
            graceful, _very_ wonderful as gymnastic feats, and no more. But the captain called out
            to one Latifeh, an ugly, clumsy-looking wench, to show the Sitt what she could do. And
            then it was revealed to me. The ugly girl started on her feet and became the ‘serpent of
            old Nile,’—the head, shoulders and arms eagerly bent forward, waist in, and haunches
            advanced on the bent knees—the posture of a cobra about to spring. I could not call it
            _voluptuous_ any more than Racine’s _Phèdre_. It is _Venus toute entière à sa proie
            attachée_, and to me seemed tragic. It is far more realistic than the ‘fandango,’ and
            far less coquettish, because the thing represented is _au grande sérieux_, not
            travestied, _gazé_, or played with; and like all such things, the Arab men don’t think
            it the least improper. Of course the girls don’t commit any indecorums before European
            women, except the dance itself. Seyyid Achmet would have given me a fantasia, but he
            feared I might have men with me, and he had had a great annoyance with two Englishmen
            who wanted to make the girls dance naked, which they objected to, and he had to turn
            them out of his house after hospitably entertaining them. </p>
         <p> Our procession home to the boat was very droll. Mme. Mounier could not ride an Arab
            saddle, so I lent her mine and _enfourché’d_ my donkey, and away we went with men
            running with ‘meshhaals’ (fire-baskets on long poles) and lanterns, and the captain
            shouting out ‘Full speed!’ and such English phrases all the way—like a regular old salt
            as he is. We got here last night, and this morning Mustapha A’gha and the Nazir came
            down to conduct me up to my palace. I have such a big rambling house all over the top of
            the temple of Khem. How I wish I had you and the chicks to fill it! We had about twenty
            _fellahs_ to clean the dust of _three years_’ accumulation, and my room looks quite
            handsome with carpets and a divan. Mustapha’s little girl found her way here when she
            heard I was come, and it seemed quite pleasant to have her playing on the carpet with a
            dolly and some sugar-plums, and making a feast for dolly on a saucer, arranging the
            sugar-plums Arab fashion. She was monstrously pleased with Rainie’s picture and kissed
            it. Such a quiet, nice little brown tot, and curiously like Rainie and walnut-juice. </p>
         <p> [Picture: Luxor, by Edward Lear, showing Lady Duff Gordon’s house, now destroyed] </p>
         <p> The view all round my house is magnificent on every side, over the Nile in front facing
            north-west, and over a splendid range of green and distant orange buff hills to the
            south-east, where I have a spacious covered terrace. It is rough and dusty to the
            extreme, but will be very pleasant. Mustapha came in just now to offer me the loan of a
            horse, and to ask me to go to the mosque in a few nights to see the illumination in
            honour of a great Sheykh, a son of Sidi Hosseyn or Hassan. I asked whether my presence
            might not offend any Muslimeen, and he would not hear of such a thing. The sun set while
            he was here, and he asked if I objected to his praying in my presence, and went through
            his four _rekahs_ very comfortably on my carpet. My next-door neighbour (across the
            courtyard all filled with antiquities) is a nice little Copt who looks like an antique
            statue himself. I shall _voisiner_ with his family. He sent me coffee as soon as I
            arrived, and came to help. I am invited to El-Moutaneh, a few hours up the river, to
            visit the Mouniers, and to Keneh to visit Seyyid Achmet, and also the head of the
            merchants there who settled the price of a carpet for me in the bazaar, and seemed to
            like me. He was just one of those handsome, high-bred, elderly merchants with whom a
            story always begins in the Arabian Nights. When I can talk I will go and see a real Arab
            hareem. A very nice English couple, a man and his wife, gave me breakfast in their boat,
            and turned out to be business connections of Ross’s, of the name of Arrowsmith; they
            were going to Assouan, and I shall see them on their way back. I asked Mustapha about
            the Arab young lady, and he spoke very highly of her, and is to let me know if she comes
            here and to offer hospitality from me: he did not know her name—she is called ‘el
            _Hággeh_’ (the Pilgrimess). </p>
         <p> _Thursday_.—Now I am settled in my Theban palace, it seems more and more beautiful, and
            I am quite melancholy that you cannot be here to enjoy it. The house is very large and
            has good thick walls, the comfort of which we feel to-day for it blows a hurricane; but
            indoors it is not at all cold. I have glass windows and doors to some of the rooms. It
            is a lovely dwelling. Two funny little owls as big as my fist live in the wall under my
            window, and come up and peep in, walking on tip-toe, and looking inquisitive like the
            owls in the hieroglyphics; and a splendid horus (the sacred hawk) frequents my lofty
            balcony. Another of my contemplar gods I sacrilegiously killed last night, a whip snake.
            Omar is rather in consternation for fear it should be ‘the snake of the house,’ for
            Islam has not dethroned the _Dii lares et tutelares_. </p>
         <p> I have been ‘sapping’ at the _Alif Bey_ (A B C) to-day, under the direction of Sheykh
            Yussuf, a graceful, sweet-looking young man, with a dark brown face and such fine
            manners, in his _fellah_ dress—a coarse brown woollen shirt, a _libdeh_, or felt
            skull-cap, and a common red shawl round his head and shoulders; writing the wrong way is
            very hard work. Some men came to mend the staircase, which had fallen in and which
            consists of huge solid blocks of stone. One crushed his thumb and I had to operate on
            it. It is extraordinary how these people bear pain; he never winced in the least, and
            went off thanking God and the lady quite cheerfully. Till to-day the weather has been
            quite heavenly; last night I sat with my window open, it was so warm. If only I had you
            all here! How Rainie would play in the temple, Maurice fish in the Nile, and you go
            about with your spectacles on your nose. I think you would discard Frangi dress and take
            to a brown shirt and a _libdeh_, and soon be as brown as any _fellah_. It was so curious
            to see Sheykh Yussuf blush from shyness when he came in first; it shows quite as much in
            the coffee-brown Arab skin as in the fairest European—quite unlike the much
            lighter-coloured mulatto or Malay, who never change colour at all. A photographer who is
            living here showed me photographs done high up the White Nile. One negro girl is so
            splendid that I must get him to do me a copy to send you. She is not perfect like the
            Nubians, but so superbly strong and majestic. If I can get hold of a handsome _fellahah_
            here, I’ll get her photographed to show you in Europe what a woman’s breast can be, for
            I never knew it before I came here—it is the most beautiful thing in the world. The
            dancing-girl I saw moved her breasts by some extraordinary muscular effort, first one
            and then the other; they were just like pomegranates and gloriously independent of stays
            or any support.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
