<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>January 26, 1867: Mrs. Austin, LUXOR, January 26, 1867.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST MUTTER, </p>
         <p> I must betray dear Sheykh Yussuf’s confidence, and tell you his love story. </p>
         <p> A young fellow ran away with a girl he loved a short time ago, she having told him that
            her parents wanted to marry her to another, and that she would go to such a spot for
            water, and he must come on a horse, beat her and carry her off (the beating saves the
            maiden’s blushes). Well, the lad did it, and carried her to Salamieh where they were
            married, and then they went to Sheykh Yussuf to get him to conciliate the family, which
            he did. He told me the affair, and I saw he sympathized much with the runaways. ‘Ah,’ he
            said ‘Lady, it is love, and that is terrible, I can tell thee love is dreadful indeed to
            bear.’ Then he hesitated and blushed, and went on, ‘I felt it once, Lady, it was the
            will of God that I should love her who is now my wife. Thirteen years ago I loved her
            and wished to marry her, but my father, and her grandfather my uncle the Shereef, had
            quarrelled, and they took her and married her to another man. I never told anyone of it,
            but my liver was burning and my heart ready to burst for three years; but when I met her
            I fixed my eyes on the ground for fear she should see my love, and I said to myself, Oh
            Yussuf, God has afflicted thee, praise be unto Him, do thou remember thy blood (Shereef)
            and let thy conduct be that of the Beni Azra who when they are thus afflicted die rather
            than sin, for they have the strongest passion of love and the greatest honour. And I did
            not die but went to <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> to the Gama el-Azhar and
            studied, and afterwards I married twice, as thou knowest, but I never loved any but that
            one, and when my last wife died the husband of this one had just divorced her to take a
            younger and prettier one and my father desired me then to take her, but I was half
            afraid not knowing whether she would love me; but, Praise be to God I consented, and
            behold, poor thing, she also had loved me in like manner.’ I thought when I went to see
            her that she was unusually radiant with new-married happiness, and she talked of
            ‘el-Sheykh’ with singular pride and delight, and embraced me and called me ‘mother’ most
            affectionately. Is it not a pretty piece of regular Arab romance like Ghamem? </p>
         <p> My boat has gone up to-day with two very nice Englishmen in her. Their young Maltese
            dragoman, aged twenty-four, told me his father often talked of ‘the Commissioners’ and
            all they had done, and how things were changed in the island for the better. (1)
            Everything spiritual and temporal has been done for the boat’s safety in the
            Cataract—urgent letters to the Maōhn el Baudar, and him of Assouan to see to the men,
            and plenty of prayers and vows to Abu-l-Hajjaj on behalf of the ‘property of the Lady,’
            or _kurzweg_ ‘our boat’ as she is commonly called in Luxor. </p>
         <p> Here we have the other side of the misery of the Candian business; in Europe, of
            course, the obvious thing is the sufferings of the Cretans, but really I am more sorry
            for the poor fellah lads who are dragged away to fight in a quarrel they had no hand in
            raising, and with which they have no sympathy. The _Times_ suggests that the Sultan
            should relinquish the island, and that has been said in many an Egyptian hut long
            before. The Sultan is worn out, and the Muslims here know it, and say it would be the
            best day for the Arabs if he were driven out; that after all a Turk never was the true
            _Ameer el-Moomeneen_ (Commander of the Faithful). Only in Europe people talk and write
            as if it were all Muslim _versus_ Christian, and the Christians were all oppressed, and
            the Muslims all oppressors. I wish they could see the domineering of the Greeks and
            Maltese as Christians. The Englishman domineers as a free man and a Briton, which is
            different, and that is the reason why the Arabs wish for English rule, and would dread
            that of Eastern Christians. Well they may; for if ever the Greeks do reign in Stamboul
            the sufferings of the Muslims will satisfy the most eager fanatic that ever cursed
            Mahound. I know nothing of Turkey, but I have seen and heard enough to know that there
            are plenty of other divisions besides that of Christian and Muslim. Here in Egypt it is
            clear enough: it is Arab _versus_ Turk and the Copt siding with the stronger for his
            interest, while he rather sympathizes with his brother fellah. At all events the Copt
            don’t want other Christians to get power; he would far rather have a Muslim than a
            heretic ruler, above all the hated Greek. The Englishman he looks on as a variety of
            Muslim—a man who washes, has no pictures in his church, who has married bishops, and
            above all, who does not fast from all that has life for half the year, and this heresy
            is so extreme as not to give offence, unless he tries to convert. </p>
         <p> The Pasha’s sons have just been up the river: they ordered a reading of the Koran at
            the tomb of Abu-l-Hajjaj and gave every Alim sixpence. We have not left off chaffing (as
            Maurice would say) Sheykh Allah-ud-deen, the Muezzin, and sundry others on this superb
            backsheesh, and one old Fikee never knows whether to laugh, to cry, or to scold, when I
            ask to see the shawl and tarboosh he has bought with the presents of Pashas. Yussuf and
            the Kadee too had been called on to contribute baskets of bread to the steamer so that
            their sixpences were particularly absurd. </p>
         <p> The little boy whose father died is still with the Abab’deh, who will not let him
            travel to <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> till the weather is warmer and they
            find a safe person to be kind to him. Rachmeh says ‘Please God, he will go with the
            Sitt, perhaps.’ Hassan has consoled him with sugar-cane and indulgence, and if I lose
            Mabrook, and the little boy takes to me, he may fall into my hands as Achmet has done. I
            hear he is a good boy but a perfect savage; that however, I find makes no difference—in
            fact, I think they learn faster than those who have ways of their own. So I see Terence
            was a nigger! I would tell Rachmeh so if I could make him understand who Terence was,
            and that he, Rachmeh, stood in need of any encouragement, but the worthy fellow never
            imagines that his skin is in any way inferior to mine.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
