<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>April 18, 1863: To Mr. Tom Taylor, CAIRO, April 18, 1863.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>MY DEAR TOM,</p>

         <p>Your letter and Laura’s were a great pleasure to me in this distant land. I could not
            answer before, as I have been very ill. But Samaritans came with oil and wine and
            comforted me. It had an odd, dreary effect to hear my friend Hekekian Bey, a learned old
            Armenian, and De Leo Bey, my doctor, discoursing Turkish at my bedside, while my
            faithful Omar cried and prayed _Yah Robbeena_! _Yah Saatir_! (O Lord! O Preserver!)
            ‘don’t let her die.’</p>

         <p>Alick is quite right that I am in love with the Arabs’ ways, and I have contrived to see
            and know more of family life than many Europeans who have lived here for years. When the
            Arabs feel that one really cares for them, they heartily return it. If I could only
            speak the language I could see anything. <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> _is_
            the Arabian Nights; there is a little Frankish varnish here and there, but the
            government, the people—all is unchanged since that most veracious book was written. No
            words can describe the departure of the holy Mahmal and the pilgrims for Mecca. I spent
            half the day loitering about in the Bedaween tents admiring the glorious, free people.
            To see a Bedaween and his wife walk through the streets of <placeName ref="Cairo"
               >Cairo</placeName> is superb. Her hand resting on his shoulder, and scarcely deigning
            to cover her haughty face, she looks down on the Egyptian veiled woman who carries the
            heavy burden and walks behind her lord and master.</p>

         <p>By no deed of my own have I become a slave-owner. The American Consul-General turned
            over to me a black girl of eight or nine, and in consequence of her reports the poor
            little black boy who is the slave and marmiton of the cook here has been entreating Omar
            to beg me to buy him and take him with me. It is touching to see the two poor little
            black things recounting their woes and comparing notes. I went yesterday to deposit my
            cooking things and boat furniture at my washerwoman’s house. Seeing me arrive on my
            donkey, followed by a cargo of household goods, about eight or ten Arab women thronged
            round delighted at the idea that I was coming to live in their quarter, and offering me
            neighbourly services. Of course all rushed upstairs, and my old washerwoman was put to
            great expense in pipes and coffee. I think, as you, that I must have the ‘black drop,’
            and that the Arabs see it, for I am always told that I am like them, with praises of my
            former good looks. ‘You were beautiful Hareem once.’ Nothing is more striking to me than
            the way in which one is constantly reminded of Herodotus. The Christianity and the Islam
            of this country are full of the ancient worship, and the sacred animals have all taken
            service with Muslim saints. At Minieh one reigns over crocodiles; higher up I saw the
            hole of Æsculapius’ serpent at Gebel Sheykh Hereedee, and I fed the birds—as did
            Herodotus—who used to tear the cordage of boats which refused to feed them, and who are
            now the servants of Sheykh Naooneh, and still come on board by scores for the bread
            which no Reis dares refuse them. Bubastis’ cats are still fed in the Cadi’s court at
            public expense in <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>, and behave with singular
            decorum when ‘the servant of the cats’ serves them their dinner. Among gods, Amun Ra,
            the sun-god and serpent-killer, calls himself Mar Girgis (St. George), and is worshipped
            by Christians and Muslims in the same churches, and Osiris holds his festivals as
            riotously as ever at Tanta in the Delta, under the name of Seyd el Bedawee. The _fellah_
            women offer sacrifices to the Nile, and walk round ancient statues in order to have
            children. The ceremonies at births and burials are not Muslim, but ancient Egyptian.</p>

         <p>The Copts are far more close and reserved and backward than the Arabs, and they have
            been so repudiated by Europeans that they are doubly shy of us. The Europeans resent
            being called ‘Nazranee’ as a genteel Hebrew gentleman may shrink from ‘Jew.’ But I said
            boldly, ‘_Ana Nazraneeh_. _Alhamdulillah_!’ (I am a Nazranee. Praise be to God), and
            found that it was much approved by the Muslims as well as the Copts. Curious things are
            to be seen here in religion—Muslims praying at the tomb of Mar Girgis (St. George) and
            the resting-places of Sittina Mariam and Seyidna Issa, and miracles, brand-new, of an
            equally mixed description.</p>

         <p>If you have any power over any artists, send them to paint here. No words can describe
            either the picturesque beauty of <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> or the
            splendid forms of the people in Upper Egypt, and above all in Nubia. I was in raptures
            at seeing how superb an animal man (and woman) really is. My donkey-girl at Thebes,
            dressed like a Greek statue—Ward es-Sham (the Rose of Syria)—was a feast to the eyes;
            and here, too, what grace and sweetness, and how good is a drink of Nile water out of an
            amphora held to your lips by a woman as graceful as she is kindly. ‘May it benefit
            thee,’ she says, smiling with all her beautiful teeth and eyes. ‘_Alhamdulillah_,’ you
            reply; and it is worth thanking God for. The days of the beauty of <placeName
               ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> are numbered. The mosques are falling to decay, the
            exquisite lattice windows rotting away and replaced by European glass and jalousies.
            Only the people and the Government remain unchanged. Read all the pretty paragraphs
            about civilisation here, and then say, Bosh!</p>

         <p>If you know anyone coming here and wanting a good servant and dragoman, recommend my
            dear Omar Abou el-Haláweh of Alexandria. He has been my friend and companion, as well as
            my cook and general servant, now for six months, and we are very sad at our approaching
            separation. I am to spend a day in his house with his young wife at Alexandria, and to
            eat his bread. He sadly wants to go with me to Europe and to see my children. Sally, I
            think, is almost as fond of the Arabs as I am, and very popular. My poor ragged crew
            were for ever calling out ‘Yah Sara’ for some assistance or other, hurt fingers or such
            calamities; and the quantity of doctoring I did was fearful. Sally was constantly
            wishing for you to see all manner of things and to sketch. What a yarn I have made!</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
