<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>August 27, 1866: Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, OFF BOULAK, August 27, 1866.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK, </p>
         <p> Your letter of the 18th has this moment arrived. I am very glad to hear you are so much
            better. I am still seedy-ish, but no worse. Everybody is liver-sick this year, I give
            calomel and jalep all round—except to myself. </p>
         <p> The last two or three days we have been in great tribulation about the boat. On
            Saturday all her ribs were finished, and the planking and caulking ready to be put on,
            when in the night up came the old Nile with a rush, and threatened to carry her off; but
            by the favour of Abu-l-Hajjaj and Sheykh el-Bostawee she was saved in this wise. You
            remember the tall old steersman who went with us to Bedreeshayn, and whom we thought so
            ill-conditioned; well, he was in charge of a dahabieh close by, and he called up all the
            Reises and steermen to help. ‘Oh men of el-Bostawee, this is _our_ boat (_i.e._ we are
            the servants of her owner) and she is in our faces;’ and then he set the example,
            stripped and carried dust and hammered in piles all night, and by the morning she was
            surrounded by a dyke breast-high. The ‘long-shore’ men of <placeName ref="Boulak"
               >Boulak</placeName> were not a little surprised to see dignified Reises working for
            nothing like fellaheen. Meanwhile my three _Ma-allimeen_, the chief builder, caulker and
            foreman, had also stayed all night with Omar and my Reis, who worked like the rest, and
            the Sheykh of all the boat-builders went to visit one of my _Ma-allimeen_, who is his
            nephew, and hearing the case came down too at one in the morning and stayed till dawn.
            Then as the workmen passed, going to their respective jobs, he called them, and said,
            ‘Come and finish this boat; it must be done by to-morrow night.’ Some men who objected
            and said they were going to the Pasha’s dockyard, got a beating _pro forma_ and the end
            of it was that I found forty-six men under my boat working ‘like Afreets and Shaitans,’
            when I went to see how all was going in the morning. The old Sheykh marked out a piece
            to each four men, and then said, ‘If that is not done to-night, Oh dogs! to-morrow I’ll
            put on the hat’—_i.e._ ‘To-day I have beaten moderately, like an Arab, but to-morrow,
            please God, I’ll beat like a Frank, and be mad with the stick.’ _Kurz und gut_, the boat
            which yesterday morning was a skeleton, is now, at four p.m. to-day, finished, caulked,
            pitched and all capitally done; if the Nile carries off the dyke, she will float safe.
            The shore is covered with débris of other people’s half-finished boats I believe. I owe
            the ardour of the _Ma-allims_ and of the Sheykh of the builders to one of my absurd
            pieces of Arab civility. On the day when Omar killed poor Ablook, my black sheep, over
            the bows and ‘straked’ his blood upon them, the three _Ma-allimeen_ came on board this
            boat to eat their dish, and I followed the old Arab fashion and ate out of the wooden
            dish with them and the Reis ‘for luck,’ or rather ‘for a blessing’ as we say here; and
            it seems that this gave immense satisfaction. </p>
         <p> My Reis wept at the death of the black sheep, which used to follow him to the
            coffee-shop and the market, and ‘was to him as a son,’ he said, but he ate of him
            nevertheless. Omar surreptitiously picked out the best pieces for my dinner for three
            days, with his usual eye to economy; then lighted a fire of old wood, borrowed a
            cauldron of some darweeshes, cut up the sheep, added water and salt, onions and herbs,
            and boiled the sheep. Then the big washing copper (a large round flat tray, like a
            sponging bath) was filled with bread broken in pieces, over which the broth was slowly
            poured till the bread was soaked. Next came a layer of boiled rice, on the top of that
            the pieces of boiled meat, and over all was poured butter, vinegar and garlic boiled
            together. This is called a _Fettah_, and is the orthodox dish of darweeshes and given at
            all _Khatmehs_ and other semi-religious, semi-festive, semi-charitable festivities. It
            is excellent and not expensive. I asked how many had eaten and was told one hundred and
            thirty men had ‘blessed my hand.’ I expended 160 piastres on bread, butter and vinegar,
            etc. and the sheep was worth two napoleons; three napoleons in all, or less—for I ate
            for two days of the mutton. </p>
         <p> The three _Ma-allims_ came on board this boat, as I said and ate; and it was fine to
            hear us—how polite we were. ‘A bit more, oh _Ma-allim_?’ ‘Praise be to God, we have
            eaten well—we will return to our work’; ‘By the Prophet, coffee and a pipe.’ ‘Truly thou
            art of the most noble people.’ ‘Oh _Ma-allim_, ye have honoured us and rejoiced us,’
            ‘Verily this is a day white among days,’ etc. A very clever Egyptian engineer, a pupil
            of Whitworth’s, who is living in a boat alongside mine, was much amused, and said, ‘Ah
            you know how to manage ’em.’ </p>
         <p> I have learnt the story of the two dead bodies that hitched in my anchor-chain some
            time ago. They were not Europeans as I thought, but Circassians—a young man and his
            mother. The mother used to take him to visit an officer’s wife who had been brought up
            in the hareem of the Pasha’s mother. The husband caught them, killed them, tied them
            together and flung them into the Nile near Rhoda, and gave himself into the hands of the
            police. All was of course hushed up. He goes to Fazoghlou; and I don’t know what becomes
            of the slave-girl, his wife. These sort of things happen every day (as the bodies
            testify) among the Turks, but the Europeans never hear it. I heard it by a curious
            chance. </p>
         <p> _September_ 4.—My boat will soon be finished, and now will be as good as new. Omar has
            worked like a good one from daybreak till night, overlooking, buying all the materials,
            selling all the old wood and iron, etc., and has done capitally. I shall take a paper
            from my _Ma-allims_ who are all first class men, to certify what they have done and that
            the boat is as good as new. Goodah Effendi has kindly looked at her several times for me
            and highly approves the work done. I never saw men do a better day’s work than those at
            the boat. It is pretty to see the carpenter holding the wood with one hand and one foot
            while he saws it, sitting on the ground—just like the old frescoes. Do you remember the
            picture of boat-building in the tomb at Sakkara? Well, it is just the same; all done
            with the adze; but it is stout work they put into it, I can tell you. </p>
         <p> If you do not come (and I do not like to press you, I fear the fatigue for you and the
            return to the cold winter) I shall go to Luxor in a month or so and send back the boat
            to let. I have a neighbour now, Goodah Effendi, an engineer, who studied and married in
            England. His wife is gone there with the children, and he is living in a boat close by;
            so he comes over of an evening very often, and I am glad of his company: he is a right
            good fellow and very intelligent. </p>
         <p> My best love to all at home. I’ve got a log from the cedars of Lebanon, my Moslem
            carpenter who smoothed the broken end, swallowed the sawdust, because he believed ‘Our
            Lady Mary’ had sat under the tree with ‘Our Lord Jesus.’</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
