<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>January 8, 1865: Dowager Lady Duff Gordon, LUXOR, January 8, 1865.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAR OLD LADY, </p>
         <p> I received your kind letter in the midst of the drumming and piping and chanting and
            firing of guns and pistols and scampering of horses which constitute a religious
            festival in Egypt. The last day of the _moolid_ of Abu-l-Hajjaj fell on the 1st January
            so you came to wish me ‘May all the year be good to thee’ as the people here were civil
            enough to do when I told them it was the first day of the _Frankish_ year. (The
            _Christian_ year here begins in September.) </p>
         <p> I was very sorry to hear of poor Lady Theresa’s (Lady Theresa Lewis) death. I feel as
            if I had no right to survive people whom I left well and strong when I came away so ill.
            As usual the air of Upper Egypt has revived me again, but I am still weak and thin, and
            hear many lamentations at my altered looks. However, ‘_Inshallah_, thou wilt soon be
            better.’ </p>
         <p> Why don’t you make Alexander edit your letters from Spain? I am sure they would be far
            more amusing than mine can possibly be—for you _can_ write letters and I never could. I
            wish I had Miss Berry’s though I never did think her such a genius as most people, but
            her letters must be amusing from the time when they were written. Alexander will tell
            you how heavy the hand of Pharaoh is upon this poor people. ‘My father scourged you with
            whips but I will scourge you with scorpions,’ did not Rehoboam say so? or I forget which
            King of Judah. The distress here is frightful in all classes, and no man’s life is safe. </p>
         <p> Ali Bey Rheda told me the other day that Prince Arthur is coming here and that he was
            coming up with him after taking a Prince of Hohenzollern back to <placeName ref="Cairo"
               >Cairo</placeName>. There will be all the _fantasia_ possible for him here. Every man
            that has a horse will gallop him to pieces in honour of the son of the Queen of the
            English, and not a charge of powder will be spared. If you see Layard tell him that
            Mustapha A’gha had the whole Koran read for his benefit at the tomb of Abu-l-Hajjaj
            besides innumerable _fathahs_ which he said for him himself. He consulted me as to the
            propriety of sending Layard a backsheesh, but I declared that Layard was an Emeer of the
            Arabs and a giver, not a taker of backsheesh.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
