<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>April 9, 1863: To Mrs. Austin, CAIRO, April 9, 1863.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST MUTTER,</p>

         <p>I write to you because I know Janet is sure to write to Alick. I have had a very severe
            attack of bronchitis. As I seemed to be getting worse after Janet and Ross left for
            Alexandria, Omar very wisely sent for Hekekian Bey, who came at once bringing De Leo
            Bey, the surgeon-in-chief of the Pasha’s troops, and also the doctor to the hareem. He
            has been most kind, coming two and three times a day at first. He won’t take any fee,
            _sous prétexte_ that he is _officier du Pasha_; I must send him a present from England.
            As to Hekekian Bey, he is absolutely the Good Samaritan, and these Orientals do their
            kindnesses with such an air of enjoyment to themselves that it seems quite a favour to
            let them wait upon one. Hekekian comes in every day with his handsome old face and a
            budget of news, all the gossip of the Sultan and his doings. I shall always fancy the
            Good Samaritan in a tarboosh with a white beard and very long eyes. I am out of bed
            to-day for the second time, and waiting for a warm day to go out. Sally saw the
            illuminations last night; the Turkish bazaar she says was gorgeous. The Sultan and all
            his suite have not eaten bread here, all their food comes from Constantinople. To-morrow
            the Mahmaal goes—think of my missing that sight! _C’est désclant_.</p>

         <p>I have a black slave—a real one. I looked at her little ears wondering they had not been
            bored for rings. She fancied I wished them bored (she was sitting on the floor close at
            my side), and in a minute she stood up and showed me her ear with a great pin through
            it: ‘Is that well, lady?’ the creature is eight years old. The shock nearly made me
            faint. What extremities of terror had reduced that little mind to such a state. She is
            very good and gentle, and sews quite nicely already. When she first came, she tells me,
            she thought I should eat her; now her one dread is that I should leave her behind. She
            sings a wild song of joy to Maurice’s picture and about the little Sitt. She was sent
            from Khartoum as a present to Mr. Thayer, who has no woman-servant at all. He fetched me
            to look at her, and when I saw the terror-stricken creature being coarsely pulled about
            by his cook and groom, I said I would take her for the present. Sally teaches her, and
            she is very good; but now she has set her whole little black soul upon me. De Leo can
            give no opinion as to what I ought to do, as he knows little but Egypt, and thinks
            England rather like Norway, I fancy. Only don’t let me be put in a dreadful mountain
            valley; I hear the drip, drip, drip of Eaux Bonnes in bad dreams still, when I am chilly
            and oppressed in my sleep. I’ll write again soon, send this to Alick, please.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
