<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>March 7, 1864: To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, LUXOR, March 7, 1864.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK, </p>
         <p> The real hot weather (speaking after the manner of the English) has begun, and the fine
            sun and clear air are delicious and reviving. My cough fades away, and my strength
            increases slowly. One can no longer go out in the middle of the day, and I mount my
            donkey early and late, with little Achmet trotting beside me. In the evenings comes my
            dear Sheykh Yussuf, and I blunder through an hour’s dictation, and reading of the story
            of the Barber’s fifth brother (he with the basket of glass). I presume that Yussuf likes
            me too, for I am constantly greeted with immense cordiality by graceful men in green
            turbans, belonging, like him, to the holy family of Sheykh Abu-’l-Hajjaj. They inquire
            tenderly after my health, and pray for me, and hope I am going to stay among them. </p>
         <p> You would be much struck here with the resemblance to Spain, I think. ‘Cosas de España’
            is exactly the ‘_Shogl-el-Arab_,’ and Don Fulano is the Arabic word _foolan_ (such a
            one), as _Ojala_ is _Inshallah_ (please God). The music and dancing here, too, are
            Spanish, only ‘more so’ and much more. </p>
         <p> _March_ 10, 1864.—Yesterday was Bairam, and on Tuesday evening everybody who possessed
            a gun or a pistol banged away, every drum and taraboukeh was thumped, and all the
            children holloaed, _Ramadan Māt_, _Ramadan Māt_ (Ramadan’s dead) about the streets. At
            daybreak Omar went to the early prayer, a special ceremony of the day. There were crowds
            of people, so, as it was useless to pray and preach in the mosque, Sheykh Yussuf went
            out upon a hillock in the burying-ground, where they all prayed and he preached. Omar
            reported the sermon to me, as follows (it is all extempore): First Yussuf pointed to the
            graves, ‘Where are all those people?’ and to the ancient temples, ‘Where are those who
            built them? Do not strangers from a far country take away their very corpses to wonder
            at? What did their splendour avail them? etc., etc. What then, O Muslims, _will_ avail
            that you may be happy when that comes which will come for all? Truly God is just and
            will defraud no man, and He will reward you if you do what is right; and that is, to
            wrong no man, neither in person, nor in his family, nor in his possessions. _Cease then
            to cheat one another, O men_, and to be greedy, and do not think that you can make
            amends by afterwards giving alms, or praying, or fasting, or giving gifts to the
            servants of the mosque. _Benefits come from God; it is enough for you if you do no
            injury to any man, and above all to any woman or little one_.’ Of course it was much
            longer, but this was the substance, Omar tells me, and pretty sound morality too,
            methinks, and might be preached with advantage to a meeting of philanthropists in Exeter
            Hall. There is no predestination in _Islam_, and every man will be judged upon his
            actions. ‘Even unbelievers God will not defraud,’ says the Koran. Of course, a belief in
            meritorious works leads to the same sort of superstition as among Catholics, the
            endeavour to ‘make one’s soul’ by alms, fastings, endowments, etc.; therefore Yussuf’s
            stress upon doing no evil seems to me very remarkable, and really profound. After the
            sermon, all the company assembled rushed on him to kiss his head, and his hands and his
            feet, and mobbed him so fearfully that he had to lay about him with the wooden sword
            which is carried by the officiating Alim. He came to wish me the customary good wishes
            soon after, and looked very hot and tumbled, and laughed heartily about the awful
            kissing he had undergone. All the men embrace on meeting on the festival of Bairam. </p>
         <p> The kitchen is full of cakes (ring-shaped) which my friends have sent me, just such as
            we see offered to the gods in the temples and tombs. I went to call on the Maōhn in the
            evening, and found a lot of people all dressed in their best. Half were Copts, among
            them a very pleasing young priest who carried on a religious discussion with Seleem
            Effendi, strange to say, with perfect good-humour on both sides. A Copt came up with his
            farm labourer, who had been beaten and the field robbed. The Copt stated the case in ten
            words, and the Maōhn sent off his cavass with him to apprehend the accused persons, who
            were to be tried at sunrise and beaten, if found guilty, and forced to make good the
            damage. General Hay called yesterday—a fine old, blue-eyed soldier. He found a lot of
            Fellaheen sitting with me, enjoying coffee and pipes hugely, and they were much
            gratified at our pressing them not to move or disturb themselves, when they all started
            up in dismay at the entrance of such a grand-looking Englishman and got off the carpet.
            So we told them that in our country the business of a farmer was looked upon as very
            respectable, and that the General would ask his farmers to sit and drink wine with him.
            ‘_Mashallah, taib kateer_’ (It is the will of God, and most excellent), said old Omar,
            my fellah friend, and kissed his hand to General Hay quite affectionately. We English
            are certainly liked here. Seleem said yesterday evening that he had often had to do
            business with them, and found them always _doghri_ (straight), men of one word and of no
            circumlocutions, ‘and so unlike all the other Europeans, and especially the French!’ The
            fact is that few but decent English come here, I fancy our scamps go to the colonies,
            whereas Egypt is the sink for all the iniquity of the South of Europe. </p>
         <p> A worthy Copt here, one Todorus, took ‘a piece of paper’ for £20 for antiquities sold
            to an Englishman, and after the Englishman was gone, brought it to me to ask what sort
            of paper it was, and how he could get it changed, or was he, perhaps, to keep it till
            the gentleman sent him the money? It was a circular note, which I had difficulty in
            explaining, but I offered to send it to <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> to
            Brigg’s and get it cashed; as to when he would get the money I could not say, as they
            must wait for a safe hand to send gold by. I told him to put his name on the back of the
            note, and Todorus thought I wanted it _as a receipt_ for the money which was yet to
            come, and was going cheerfully to write me a receipt for the £20 he was entrusting to
            me. Now a Copt is not at all green where his pocket is concerned, but they will take
            anything from the English. I do hope no swindler will find it out. Mr. Close told me
            that when his boat sank in the Cataract, and he remained half dressed on the rock,
            without a farthing, four men came and offered to lend him anything. While I was in
            England last year an Englishman to whom Omar acted as _laquais de place_ went away owing
            him £7 for things bought. Omar had money enough to pay all the tradespeople, and kept it
            secret for fear any of the other Europeans should say, ‘Shame for the English’ and did
            not even tell his family. Luckily, the man sent the money by the next mail from Malta,
            and the Sheykh of the dragomans proclaimed it, and so Omar got it; but he would never
            have mentioned it else. This ‘concealing of evil’ is considered very meritorious, and
            where women are concerned positively a religious duty. _Le scandale est ce qui fait
            l’offense_ is very much the notion in Egypt, and I believe that very forgiving husbands
            are commoner here than elsewhere. The whole idea is founded on the verse of the Koran,
            incessantly quoted, ‘The woman is made for the man, but the man is made for the woman’;
            _ergo_, the obligations to chastity are equal; _ergo_, as the men find it difficult,
            they argue that the women do the same. I have never heard a woman’s misconduct spoken of
            without a hundred excuses; perhaps her husband had slave girls, perhaps he was old or
            sick, or she didn’t like him, or she couldn’t help it. Violent love comes ‘by the
            visitation of God,’ as our juries say; the man or woman must satisfy it or die. A poor
            young fellow is now in the muristan (the madhouse) of <placeName ref="Cairo"
               >Cairo</placeName> owing to the beauty and sweet tongue of an English lady whose
            servant he was. How could he help it? God sent the calamity. </p>
         <p> I often hear of Lady Ellenborough, who is married to the Sheykh-el-Arab of Palmyra, and
            lives at Damascus. The Arabs think it inhuman of English ladies to avoid her. Perhaps
            she has repented; at all events, she is married and lives with her husband. I asked Omar
            if he would tell his brother if he saw his wife do anything wrong. (N.B.—He can’t endure
            her.) ‘Certainly not, I must cover her with my cloak.’ I am told, also, that among the
            Arabs of the desert (the _real_ Arabs), when a traveller, tired and wayworn, seeks their
            tents, it is the duty of his host, generally the Sheykh, to send him into the hareem,
            and leave him there three days, with full permission to do as he will after the women
            have bathed, and rubbed, and refreshed him. But then he must never speak of that Hareem;
            they are to him as his own, to be reverenced. If he spoke, the husband would kill him;
            but the Arab would never do it for a European, ‘because all Europeans are so hard upon
            women,’ and do not fear God and conceal their offences. If a dancing-girl repents, the
            most respectable man may and does marry her, and no one blames or laughs at him. I
            believe all this leads to a good deal of irregularity, but certainly the feeling is
            amiable. It is impossible to conceive how startling it is to a Christian to hear the
            rules of morality applied with perfect impartiality to both sexes, and to hear Arabs who
            know our manners talk of the English being ‘jealous’ and ‘hard upon their women.’ Any
            unchastity is wrong and _haram_ (unlawful), but equally so in men and women. Seleem
            Effendi talked in this strain, and seemed to incline to greater indulgence to women on
            the score of their ignorance and weakness. Remember, I only speak of Arabs. I believe
            the Turkish ideas are different, as is their whole hareem system, and Egypt is not the
            rule for all Muslims. </p>
         <p> _Saturday_, 12_th_.—I dined last night with Mustapha, who again had the dancing-girls
            for some Englishmen to see. Seleem Effendi got the doctor, who was of the party, to
            prescribe for him, and asked me to translate to him all about his old stomach as coolly
            as possible. He, as usual, sat by me on the divan, and during the pause in the dancing
            called ‘el Maghribeeyeh,’ the best dancer, to come and talk. She kissed my hand, sat on
            her heels before us, and at once laid aside the professional _galliardise_ of manner,
            and talked very nicely in very good Arabic and with perfect propriety, more like a man
            than a woman; she seemed very intelligent. What a thing we should think it for a
            worshipful magistrate to call up a girl of that character to talk to a lady! </p>
         <p> Yesterday we had a strange and unpleasant day’s business. The evening before I had my
            pocket picked in Karnac by two men who hung about me, one to sell a bird, the other one
            of the regular ‘loafers’ who hang about the ruins to beg, and sell water or curiosities,
            and who are all a lazy, bad lot, of course. I went to Seleem, who wrote at once to the
            Sheykh-el-Beled of Karnac to say that we should go over next morning at eight o’clock to
            investigate the affair, and to desire him to apprehend the men. Next morning Seleem
            fetched me, and Mustapha came to represent English interests, and as we rode out of
            Luxor the Sheykh-el-Ababdeh joined us, with four of his tribe with their long guns, and
            a lot more with lances. He was a volunteer, and furious at the idea of a lady and a
            stranger being robbed. It is the first time it has happened here, and the desire to beat
            was so strong that I went to act as counsel for the prisoner. Everyone was peculiarly
            savage that it should have happened to me, a person well known to be so friendly to _el
            Muslimeen_. When we arrived we went into a square enclosure, with a sort of cloister on
            one side, spread with carpets where we sat, and the wretched fellows were brought in
            chains. To my horror, I found they had been beaten already. I remonstrated, ‘What if you
            had beaten the wrong men?’ ‘_Maleysh_! (Never mind!) we will beat the whole village
            until your purse is found.’ I said to Mustapha, ‘This won’t do; you must stop this.’ So
            Mustapha ordained, with the concurrence of the Maōhn, that the Sheykh-el-Beled and the
            _gefiyeh_ (the keeper of the ruins) should pay me the value of the purse. As the people
            of Karnac are very troublesome in begging and worrying, I thought this would be a good
            lesson to the said Sheykh to keep better order, and I consented to receive the money,
            promising to return it and to give a napoleon over if the purse comes back with its
            contents (3½ napoleons). The Sheykh-el-Ababdeh harangued the people on their
            ill-behaviour to Hareemát, called them _harámee_ (rascals), and was very high and mighty
            to the Sheykh-el-Beled. Hereupon I went away to visit a Turkish lady in the village,
            leaving Mustapha to settle. After I was gone they beat eight or ten of the boys who had
            mobbed me, and begged with the two men. Mustapha, who does not like the stick, stayed to
            see that they were not hurt, and so far it will be a good lesson to them. He also had
            the two men sent over to the prison here, for fear the Sheykh-el-Beled should beat them
            again, and will keep them here for a time. So far so good, but my fear now is that
            innocent people will be squeezed to make up the money, if the men do not give up the
            purse. I have told Sheykh Yussuf to keep watch how things go, and if the men persist in
            the theft and don’t return the purse, I shall give the money to those whom the
            Sheykh-el-Beled will assuredly squeeze, or else to the mosque of Karnac. I cannot pocket
            it, though I thought it quite right to exact the fine as a warning to the Karnac
            _mauvais sujets_. As we went home the Sheykh-el-Ababdeh (such a fine fellow he looks)
            came up and rode beside me, and said, ‘I know you are a person of kindness; do not tell
            this story in this country. If Effendina (Ismail Pasha) comes to hear, he may “take a
            broom and sweep away the village.”’ I exclaimed in horror, and Mustapha joined at once
            in the request, and said, ‘Do not tell anyone in Egypt. The Sheykh-el-Ababdeh is quite
            true; it might cost many lives.’ The whole thing distressed me horribly. If I had not
            been there they would have beaten right and left, and if I had shown any desire to have
            anyone punished, evidently they would have half killed the two men. Mustapha behaved
            extremely well. He showed sense, decision, and more feelings of humanity than I at all
            expected of him. Pray do as I begged you, try to get him paid. Some of the Consuls in
               <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> are barely civil, and old Mustapha has all
            the bother and work of the whole of the Nile boats (eighty-five this winter), and he is
            boundlessly kind and useful to the English, and a real protection against cheating,
            etc.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
