<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>October 31, 1863: To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, KAFR ZEYAT, October 31,
               1863.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK,</p>

         <p>We left Alexandria on Thursday about noon, and sailed with a fair wind along the
            Mahmoudieh Canal. My little boat flies like a bird, and my men are a capital set of
            fellows, bold and careful sailors. I have only seven in all, but they work well, and at
            a pinch Omar leaves the pots and pans and handles a rope or a pole manfully. We sailed
            all night and passed the locks at Atleh at four o’clock yesterday, and were greeted by
            old Nile tearing down like a torrent. The river is magnificent, ‘seven men’s height,’ my
            Reis says, above its usual pitch; it has gone down five or six feet and left a sad scene
            of havoc on either side. However what the Nile takes he repays with threefold interest,
            they say. The women are at work rebuilding their mud huts, and the men repairing the
            dykes. A Frenchman told me he was on board a Pasha’s steamer under M. de Lesseps’
            command, and they passed a flooded village where two hundred or so people stood on their
            roofs crying for help. Would you, could you, believe it that they passed on and left
            them to drown? None but an eyewitness could have made me believe such villainy.</p>

         <p>All to-day we sailed in such heavenly weather—a sky like nothing but its most beautiful
            self. At the bend of the river just now we had a grand struggle to get round, and got
            entangled with a big timber boat. My crew got so vehement that I had to come out with an
            imperious request to everyone to bless the Prophet. Then the boat nearly pulled the men
            into the stream, and they pulled and hauled and struggled up to their waists in mud and
            water, and Omar brandished his pole and shouted ‘Islam el Islam!’ which gave a fresh
            spirit to the poor fellows, and round we came with a dash and caught the breeze again.
            Now we have put up for the night, and shall pass the railway-bridge to-morrow. The
            railway is all under water from here up to Tantah—eight miles—and in many places higher
            up.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
