<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>February 19, 1864: To Mrs. Austin, LUXOR, February 19, 1864.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST MUTTER, </p>
         <p> I have only time for a few lines to go down by Mr. Strutt and Heathcote’s boat to
               <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>. They are very good specimens and quite
            recognised as ‘belonging to the higher people,’ because they ‘do not make themselves
            big.’ I received your letter of January 21 with little darling Rainie’s three days ago. </p>
         <p> I am better now that the weather is fine again. We had a whole day’s rain (which
            Herodotus says is a portent here) and a hurricane from the south worthy of the Cape. I
            thought we should have been buried under the drifting sand. To-day is again heavenly. I
            saw Abd-el-Azeez, the chemist in <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>; he seemed a
            very good fellow, and was a pupil of my old friend M. Chrevreul, and highly recommended
            by him. Here I am out of all European ideas. The Sheykh-el-Arab (of the Ababdeh tribe),
            who has a sort of town house here, has invited me out into the desert to the black
            tents, and I intend to pay a visit with old Mustapha A’gha. There is a Roman well in his
            yard with a ghoul in it. I can’t get the story from Mustapha, who is ashamed of such
            superstitions, but I’ll find it out. We had a fantasia at Mustapha’s for young Strutt
            and Co., and a very good dancing-girl. Some dear old prosy English people made me laugh
            so. The lady wondered how the women here could wear clothes ‘so different from English
            females—poor things!’ but they were not _malveillants_, only pitying and
            wonderstruck—nothing astonished them so much as my salutations with Seleem Effendi, the
            Maōhn. </p>
         <p> I begin to feel the time before me to be away from you all very long indeed, but I do
            think my best chance is a long spell of real heat. I have got through this winter
            without once catching cold at all to signify, and now the fine weather is come. I am
            writing in Arabic from Sheykh Yussuf’s dictation the dear old story of the barber’s
            brother with the basket of glass. The Arabs are so diverted at hearing that we all know
            the _Alf Leyleh o Leyleh_, the ‘Thousand Nights and a Night.’ The want of a dictionary
            with a teacher knowing no word of English is terrible. I don’t know how I learn at all.
            The post is pretty quick up to here. I got your letter within three weeks, you see, but
            I get no newspapers; the post is all on foot and can’t carry anything so heavy. One of
            my men of last year, Asgalani the steersman, has just been to see me; he says his
            journey was happier last year. </p>
         <p> I hear that Phillips is coming to <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>, and have
            written to him there to invite him up here to paint these handsome Saeedees. He could
            get up in a steamer as I did through Hassaneyn Effendi for a trifle. I wish you _could_
            come, but the heat here which gives me life would be quite _impossible_ to you. The
            thermometer in the cold antechamber now is 67° where no sun ever comes, and the blaze of
            the sun is prodigious.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
