<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>February 11, 1863: To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, THEBES, February 11,
               1863.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK,</p>

         <p>On arriving here last night I found one letter from you, dated December 10, and have
            received nothing else. Pray write again forthwith to <placeName ref="Cairo"
               >Cairo</placeName> where I hope to stay some weeks. A clever old dragoman I met at
            Philæ offers to lend me furniture for a lodging or a tent for the desert, and when I
            hesitated he said he was very well off and it was not his business to sell things, but
            only to be paid for his services by rich people, and that if I did not accept it as he
            meant it he should be quite hurt. This is what I have met with from everything
            Arab—nothing but kindness and politeness. I shall say farewell to Egypt with real
            feeling; among other things, it will be quite a pang to part with Omar who has been my
            shadow all this time and for whom I have quite an affection, he is so thoroughly good
            and amiable.</p>

         <p>I am really much better I hope and believe, though only within the last week or two. We
            have had the coldest winter ever known in Nubia, such bitter north-east winds, but when
            the wind by great favour did not blow, the weather was heavenly. If the millennium
            really does come I shall take a good bit of mine on the Nile. At Assouan I had been
            strolling about in that most poetically melancholy spot, the granite quarry of old Egypt
            and burial-place of Muslim martyrs, and as I came homewards along the bank a party of
            slave merchants, who had just loaded their goods for Senaar from the boat on the camels,
            asked me to dinner, and, oh! how delicious it felt to sit on a mat among the camels and
            strange bales of goods and eat the hot tough bread, sour milk and dates, offered with
            such stately courtesy. We got quite intimate over our leather cup of sherbet (brown
            sugar and water), and the handsome jet-black men, with features as beautiful as those of
            the young Bacchus, described the distant lands in a way which would have charmed
            Herodotus. They proposed to me to join them, ‘they had food enough,’ and Omar and I were
            equally inclined to go. It is of no use to talk of the ruins; everybody has said, I
            suppose, all that can be said, but Philæ surpassed my expectations. No wonder the Arab
            legends of Ans el Wogood are so romantic, and Abou Simbel and many more. The scribbling
            of names is quite infamous, beautiful paintings are defaced by Tomkins and Hobson, but
            worst of all Prince Pückler Muskau has engraved his and his _Ordenskreuz_ in huge
            letters on the naked breast of that august and pathetic giant who sits at Abou Simbel. I
            wish someone would kick him for his profanity.</p>

         <p>I have eaten many odd things with odd people in queer places, dined in a respectable
            Nubian family (the castor-oil was trying), been to a Nubian wedding—such a dance I saw.
            Made friends with a man much looked up to in his place (Kalabshee—notorious for cutting
            throats), inasmuch as he had killed several intrusive tax-gatherers and recruiting
            officers. He was very gentlemanly and kind and carried me up a place so steep I could
            not have reached it. Just below the cataract—by-the-by going up is nothing but noise and
            shouting, but coming down is fine fun—_Fantasia khateer_ as my excellent little Nubian
            pilot said. My sailors all prayed away manfully and were horribly frightened. I confess
            my pulse quickened, but I don’t think it was fear. Well, below the cataract I stopped
            for a religious fête, and went to a holy tomb with the darweesh, so extraordinarily
            handsome and graceful—the true _feingemacht_ noble Bedaween type. He took care of me
            through the crowd, who never had seen a Frank woman before and crowded fearfully, and
            pushed the true believers unmercifully to make way for me. He was particularly pleased
            at my not being afraid of Arabs; I laughed, and asked if he was afraid of us. ‘Oh no! he
            would like to come to England; when there he would work to eat and drink, and then sit
            and sleep in the church.’ I was positively ashamed to tell my religious friend that with
            us the ‘house of God’ is not the house of the poor stranger. I asked him to eat with me
            but he was holding a preliminary Ramadan (it begins next week), and could not; but he
            brought his handsome sister, who was richly dressed, and begged me to visit him and eat
            of his bread, cheese and milk. Such is the treatment one finds if one leaves the
            highroad and the backsheesh-hunting parasites. There are plenty of ‘gentlemen’
            barefooted and clad in a shirt and cloak ready to pay attentions which you may return
            with a civil look and greeting, and if you offer a cup of coffee and a seat on the floor
            you give great pleasure, still more if you eat the dourah and dates, or bread and sour
            milk with an appetite.</p>

         <p>At Koom Ombo we met a Rifaee darweesh with his basket of tame snakes. After a little
            talk he proposed to initiate me, and so we sat down and held hands like people marrying.
            Omar sat behind me and repeated the words as my ‘Wakeel,’ then the Rifaee twisted a
            cobra round our joined hands and requested me to spit on it, he did the same and I was
            pronounced safe and enveloped in snakes. My sailors groaned and Omar shuddered as the
            snakes put out their tongues—the darweesh and I smiled at each other like Roman augurs.
            I need not say the creatures were toothless.</p>

         <p>It is worth going to Nubia to see the girls. Up to twelve or thirteen they are neatly
            dressed in a bead necklace and a leather fringe 4 inches wide round the loins, and
            anything so absolutely perfect as their shapes or so sweetly innocent as their look
            can’t be conceived. My pilot’s little girl came in the dress mentioned before carrying a
            present of cooked fish on her head and some fresh eggs; she was four years old and so
            _klug_. I gave her a captain’s biscuit and some figs, and the little pet sat with her
            little legs tucked under her, and ate it so _manierlich_ and was so long over it, and
            wrapped up some more white biscuit to take home in a little rag of a veil so carefully.
            I longed to steal her, she was such a darling. Two beautiful young Nubian women visited
            me in my boat, with hair in little plaits finished off with lumps of yellow clay
            burnished like golden tags, soft, deep bronze skins, and lips and eyes fit for Isis and
            Hathor. Their very dress and ornaments were the same as those represented in the tombs,
            and I felt inclined to ask them how many thousand years old they were. In their house I
            sat on an ancient Egyptian couch with the semicircular head-rest, and drank out of
            crockery which looked antique, and they brought a present of dates in a basket such as
            you may see in the British Museum. They are dressed in drapery like Greek statues, and
            are as perfect, but have hard, bold faces, and, though far handsomer, lack the charm of
            the Arab women; and the men, except at Kalabshee and those from far up the country, are
            not such gentlemen as the Arabs.</p>

         <p> Everyone is cursing the French here. Forty thousand men always at work at the Suez
            Canal at starvation-point, does not endear them to the Arabs. There is great excitement
            as to what the new Pasha will do. If he ceases to give forced labour, the Canal, I
            suppose, must be given up. Well, I must leave off and send my letter to Mustapha Aga to
            forward. I shall stay here ten days or so, and then return slowly to <placeName
               ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> on March 10, the last day of Ramadan. I will stay a
            short time at <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>, and then take a small boat and
            drop down to Alexandria and see Janet. How I did wish for my darling Rainie to play with
            Achmet in the boat and see the pretty Nubian boys and girls. I have seen and heard so
            much, that like M. de Conti _je voudrais être levé pour l’aller dire_. I long to bore
            you with traveller’s tales. Pray write soon.</p>

         <p>Omar wanted to hear all that ‘the gentleman’ said about ‘weled and bint’ (boy and girl),
            and was quite delighted to hear of Maurice’s good report at school, he thinks that the
            ‘Abou el welàd’ (father of the children—you, to wit) will send a sheep to the ‘fikee’
            who teaches him. I have learned a new code of propriety altogether—_célà a du bon et du
            mauvais_, like ours. When I said ‘my husband’ Omar blushed and gently corrected me; when
            my donkey fell in the streets he cried with vexation, and on my mentioning the fall to
            Hekekian Bey he was quite indignant. ‘Why you say it, ma’am? that shame’—a _faux pas_ in
            fact. On the other hand they mention all that belongs to the production of children with
            perfect satisfaction and pleasure. A very pleasing, modest and handsome Nubian young
            woman, wishing to give me the best present she could think of, brought me a mat of her
            own making, and which had been her marriage-bed. It was a gift both friendly and
            honourable, and I treasure it accordingly. Omar gave me a description of his own
            marriage, appealing to my sympathy about the distress of absence from his wife. I
            intimated that English people were not accustomed to some words and might be shocked, on
            which he said, ‘Of course I not speak of my Hareem to English gentleman, but to good
            Lady can speak it.’</p>

         <p>Good-bye, dear Alick, no, that is improper: I must say ‘O my Lord’ or ‘Abou
            Maurice.’</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
