<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>March 7, 1863: To Mrs. Austin, A FEW MILES BELOW GIRGEH, March 7, 1863.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST MUTTER,</p>

         <p>I was so glad to find from your letter (which Janet sent me to Thebes by a steamer) that
            mine from Siout had reached you safely. First and foremost I am wonderfully better. In
               <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> the winter has been terribly cold and damp,
            as the Coptic priest told me yesterday at Girgeh. So I don’t repent the expense of the
            boat for _j’en ai pour mon argent_—I am _all_ the money better and really think of
            getting well. Now that I know the ways of this country a little, which Herodotus truly
            says is like no other, I see that I might have gone and lived at Thebes or at Keneh or
            Assouan on next to nothing, but then how could I know it? The English have raised a
            mirage of false wants and extravagance which the servants of the country of course, some
            from interest and others from mere ignorance, do their best to keep up. As soon as I had
            succeeded in really persuading Omar that I was not as rich as a Pasha and had no wish to
            be thought so, he immediately turned over a new leaf as to what must be had and said
            ‘Oh, if I could have thought an English lady would have eaten and lived and done the
            least like Arab people, I might have hired a house at Keneh for you, and we might have
            gone up in a clean passenger boat, but I thought no English could bear it.’ At
               <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>, where we shall be, Inshallaha, on the 19th,
            Omar will get a lodging and borrow a few mattresses and a table and chair and, as he
            says, ‘keep the money in our pockets instead of giving it to the hotel.’ I hope Alick
            got my letter from Thebes, and that he told you that I had dined with ‘the blameless
            Ethiopians.’ I have seen all the temples in Nubia and down as far as I have come, and
            nine of the tombs at Thebes. Some are wonderfully beautiful—Abou Simbel, Kalabshee, Room
            Ombo—a little temple at El Kab, lovely—three tombs at Thebes and most of all Abydos;
            Edfou and Dendera are the most perfect, Edfou quite perfect, but far less beautiful. But
            the most lovely object my eyes ever saw is the island of Philæ. It gives one quite the
            supernatural feeling of Claude’s best landscapes, only not the least like them—_ganz
            anders_. The Arabs say that Ans el Wogood, the most beautiful of men, built it for his
            most beautiful beloved, and there they lived in perfect beauty and happiness all alone.
            If the weather had not been so cold while I was there I should have lived in the temple,
            in a chamber sculptured with the mystery of Osiris’ burial and resurrection. Omar
            cleaned it out and meant to move my things there for a few days, but it was too cold to
            sleep in a room without a door. The winds have been extraordinarily cold this year, and
            are so still. We have had very little of the fine warm weather, and really been pinched
            with cold most of the time. On the shore away from the river would be much better for
            invalids.</p>

         <p>Mustapha Aga, the consular agent at Thebes, has offered me a house of his, up among the
            tombs in the finest air, if ever I want it. He was very kind and hospitable indeed to
            all the English there. I went into his hareem, and liked his wife’s manners very much.
            It was charming to see that she henpecked her handsome old husband completely. They had
            fine children and his boy, about thirteen or so, rode and played Jereed one day when
            Abdallah Pasha had ordered the people of the neighbourhood to do it for General Parker.
            I never saw so beautiful a performance. The old General and I were quite excited, and he
            tried it to the great amusement of the Sheykh el Beled. Some young Englishmen were
            rather grand about it, but declined mounting the horses and trying a throw. The Sheykh
            and young Hassan and then old Mustapha wheeled round and round like beautiful hawks, and
            caught the palm-sticks thrown at them as they dashed round. It was superb, and the
            horses were good, though the saddles and bridles were rags and ends of rope, and the men
            mere tatterdemalions. A little below Thebes I stopped, and walked inland to Koos to see
            a noble old mosque falling to ruin. No English had ever been there and we were
            surrounded by a crowd in the bazaar. Instantly five or six tall fellows with long sticks
            improvised themselves our body-guard and kept the people off, who _du reste_ were
            perfectly civil and only curious to see such strange ‘Hareem,’ and after seeing us well
            out of the town evaporated as quietly as they came without a word. I gave about
            ten-pence to buy oil, as it is Ramadan and the mosque ought to be lighted, and the old
            servant of the mosque kindly promised me full justice at the Day of Judgment, as I was
            one of those Nasranee of whom the Lord Mohammed said that they are not proud and wish
            well to the Muslimeen. The Pasha had confiscated all the lands belonging to the mosque,
            and allowed 300 piastres—not £2 a month—for all expenses; of course the noble old
            building with its beautiful carving and arabesque mouldings must fall down. There was a
            smaller one beside it, where he declared that anciently forty girls lived unmarried and
            recited the Koran—Muslim nuns, in fact. I intend to ask the Alim, for whom I have a
            letter from Mustapha, about such an anomaly.</p>

         <p>Some way above Bellianeh Omar asked eagerly leave to stop the boat as a great Sheyk had
            called to us, and we should inevitably have some disaster if we disobeyed. So we stopped
            and Omar said, ‘come and see the Sheyk, ma’am.’ I walked off and presently found about
            thirty people, including all my own men, sitting on the ground round St. Simon
            Stylites—without the column. A hideous old man like Polyphemus, utterly naked, with the
            skin of a rhinoceros all cracked with the weather, sat there, and had sat day and night,
            summer and winter, motionless for twenty years. He never prays, he never washes, he does
            not keep Ramadan, and yet he is a saint. Of course I expected a good hearty curse from
            such a man, but he was delighted with my visit, asked me to sit down, ordered his
            servant to bring me sugar-cane, asked my name and tried to repeat it over and over
            again, and was quite talkative and full of jokes and compliments, and took no notice of
            anyone else. Omar and my crew smiled and nodded, and all congratulated me heartily. Such
            a distinction proves my own excellence (as the Sheyk knows all people’s thoughts), and
            is sure to be followed by good fortune. Finally Omar proposed to say the Fathah in which
            all joined except the Sheykh, who looked rather bored by the interruption, and desired
            us not to go so soon, unless I were in a hurry. A party of Bedaween came up on camels
            with presents for the holy man, but he took no notice of them, and went on questioning
            Omar about me, and answering my questions. What struck me was the total absence of any
            sanctimonious air about the old fellow, he was quite worldly and jocose; I suppose he
            knew that his position was secure, and thought his dirt and nakedness proved his
            holiness enough. Omar then recited the Fathah again, and we rose and gave the servants a
            few foddahs—the saint takes no notice of this part of the proceeding—but he asked me to
            send him twice my hand full of rice for his dinner, an honour so great that there was a
            murmur of congratulation through the whole assembly. I asked Omar how a man could be a
            saint who neglected all the duties of a Muslim, and I found that he fully believed that
            Sheykh Seleem could be in two places at once, that while he sits there on the shore he
            is also at Mecca, performing every sacred function and dressed all in green. ‘Many
            people have seen him there, ma’am, quite true.’</p>

         <p>From Bellianeh we rode on pack-donkeys without bridles to Abydos, six miles through the
            most beautiful crops ever seen. The absence of weeds and blight is wonderful, and the
            green of Egypt, where it is green, would make English green look black. Beautiful
            cattle, sheep and camels were eating the delicious clover, while their owners camped
            there in reed huts during the time the crops are growing. Such a lovely scene, all
            sweetness and plenty. We ate our bread and dates in Osiris’ temple, and a woman offered
            us buffalo milk on our way home, which we drank warm out of the huge earthen pan it had
            been milked in. At Girgeh I found my former friend Mishregi absent, but his servants
            told some of his friends of my arrival, and about seven or eight big black turbans soon
            gathered in the boat. A darling little Coptic boy came with his father and wanted a
            ‘_kitaab_’ (book) to write in, so I made one with paper and the cover of my old
            pocket-book, and gave him a pencil. I also bethought me of showing him ‘pickys’ in a
            book, which was so glorious a novelty that he wanted to go with me to my town, ‘Beled
            Ingleez,’ where more such books were to be found.</p>

         <p>SIOUT, _March_ 9.</p>

         <p>I found here letters from Alick, telling me of dear Lord Lansdowne’s death. Of course I
            know that his time was come, but the thought that I shall never see his face again, that
            all that kindness and affection is gone out of my life, is a great blow. No friend could
            leave such a blank to me as that old and faithful one, though the death of younger ones
            might be more tragic; but so many things seem gone with him into the grave. Many indeed
            will mourn that kind, wise, steadfast man—_Antiqua fides_. No one nowadays will be so
            noble with such unconsciousness and simplicity. I have bought two Coptic turbans to make
            a black dress out of. I thought I should like to wear it for him—here, where
            ‘compliment’ is out of the question.</p>

         <p>I also found a letter from Janet, who has been very ill; the account was so bad that I
            have telegraphed to hear how she is, and shall go at once to Alexandria if she is not
            better. If she is I shall hold to my plan and see Beni Hassan and the Pyramids on my way
            to <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>. I found my kind friend the Copt Wassef
            kinder than ever. He went off to telegraph to Alexandria for me, and showed so much
            feeling and real kindness that I was quite touched.</p>

         <p>I was grieved to hear that you had been ill again, dearest Mutter. The best is that I
            feel so much better that I think I may come home again without fear; I still have an
            irritable cough, but it has begun to have lucid intervals, and is far less frequent. I
            can walk four or five miles and my appetite is good. All this in spite of really cold
            weather in a boat where nothing shuts within two fingers’ breadths. I long to be again
            with my own people.</p>

         <p>Please send this to Alick, to whom I will write again from <placeName ref="Cairo"
               >Cairo</placeName>.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
