<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>November 3, 1867: Mrs. Ross, BOULAK, November 3, 1867.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST JANET, </p>
         <p> Maurice arrived on Friday week, and is as happy as can be, he says he never felt so
            well and never had such good snipe shooting. Little Darfour’s amusement at Maurice is
            boundless; he grins at him all the time he waits at table, he marvels at his dirty
            boots, at his bathing, at his much walking out shooting, at his knowing no Arabic. The
            dyke burst the other day up at Bahr Yussuf, and we were nearly all swept away by the
            furious rush of water. My little boat was upset while three men in her were securing the
            anchor, and two of them were nearly drowned, though they swim like fish; all the
            dahabiehs were rattled and pounded awfully; and in the middle of the _fracas_, at
            noonday, a steamer ran into us quite deliberately. I was rather frightened when the
            steamer bumped us, and carried away the iron supports of the awning; and they cursed our
            fathers into the bargain, which I thought needless. The English have fallen into such
            contempt here that one no longer gets decent civility from anything in the _Miri_
            (Government). </p>
         <p> Olagnier has lent us a lovely little skiff, and I have had her repaired and painted, so
            Maurice is set up for shooting and boating. Darfour calls him the ‘son of a crocodile’
            because he loves the water, and generally delights in him hugely, and all my men are
            enchanted with him.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
