<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>April, 1868: Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, LUXOR, April, 1868.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK, </p>
         <p> I have been too weak to write, but the heat set in three days ago and took away my
            cough, and I feel much better. Maurice also flourishes in the broil, and protests
            against moving yet. He speaks a good deal of Arabic and is friends with everyone. It is
            _Salaam aleykoum ya maris_ on all sides. A Belgian has died here, and his two slaves, a
            very nice black boy and an Abyssinian girl, got my little varlet, Darfour, to coax me to
            take them under my protection, which I have done, as there appeared a strong probability
            that they would be ‘annexed’ by a rascally Copt who is a Consular agent at Keneh. I
            believe the Belgian has left money for them, which of course they would never get
            without someone to look after it, and so I have Ramadan, the boy, with me, and shall
            take the girl when I go, and carry them both to <placeName ref="Cairo"
            >Cairo</placeName>, settle their little business, and let them present a sealed-up book
            which they have to their Consul there, according to their master’s desire, and then
            marry the girl to some decent man. I have left her in Mustapha’s hareem till I go. </p>
         <p> I enjoyed Nubia immensely, and long to go and live with the descendants of a great
            _Ras_ (head, chief,) who entertained me at Ibreem, and who said, like Ravenswood, ‘Thou
            art come to a fallen house, and there is none to serve thee left save me.’ It was a
            paradise of a place, and the Nubian had the grand manners of a very old, proud nobleman.
            I had a letter to him from Sheykh Yussuf. </p>
         <p> Since I wrote the above it has turned quite chilly again, so we agreed to stay till the
            heat really begins. Maurice is so charmed with Luxor that he does not want to go, and we
            mean to let the boat and live here next winter. I think another week will see us start
            down stream. Janet talks of coming up the Nile with me next year, which would be
            pleasant. I am a little better than I have been the last two months. I was best in Nubia
            but I got a cold at Esneh, second hand from Maurice, which made me very seedy. I cannot
            go about at all for want of breath. Could you send me a chair such as people are carried
            in by two men? A common chair is awkward for the men when the banks are steep, and I am
            nervous, so I never go out. I wish you could see your son bare-legged and footed, in a
            shirt and a pair of white Arab drawers, rushing about with the fellaheen. He is
            everybody’s ‘brother’ or ‘son.’</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
