<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>January 25, 1869: Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, ASSOUAN, January 25, 1869.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK, </p>
         <p> We have been here ten days, and I find the air quite the best for me. I cough much
            less, only I am weak and short of breath. I have got a most excellent young Reis for my
            boat, and a sailor who sings like a nightingale, indeed he is not a sailor at all, but a
            professional <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> singer who came up with me for
            fun. He draws crowds to hear him, and at Esneh the congregation prayed for me in the
            mosque that God might reward me for the pleasure I had provided for them. Fancy desiring
            the prayers of this congregation for the welfare of the lady who gave me her opera-box
            last Saturday. If prayers could avail to cure I ought to get well rapidly. At Luxor Omar
            killed the sheep he had vowed, and Mustapha and Mohammed each killed two, as
            thank-offerings for my life, and all the derweeshes held two great _Zikrs_ in a tent
            pitched behind the boat, and drummed and chanted and called on the Lord for two whole
            nights; and every man in my boat fasted Ramadan severely, from Omar and the crew to the
            little boys. I think Darfour was the most meritorious of all, because he has such a
            Gargantuan appetite, but he fasted his thirty days bravely and rubbed his little nose in
            the dust energetically in prayer. </p>
         <p> On Christmas day I was at Esneh, it was warm and fine, and I made fantasia and had the
            girls to dance. Zeyneb and Hillaleah claim to be my own special _Ghazawee_, so to speak
            my _Ballerine da camera_, and they did their best. How I did long to transport the whole
            scene before your eyes—Ramadan warbling intense lovesongs, and beating on a tiny
            tambourine, while Zeyneb danced before him and gave the pantomime to his song; and the
            sailors, and girls, and respectable merchants sat _pêle-mêle_ all round on the deck, and
            the player on the rabab drew from it a wail like that of Isis for dead Osiris. I never
            quite know whether it is now or four thousand years ago, or even ten thousand, when I am
            in the dreamy intoxication of a real Egyptian fantasia; nothing is so antique as the
            Ghazawee—the _real_ dancing girls. They are still subject to religious ecstasies of a
            very curious kind, no doubt inherited from the remotest antiquity. Ask any learned
            pundit to explain to you the _Zar_—it is really curious. </p>
         <p> Now that I am too ill to write I feel sorry that I did not persist and write on the
            beliefs of Egypt in spite of your fear that the learned would cut me up, for I honestly
            believe that knowledge will die with me which few others possess. You must recollect
            that the learned know books, and I know men, and what is still more difficult, women. </p>
         <p> The Cataract is very bad this year, owing to want of water in the Nile, and to the
            shameful conduct of the Maohn here. The cataract men came to me, and prayed me to ‘give
            them my voice’ before the Mudir, which I will do. Allah ed-deen Bey seems a decent man
            and will perhaps remove the rascal, whose robberies on travellers are notorious, and his
            oppression of the poor savages who pull the boats up odious. Two boats have been
            severely damaged, and my friend the Reis of the Cataract (the one I threatened to shoot
            last year, and who has believed in me ever since) does not advise me to go up, though he
            would take me for nothing, he swears, if I wished. So as the air is good here and
            Maurice is happy with his companions, I will stay here. </p>
         <p> I meant to have discharged my men, but I have grown so fond of them (having so good a
            set), that I can’t bring myself to save £20 by turning them adrift when we are all so
            happy and comfortable, and the poor fellows are just marrying new wives with their
            wages. Good-bye dearest Alick, forgive a scrawl, for I am very weak all over, fingers
            and all. Best love to my darling Rainie. Three boats have little girls of five to eight
            on board, and I do envy them so. I think Maurice had better go home to you, when we get
            to <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>. He ought to be doing something.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
