<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>September 7, 1867: Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, BOULAK, September 7, 1867.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK, </p>
         <p> Many thanks for your letter and for all the trouble you have taken. I wish you were
            better. </p>
         <p> There is such a group all stitching away at the big new sail; Omar, the Reis, two or
            three volunteers, some old sailors of mine, and little Darfour. If I die I think you
            must have that tiny nigger over; he is such a merry little soul, I am sure you would
            love him, he is quite a civilized being and has a charming temper, and he seems very
            small to be left alone in the world. </p>
         <p> I hope Maurice is not of the faction of the _ennuyés_ of this generation. I am more and
            more of Omar’s opinion, who said, with a pleased sigh, as we sat on the deck under some
            lovely palm-trees in the bright moon-light, moored far from all human dwellings, ‘how
            sweet are the quiet places of the world.’ </p>
         <p> I wonder when Europe will drop the absurd delusion about Christians being persecuted by
            Muslims. It is absolutely the other way,—here at all events. The Christians know that
            they will always get backed by some Consul or other, and it is the Muslims who go to the
            wall invariably. The brute of a Patriarch is resolved to continue his persecution of the
            converts, and I was urged the other day by a Sheykh to go to the Sheykh ul-Islam himself
            and ask him to demand equal rights for all religions, which is the law, on behalf of
            these Coptic Protestants. Everywhere the Ulema have done what they could to protect
            them, even at Siout, where the American missionaries had caused them (the Ulemas) a good
            deal of annoyance on a former occasion. No one in Europe can conceive how much the Copts
            have the upper hand in the villages. They are backed by the Government, and they know
            that the Europeans will always side with them. </p>
         <p> _September_ 13.—Omar is crazy with delight at the idea of Maurice’s arrival, and Reis
            Mohammed is planning what men to take who can make fantasia, and not ask too much wages.
            Let me know what boat Maurice comes by that I may send Omar to Alexandria to meet him.
            Omar begs me to give you and Sitti Rainie his best salaam, and his assurance that he
            will take great care of the young master and ‘keep him very tight.’ I think Maurice will
            be diverted with small Darfour. Mabrook now really cooks very fairly under Omar’s
            orders, but he is beyond belief uncouth, and utters the wildest howls now that his voice
            is grown big and strong like himself. Moreover he ‘won’t be spoken to,’ as our servants
            say; but he is honest, clean, and careful. I should not have thought any human creature
            could remain so completely a savage in a civilized community. I rather respect his
            savage _hauteur_, especially as it is combined with truth and honesty.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
