<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://notesfromegypt.info/schema/tei_nfe_places.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>NFE: Controlled vocabulary for all places</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Data from this authority file for places can be reused under the Creative Commons
                    Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 licence (CC-BY-SA 4.0).</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the authority file for places used in the "Notes from Egypt" project
                    (https://notesfromegypt.info).</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <listPlace>
                <place xml:id="abou_simbel">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Abu Simbel</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>22.336944, 31.625556</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>The Abu Simbel temples are two massive rock-cut temples at Abu Simbel
                        (Arabic: أبو سمبل‎), a village in Aswan Governorate, Upper Egypt, near the
                        border with Sudan. They are situated on the western bank of Lake Nasser,
                        about 230 km southwest of Aswan (about 300 km by road). The complex is part
                        of the UNESCO World Heritage Site known as the "Nubian Monuments", which run
                        from Abu Simbel downriver to Philae (near Aswan). The twin temples were
                        originally carved out of the mountainside in the 13th century BC, during the
                        19th Dynasty reign of the Pharaoh Ramesses II. They serve as a lasting
                        monument to the king and his queen Nefertari, and commemorate his victory at
                        the Battle of Kadesh. Their huge external rock relief figures have become
                        iconic. </note>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/362040</idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abu_Simbel_temples</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="abydos">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Abydos</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>26.185, 31.918889</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Abydos (Arabic: أبيدوس‎; /əˈbaɪdɒs/ Sahidic Coptic: Ⲉⲃⲱⲧ Ebōt) is one of
                        the oldest cities of ancient Egypt, and also of the eighth nome in Upper
                        Egypt. It is located about 11 kilometres west of the Nile at latitude 26°
                        10' N, near the modern Egyptian towns of El Araba El Madfuna and El Balyana.
                        In the ancient Egyptian language, the city was called Abdju (ꜣbḏw or
                        AbDw).</note>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/361885</idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abydos,_Egypt</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="alexandria">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Alexandria</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>31.2, 29.916667</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Alexandria (/ˌælɪɡˈzændriə/ or /-ˈzɑːnd-/; Arabic: الإسكندرية‎
                        al-ʾIskandariyya; Egyptian Arabic: اسكندرية‎ Eskendereyya; Coptic: ⲣⲁⲕⲟϯ
                        Rakodī; Greek: Αλεξάνδρεια Alexandria) is the second-largest city in Egypt.
                        Alexandria was founded in c. 331 BC by Alexander the Great, king of Macedon
                        and leader of the Greek League of Corinth, during his conquest of the
                        Achaemenid Empire. By the time of the Arab conquest of Egypt in 641 AD, the
                        city had already been largely plundered and lost its significance before
                        re-emerging in the modern era. From the late 18th century, Alexandria became
                        a major centre of the international shipping industry and one of the most
                        important trading centres in the world, both because it profited from the
                        easy overland connection between the Mediterranean Sea and the Red
                        Sea.</note>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexandria</idno>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/361058</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="alhambra">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Alhambra</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>37.17695, -3.59001</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>The Alhambra (/ælˈhæmbrə/ (About this soundlisten), Spanish: [aˈlambɾa];
                        Arabic: الْحَمْرَاء‎, romanized: Al-Ḥamrāʾ, pronounced [alħamˈraːʔ], lit.
                        'The Red One') is a palace and fortress complex located in Granada,
                        Andalusia, Spain. It was originally constructed as a small fortress in 889
                        CE on the remains of Roman fortifications, and then largely ignored until
                        its ruins were renovated and rebuilt in the mid-13th century by the Arab
                        Nasrid emir Mohammed ben Al-Ahmar of the Emirate of Granada, who built its
                        current palace and walls with many beautiful, intricate details. It was
                        converted into a royal palace in 1333 by Yusuf I, Sultan of Granada. After
                        the conclusion of the Christian Reconquista in 1492, the site became the
                        Royal Court of Ferdinand and Isabella (where Christopher Columbus received
                        royal endorsement for his expedition), and the palaces were partially
                        altered in the Renaissance style. In 1526 Charles I &amp; V commissioned a
                        new Renaissance palace better befitting the Holy Roman Emperor in the
                        revolutionary Mannerist style influenced by humanist philosophy in direct
                        juxtaposition with the Nasrid Andalusian architecture, but it was ultimately
                        never completed due to Morisco rebellions in Granada.</note>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alhambra</idno>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/7302839</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="assouan">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Aswan</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>24.088889, 32.899722</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Aswan (/æsˈwɑːn, ɑːs-/, also US: /ˈæswɑːn, ˈɑːs-, ˈæz-/; Arabic: أسوان‎,
                        romanized: ʾAswān [ʔɑsˈwɑːn]; Coptic: Ⲥⲟⲩⲁⲛ, romanized: Souan pronounced
                        [swaːn]) is a city in the south of Egypt, and is the capital of the Aswan
                        Governorate. Aswan is a busy market and tourist centre located just north of
                        the Aswan Dam on the east bank of the Nile at the first cataract. </note>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aswan</idno>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/359792</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="atleh">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Atleh</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo> </geo>
                    </location>
                    <idno type="geonames"/>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="bellianeh">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">El Balyana</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>26.233333, 32</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>El Balyana (Arabic: البلينا‎; Coptic: ⲃⲩⲗⲓⲁⲛⲏ, ⲧⲡⲟⲗⲩⲃⲓⲁⲛⲏ Tpolubianē,
                        pronounced [təpoliβjˈanə]) is a small town in the Sohag Governorate of Upper
                        Egypt. Located on the west bank of the Nile, it is situated near the ancient
                        Egyptian city of Abydos.</note>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/361435</idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/El_Balyana</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="beni_hassan">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Beni Hasan</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>27.933333, 30.883333</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Beni Hasan (also written as Bani Hasan, or also Beni-Hassan) (Arabic: بني
                        حسن‎) is an ancient Egyptian cemetery site. It is located approximately 20
                        kilometers to the south of modern-day Minya in the region known as Middle
                        Egypt, the area between Asyut and Memphis. While there are some Old Kingdom
                        burials at the site, it was primarily used during the Middle Kingdom,
                        spanning the 21st to 17th centuries BCE (Middle Bronze Age). To the south of
                        the cemetery is a temple constructed by Hatshepsut and Thutmose III,
                        dedicated to the local goddess Pakhet. It is known as the Cave of Artemis,
                        because the Greeks identified Pakhet with Artemis, and the temple is
                        subterranean. </note>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/359243</idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beni_Hasan</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="benisouef">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Beni Suef</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>29.066667, 31.083333</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Beni Suef (Arabic: بني سويف‎ Baniswēf) is the capital city of the Beni
                        Suef Governorate in Egypt. An important agricultural trade centre on the
                        west bank of the Nile River, the city is located 110 km south of Cairo. </note>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/359173</idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beni_Suef</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="bibbeh">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Bibbeh</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo> </geo>
                    </location>
                    <idno type="geonames"/>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="boulak">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Boulaq</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>30.053, 31.23 </geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Boulaq[a] (Arabic: بولاق‎, romanized: Būlāq from Ancient Greek: φυλακή
                        "guard, customs post"), is a district of Cairo, in Egypt. It neighbours
                        Downtown Cairo, Azbakeya, and the River Nile. </note>
                    <idno type="geonames">http://sws.geonames.org/358683/</idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boulaq</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="bubastis">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Bubastis</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>30.572778, 31.51</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Bubastis (Bohairic Coptic: Ⲡⲟⲩⲃⲁⲥϯ Poubasti; Greek: Βούβαστις Boubastis or
                        Βούβαστος Boubastos), also known in Arabic as Tell-Basta or in Egyptian as
                        Per-Bast, was an ancient Egyptian city. Bubastis is often identified with
                        the biblical Pi-Beseth (Hebrew: פי-בסת‎ py-bst, Ezekiel 30:17). It was the
                        capital of its own nome, located along the River Nile in the Delta region of
                        Lower Egypt, and notable as a center of worship for the feline goddess
                        Bastet, and therefore the principal depository in Egypt of mummies of
                        cats.</note>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bubastis</idno>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/358710</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="cairo">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Cairo</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>30.033333, 31.233333</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Cairo is the capital of Egypt. Located near the Nile Delta, Cairo was
                        founded in 969 AD by the Fatimid dynasty, but the land composing the
                        present-day city was the site of ancient national capitals whose remnants
                        remain visible in parts of Old Cairo. Cairo has long been a centre of the
                        region's political and cultural life, and is titled "the city of a thousand
                        minarets" for its preponderance of Islamic architecture.</note>
                    <idno type="geonames">http://sws.geonames.org/360630</idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cairo</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="damietta">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Damietta</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>31.416667, 31.816667</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Damietta (Arabic: دمياط‎ Dumyāṭ, IPA: [domˈjɑːtˤ]; Coptic: ⲧⲁⲙⲓⲁϯ,
                        romanized: Tamiat) is a port city and the capital of the Damietta
                        Governorate in Egypt, a former bishopric and present multiple Catholic
                        titular see. It is located at the Damietta branch, an eastern distributary
                        of the Nile Delta, 15 kilometres from the Mediterranean Sea, about 200
                        kilometres north of Cairo. </note>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/358048</idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Damietta</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="delta">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Delta</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo> </geo>
                    </location>
                    <idno type="geonames"> </idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="dendera">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Dendera</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>26.16627, 32.661584 </geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Dendera (Arabic: دندرة‎ Dandarah; Ancient Greek: Τεντυρις or Τεντυρα;
                        Coptic: ⲧⲉⲛⲧⲱⲣⲉ or ⲧⲉⲛⲧⲱⲣⲓ), also spelled Denderah, ancient Iunet, Tentyris
                        or Tentyra is a small town and former bishopric in Egypt situated on the
                        west bank of the Nile, about 5 kilometres south of Qena, on the opposite
                        side of the river. It is located approximately 60 kilometres north of Luxor
                        and remains a Latin Catholic titular see. It contains the Dendera Temple
                        complex, one of the best-preserved temple sites from ancient Upper Egypt. </note>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/358422</idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dendera</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="edfou">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Edfu</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>24.977778, 32.873333</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Edfu (Arabic: إدفو‎ pronounced [ˈʔedfu], Coptic: Ⲧⲃⲱ vars. Ⲁⲧⲃⲱ, Ⲧⲃⲟ
                        (Sahidic); Ⲑⲃⲱ(Bohairic); also spelt Idfu, or in modern French as Edfou, and
                        known in antiquity as Behdet) is an Egyptian city, located on the west bank
                        of the Nile River between Esna and Aswan, with a population of approximately
                        sixty thousand people. Edfu is the site of the Ptolemaic Temple of Horus and
                        an ancient settlement, Tell Edfu. About 5 km south of Edfu are remains of
                        ancient pyramids. </note>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/355635</idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edfu</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="egypt">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Egypt</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo> </geo>
                    </location>
                    <idno type="geonames"> </idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="el_kab">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">El Kab</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>25.118889, 32.797778</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>El Kab (or better Elkab) is an Upper Egyptian site on the east bank of the
                        Nile at the mouth of the Wadi Hillal about 80 kilometres south of Luxor
                        (ancient Thebes). El Kab was called Nekheb in the Egyptian language (Coptic:
                        ⲛ̀ⲭⲁⲃ Enkhab), a name that refers to Nekhbet, the goddess depicted as a
                        white vulture. In Greek it was called Eileithyias polis, "city of the
                        goddess Eileithyia". El Kab consists of prehistoric and ancient Egyptian
                        settlements, rock-cut tombs of the early Eighteenth Dynasty (1550–1295 BC),
                        remains of temples dating from the Early Dynastic period (3100–2686 BC) to
                        the Ptolemaic Kingdom (332–30 BC), as well as part of the walls of a Coptic
                        monastery.</note>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/360986</idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/El_Kab</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="esneh">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Esna</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>25.3, 32.55</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Esna (Arabic: إسنا‎ IPA: [ˈʔesnæ], Ancient Egyptian: jwny.t or tꜣ-snt;
                        Coptic: ⲥⲛⲏ or ⲉⲥⲛⲏ Snē from tꜣ-snt; Koinē Greek: Λατόπολις Latópolis or
                        πόλις Λάτων (Pólis Látōn) or Λάττων (Lattōn); Latin: Lato), is a city of
                        Egypt. It is located on the west bank of the Nile some 55 km south of
                        Luxor.</note>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/355449</idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Esna</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="fazogloo">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Fazogloo</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo> </geo>
                    </location>
                    <note/>
                    <idno type="geonames"> </idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia"> </idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="feshn">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">El Fashn</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>28.822718, 30.899205</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>El Fashn (Arabic: الفشن‎, Coptic: ⲡⲃⲏϣⲛ) is a city in Egypt. It is
                        situated near the southern borders of Beni Suef Governorate.</note>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/361329</idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/El_Fashn</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="gebel_sheykh_embarak">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Gabal Sheikh Umbarak</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo/>
                    </location>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="gebel_sheykh_hereedee">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Gabal El Haridi</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>26.766667, 31.566667 </geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Gabal El Haridi is an archaeological site in Egypt approximately 350
                        kilometers south of Cairo within Sakulta.</note>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gabal_El_Haridi</idno>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/356103</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="girgeh">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Girga</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>26.333333, 31.9</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Girga (Arabic: جرجا‎ pronounced [ˈɡeɾɡæ], Coptic: ⲧⲓⲛ Din?) is a city in
                        the Sohag Governorate of Upper Egypt. It is located on the west bank of the
                        Nile River.</note>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/355026</idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Girga</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="heliopolis">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Heliopolis</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>30.10882, 31.37924</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Heliopolis (Egyptian Arabic: مصر الجديده‎, Maṣr eg-Gedīda, [ˈmɑsˤɾ eg
                        ɡeˈdidæ], lit. "New Egypt") was a suburb outside Cairo, Egypt, which has
                        since merged with Cairo as a district of the city and is one of the more
                        affluent areas of Cairo.</note>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/352262</idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heliopolis,_Cairo</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="isbekeeyeh">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Uzbakeya</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>30.052778, 31.248333</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Uzbakeya (Arabic: أزبكية‎; also spelled Al Uzbakeya or Auzbekiya) is one
                        of the central districts of Cairo, Egypt. It contains many historically
                        important establishments. One of these is the Saint Mark's Coptic Orthodox
                        Cathedral (Azbakeya), which was inaugurated by Pope Mark VIII in 1800 and
                        served as the seat of the Coptic Pope in Cairo from 1800 to 1971.</note>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Azbakeya</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="kalabshee">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Kalabsha</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>23.960833, 32.867222</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>New Kalabsha is a promontory located near Aswan in Egypt. It houses
                        several important temples, structures, and other remains that have been
                        relocated here from the site of Old Kalabsha (Arabic: Bab al-Kalabsha‎,
                        "Gate of Kalabsha", the name of Kelāpiş tribe; Ancient Greek: Ταλμις,
                        Talmis) and other sites in Lower Nubia, to avoid the rising waters of Lake
                        Nasser caused by the construction of the Aswan High Dam.</note>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/8425909</idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Kalabsha</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="khartoum">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Khartoum</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>15.500556, 32.56</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Khartoum or Khartum (/kɑːrˈtuːm/ kar-TOOM; Arabic: الخرطوم‎, romanized:
                        Al-Khurṭūm) is the capital of Sudan. Khartoum was founded in 1821 as part of
                        Ottoman Egypt, north of the ancient city of Soba.</note>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/379252</idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Khartoum</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="kenneh">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Qena</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>26.166667, 32.716667</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Qena (Arabic: قنا‎ Qinā [ˈʔenæ], locally: [ˈɡena]; Coptic: ⲕⲱⲛⲏ Kone) is a
                        city in Upper Egypt, and the capital of the Qena Governorate. Situated on
                        the east bank of the Nile, it was known in antiquity as Kaine (Greek Καινή,
                        meaning "new (city)"; Latinized transliteration: Caene) and
                        Maximianopolis.</note>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/350550</idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qena</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="koos">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Qus</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>25.933333, 32.766667</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Qus (Arabic: قوص‎; Coptic: ⲕⲱⲥ or ⲕⲟⲥ) is a city in the modern Qena
                        Governorate, Egypt, located on the east bank of the Nile. The temple of
                        Haroeris (Horus) and Heqet was built during the Ptolemaic Period. Nowadays,
                        only two ruined pylons of the temple remain.</note>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/350422</idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qus</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="koum_ombo">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Koum Ombo</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>24.466667, 32.95</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Kom Ombo (Arabic: كوم أمبو‎, Coptic: Ⲉⲙⲃⲱ Embo, Ancient Greek: Ὄμβοι
                        Omboi) or Ombos or Latin: Ambo and Ombi – is an agricultural town in Egypt
                        famous for the Temple of Kom Ombo.</note>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/353802</idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kom_Ombo</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="mahmoudieh_canal">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Mahmoudia Canal</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>31.183889, 30.524167</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Mahmoudia Canal (Greek: Ἀγαθὸς Δαίμων Agathos Daimon or Greek: Μέγας
                        ποταμός Megas potamos) is a 72 km-long sub-canal from the Nile River which
                        starts at the Nile-port of Mahmoudia and goes through Alexandria to the
                        Mediterranean Sea. It was built to supply Alexandria with food and fresh
                        water from the Nile.</note>
                    <idno type="geonames"> </idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahmoudiyah_Canal</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="mecca">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Mecca</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>21.4225, 39.823333</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Mecca, officially Makkah al-Mukarramah (Arabic: مكة المكرمة‎, romanized:
                        Makkat al-Mukarramah, lit. 'Makkah the Noble') and commonly shortened to
                        Makkah, is the holiest city in Islam</note>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/104515</idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mecca</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="minieh">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Minya</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>28.119444, 30.744444</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Minya (Arabic: المنيا‎ [elˈmenjæ]; Coptic: ⲧⲙⲱⲛⲏ) is the capital of the
                        Minya Governorate in Upper Egypt. The name of the city is derived from its
                        ancient Egyptian name Men'at Khufu, meaning the nursing city of Khufu,
                        linking it to the Pharaoh Khufu or Cheops, builder of the Great Pyramid at
                        Giza.</note>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/360686</idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minya,_Egypt</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="nubia">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Nubia</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo/>
                    </location>
                    <note/>
                    <idno type="geonames"> </idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia"> </idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="philae">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Philae</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>24.020833, 32.889444</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Philae (/ˈfaɪliː/; Greek: Φιλαί or Φιλή and Πιλάχ, Arabic: فيلة‎ Egyptian
                        Arabic: [fiːlæ], Egyptian: p3-jw-rķ' or 'pA-jw-rq; Coptic: ⲡⲓⲗⲁⲕ, ⲡⲓⲗⲁⲕϩ) is
                        an island in the reservoir of the Aswan Low Dam, downstream of the Aswan Dam
                        and Lake Nasser, Egypt. Philae was originally located near the expansive
                        First Cataract of the Nile in Upper Egypt and was the site of an Egyptian
                        temple complex.</note>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/356859</idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philae</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="sakhara">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Saqqara</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>29.871111, 31.216389</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Saqqara (Arabic: سقارة‎, Egyptian Arabic pronunciation: [sɑʔˈʔɑːɾɑ]), also
                        spelled Sakkara or Saccara in English /səˈkɑːrə/, is a vast, ancient burial
                        ground in Egypt, serving as the necropolis for the ancient Egyptian capital,
                        Memphis. Saqqara contains numerous pyramids, including the world-famous Step
                        pyramid of Djoser, sometimes referred to as the Step Tomb, and a number of
                        mastaba tombs.</note>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/349608</idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saqqara</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="second_cataract">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Second Cataract</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>21.48, 30.97</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>The Second Cataract (or Great Cataract) was in Nubia and is now submerged
                        under Lake Nasser.</note>
                    <idno type="geonames"> </idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cataracts_of_the_Nile</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="senaar">
                    <placeName>Sennar</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>13.55, 33.583333</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Sennar (Arabic: سنار‎ Sannār) is a town on the Blue Nile in Sudan and
                        capital of the state of Sennar. For several centuries it was the capital of
                        the Funj Kingdom of Sennar.</note>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/367644</idno>
                    <idno type="wikidata">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q611867</idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sennar</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="siout">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Asyut</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>27.183333, 31.166667</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Asyut (Arabic: أسيوط‎ Asyūṭ pronounced [ʔɑsˈjuːtˤ], Coptic: ⲥⲓⲟⲟⲩⲧ, ⲥⲓⲱⲟⲩⲧ
                        Siōwt pronounced [sʲˈo:wt]) is the capital of the modern Asyut Governorate
                        in Egypt. It was built close to the ancient city of the same name, which is
                        situated nearby. </note>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/359783</idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asyut</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="suez">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Suez</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>29.966667, 32.55</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Suez (Arabic: السويس‎ as-Suways; pronounced [esseˈweːs]) is a seaport city
                        (population of about 750,000 as of August 2018) in north-eastern Egypt,
                        located on the north coast of the Gulf of Suez (a branch of the Red Sea),
                        near the southern terminus of the Suez Canal, having the same boundaries as
                        Suez Governorate. It has three harbours, Adabiya, Ain Sokhna and Port
                        Tawfiq, and extensive port facilities.</note>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/359796</idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Suez</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="tanta">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Tanta</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>30.783333, 31</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Tanta (Arabic: طنطا‎ Ṭanṭa pronounced [ˈtˤɑntˤɑ], Coptic: ⲧⲁⲛⲧⲁⲑⲟ) is a
                        city in Egypt with the country's fifth largest populated area and 658,798
                        inhabitants as of 2018. Tanta is located between Cairo and Alexandria: 94 km
                        north of Cairo and 130 km southeast of Alexandria. The capital of Gharbia
                        Governorate, it is a center for the cotton-ginning industry. One of the
                        major railway lines goes through Tanta.</note>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/347497</idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tanta</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="thebes">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Thebes</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>25.720556, 32.610278</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Thebes (Ancient Greek: Θῆβαι, Thēbai), known to the ancient Egyptians as
                        Waset, was an ancient Egyptian city located along the Nile about 800
                        kilometers south of the Mediterranean. Its ruins lie within the modern
                        Egyptian city of Luxor. Thebes was the main city of the fourth Upper
                        Egyptian nome (Sceptre nome) and was the capital of Egypt for long periods
                        during the Middle Kingdom and New Kingdom eras. It was close to Nubia and
                        the Eastern Desert, with its valuable mineral resources and trade routes. It
                        was a cult center and the most venerated city during many periods of ancient
                        Egyptian history. The site of Thebes includes areas on both the eastern bank
                        of the Nile, where the temples of Karnak and Luxor stand and where the city
                        proper was situated; and the western bank, where a necropolis of large
                        private and royal cemeteries and funerary complexes can be found.</note>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/347342</idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thebes,_Egypt</idno>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="wady_halfeh">
                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Wadi Halfa</placeName>
                    <location>
                        <geo>21.783333, 31.366667</geo>
                    </location>
                    <note>Wādī Ḥalfā (Arabic: وادي حلفا‎) is a city in the Northern state of Sudan
                        on the shores of "Lake Nubia" (the Sudanese section of Lake Nasser) near the
                        border with Egypt. It is the terminus of a rail line from Khartoum and the
                        point where goods are transferred from rail to ferries going down the lake.
                        The town is located amidst numerous ancient Nubian antiquities and was the
                        focus of much archaeological work by teams seeking to save artifacts from
                        the flooding caused by the completion of the Aswan Dam.</note>
                    <idno type="geonames">https://www.geonames.org/364132</idno>
                    <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wadi_Halfa</idno>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>