<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, LUXOR, February 3, 1867.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/96">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <date when="1867-02-03">3 February 1867</date>
               <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/360502">Luxor</settlement>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff Gordon</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK, </p>
         <p> The boat goes down to-morrow and I have little to add to Mutter’s letter, only that I
            am better. </p>
         <p> There is a man here from Girgeh, who says he is married to a Ginneeyeh (fairy)
            princess. I have asked to be presented to her, but I suspect there will be some hitch
            about it. It will be like Alexis’s _Allez, Madame, vous êtes trop incrédule_. {334} The
            unintelligible thing is the motive which prompts wonders and miracles here, seeing that
            the wonder workers do not get any money by it; and indeed, very often give, like the
            Indian saint I told you of who gave me four dollars. His miracles were all gratis, which
            was the most miraculous thing of all in a saint. I am promised that the Ginneeyeh shall
            come through the wall. If she should do so I shall be compelled to believe in her, as
            there are no mechanical contrivances in Luxor. All the Hareem here believe it, and the
            man’s human wife swears she waits on her like a slave, and backs her husband’s lie or
            delusion fully. I have not seen the man, but I should not wonder if it were a
            delusion—real _bona fide_ visions and revelations are so common, and I think there is
            but little downright imposture. Meanwhile familiarity breeds contempt. Jinns, Afreets
            and Shaitans inspire far less respect than the stupidest ghost at home, and the devil
            (Iblees) is reduced to deplorable insignificance. He is never mentioned in the pulpit,
            or in religious conversation, with the respect he enjoys in Christian countries. I
            suppose we may console ourselves with the hope that he will pay off the Muslims for
            their neglect of him hereafter. </p>
         <p> I cannot describe to you the misery here now, indeed it is wearisome even to think of:
            every day some new tax. Now every beast; camel, cow, sheep, donkey, horse, is made to
            pay. The fellaheen can no longer eat bread, they are living on barley meal, mixed with
            water and new green stuff, vetches etc., which to people used to good food is terrible,
            and I see all my acquaintances growing seedy and ragged and anxious. Yussuf is clear of
            debt, his religion having kept him from borrowing, but he wants to sell his little slave
            girl, and has sold his donkey, and he is the best off. The taxation makes life almost
            impossible—100 piastres per feddan, a tax on every crop, on every annual fruit, and
            again when it is sold in the market; on every man, on charcoal, on butter, on salt, on
            the dancing girls. I wonder I am not tormented for money—not above three people have
            tried to beg or borrow. </p>
         <p> Thanks for the Westminster epilogue; it always amuses me much. So Terence was a nigger.
            There is no trace of the negro ‘boy’ in his Davus. My nigger has grown huge, and has
            developed a voice of thunder. He is of the elephantine rather than the tiger species, a
            very mild young savage. I shall be sorry when Palgrave takes him. I am tempted to buy
            Yussuf’s nice little Dinka girl to replace him, only a girl is such an impossibility
            where there is no regular hareem. In the boat Achmet is enough under Omar; but in this
            large dusty house, and with errands to run, and comers and goers to look after, pipes
            and coffee and the like, it takes two boys to be comfortable. Mabrook too washes very
            well. It is surprising how fast the boys learn, and how well they do their work. Achmet,
            who is quite little, would be a perfectly sufficient servant for a man alone; he can
            cook, wash, clean the rooms, make the beds, do all the table service, knife and plate
            cleaning, all fairly well, and I believe now he would get along even without Omar’s
            orders. Mabrook is slower, but he has the same merit our poor Hassan had, {336} he never
            forgets what he has been once told to do, and he is clean in his work, though hopelessly
            dirty as to his clothes. He cannot get used to them, and takes a roll in the dust, or
            leans against a dirty wall, oblivious of his clean-washed blue shirt. Achmet is quicker
            and more careless, but they both are good boys and very fond of Omar. ‘Uncle Omar’ is
            the form of address, though he scolds them pretty severely if they misbehave; and I
            observe that the high jinks take place chiefly when only I am in the way, and Omar gone
            to market or to the mosque. The little rogues have found out that their laughing does
            not ‘affect my nerves,’ and I am often treated to a share in the joke. How I wish Rainie
            could see the children: they would amuse her. Yussuf’s girl, ‘Meer en Nezzil,’ is a
            charming child, and very clever; her emphatic way of explaining everything to me, and
            her gestures, would delight you. Her cousin and future husband, age five (she is six),
            broke the doll which I had given her, and her description of it was most dramatic,
            ending with a wheedling glance at the cupboard and ‘of course there are no more dolls
            there; oh no, no more.’ She is a fine little creature, far more Arab than fellaha; quite
            a _Shaitan_, her father says. She came in full of making cakes for Bairam, and offered
            her services; ‘Oh my aunt, if thou wantest anything I can work,’ said she, tucking up
            her sleeves.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>