<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>May 10, 1866: Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, LUXOR, May 10, 1866.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK, </p>
         <p> The real summer heat—the _Skems el-Kebeer_ (big sun) has fairly set in, and of course I
            am all the better. You would give my camel a good backsheesh if you saw how prodigiously
            fat I have grown on her milk; it beats codliver-oil hollow. You can drink a gallon
            without feeling it, it is so easy of digestion. </p>
         <p> I have lent the dahabieh to Mustapha and to one or two more, to go to Keneh on
            business, and when she returns (which will be to-day) I shall make ready to depart too,
            and drop down stream. Omar wants me to go down to Damietta, to ‘amuse my mind and dilate
            my stomach’ a little; and I think of doing so. </p>
         <p> Palgrave was here about a fortnight ago, on Mustapha’s and Mariette’s business. ‘By
            God! this English way is wonderful,’ said a witness, ‘that English Bey questioned me
            till my stomach came out.’ I loved Mustapha Bey, who was with him; such a nice, kind,
            gentle creature, and very intelligent and full of good sense. I rejoice to hear that he
            returns my liking, and has declared himself ‘one of my darweeshes.’ Talking of
            darweeshes reminds me of the Festival of Sheykh Gibrieel this year. I had forgotten the
            day, but in the evening some people came for me to go and eat some of the meat of the
            Sheykh, who is also a good patron of mine, they say; being a poor man’s saint, and of a
            humble spirit, it is said he favours me. There was plenty of meat and _melocheea_ and
            bread; and then _zikrs_ of different kinds, and a _Gama el Fokara_ (assembly of the
            poor). _Gama_ is the true word for Mosque—_i.e._, Meeting, which consists in a great
            circle of men seated thick on the ground, with two poets facing each other, who
            improvise religious verses. On this occasion the rule of the game was to end each stanza
            with a word having the sound of _wahed_ (one), or _el Had_ (the first). Thus one sung:
            ‘Let a man take heed how he walks,’ etc., etc.; and ‘pray to God not to let him fall,’
            which sound like _Had_. And so they went on, each chanting a verse alternately. One
            gesticulated almost as much as an Italian and pronounced beautifully; the other was
            quiet, but had a nice voice, and altogether it was very pretty. At the end of each verse
            the people made a sort of chorus, which was sadly like the braying of asses. The _zikr_
            of the Edfoo men was very curious. Our people did it quietly, and the _moonsheed_ sang
            very sweetly—indeed ‘the song of the moonsheed is the sugar in the sherbet to the
            Zikkeer,’ said a man who came up when it was over, streaming with perspiration and
            radiant with smiles. Some day I will write to you the whole ‘_grund Idee_’ of a _zikr_,
            which is, in fact, an attempt to make present ‘the communion of saints,’ dead or living.
            As I write arrives the Arooset er-rallee, and my crew furl her big sail quite ‘Bristol
            fashion.’ My men have come together again, some from Nubia and some from the Delta; and
            I shall go down with my old lot. </p>
         <p> Omar and Achmet have implored me not to take another maid at all; they say they live
            like Pashas now they have only the lady to please; that it will be a pleasure to ‘lick
            my shoes clean,’ whereas the boots of the _Cameriera_ were intolerable. The feeling of
            the Arab servants towards European colleagues is a little like that of ‘niggers’ about
            ‘mean whites’—mixed hatred, fear, and scorn. The two have done so well to make me
            comfortable that I have no possible reason for insisting on encumbering myself with ‘an
            old man of the sea,’ in the shape of a maid; and the difference in cost is immense. The
            one dish of my dinner is ample relish to their bread and beans, while the cooking for a
            maid, and her beer and wine, cost a great deal. Omar irons my clothes very tidily, and
            little Achmet cleans the house as nicely as possible. I own I am quite as much relieved
            by the absence of the ‘civilized element’ as my retainers are. </p>
         <p> Did I describe the Coptic Good Friday? Imagine 450 _Rekahs_ in church! I have seen many
            queer things, but nothing half so queer as the bobbing of the Copts. </p>
         <p> I went the other day to the old church six or eight miles off, where they buried the
            poor old Bishop who died a week ago. Abu Khom, a Christian _shaheed_ (martyr), is buried
            there. He appeared to Mustapha’s father when lost in the desert, and took him safe home.
            On that occasion he was well mounted, and robed all in white, with a _litham_ in over
            his face. No one dares to steal anything near his tomb, not one ear of corn. He revealed
            himself long ago to one of the descendants of Abu-l-Hajjaj, and to this day every Copt
            who marries in Luxor gives a pair of fowls to the family of that Muslim in remembrance
            of Abu Khom. </p>
         <p> I shall leave Luxor in five or six days—and write now to stop all letters in <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>. </p>
         <p> I don’t know what to do with my sick; they come from forty miles off, and sometimes
            twenty or thirty people sleep outside the house. I dined with the Maōhn last night—‘pot
            luck’—and was much pleased. The dear old lady was so vexed not to have a better dinner
            for me that she sent me a splendid tray of _baklaweh_ this morning to make up for
            it.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>