<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>March 22, 1864: To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, LUXOR, March 22, 1864.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK, </p>
         <p> I am glad my letters amuse you. Sometimes I think they must breathe the unutterable
            dulness of Eastern life: not that it is dull to me, a curious spectator, but how the men
            with nothing to do can endure it is a wonder. I went yesterday to call on a Turk at
            Karnac; he is a gentlemanly man, the son of a former Moudir, who was murdered, I
            believe, for his cruelty and extortion. He has 1,000 feddans (acres, or a little more)
            of land, and lives in a mud house, larger but no better than any fellahs, with two wives
            and the brother of one of them. He leaves the farm to his fellaheen altogether, I fancy.
            There was one book, a Turkish one; I could not read the title-page, and he did not tell
            me what it was. In short, there was no means of killing time but the narghile, no horse,
            no gun, nothing, and yet they did not seem bored. The two women are always clamorous for
            my visits, and very noisy and school-girlish, but apparently excellent friends and very
            good-natured. The gentleman gave me a _kufyeh_ (thick head kerchief for the sun), so I
            took the ladies a bit of silk I happened to have. You never heard anything like his
            raptures over Maurice’s portrait, ‘_Mashallah_, _Mashallah_, _Wallahy zay el ward_’ (It
            is the will of God, and by God he is like a rose). But I can’t ‘cotton to’ the Turks. I
            always feel that they secretly dislike us European women, though they profess huge
            admiration and pay _personal_ compliments, which an Arab very seldom attempts. I heard
            Seleem Effendi and Omar discussing English ladies one day lately while I was inside the
            curtain with Seleem’s slave girl, and they did not know I heard them. Omar described
            Janet, and was of the opinion that a man who was married to her could want nothing more.
            ‘By my soul, she rides like a Bedawee, she shoots with the gun and pistol, and rows the
            boat; she speaks many languages, works with the needle like an Efreet, and to see her
            hands run over the teeth of the music-box (keys of piano) amazes the mind, while her
            singing gladdens the soul. How then should her husband ever desire the coffee-shop?
            _Wallahy_! she can always amuse him at home. And as to my lady, the thing is not that
            she does not know. When I feel my stomach tightened, I go to the divan and say to her,
            ‘Do you want anything, a pipe, or sherbet, or so and so?’ and I talk till she lays down
            her book and talks to me, and I question her and amuse my mind, and, by God! if I were a
            rich man and could marry one English Hareem like that I would stand before her and serve
            her like her memlook. You see I am only this lady’s servant, and I have not once sat in
            the coffee-shop because of the sweetness of her tongue. Is it not therefore true that
            the man who can marry such Hareem is rich more than with money?’ Seleem seemed disposed
            to think a little more of looks, though he quite agreed with all Omar’s enthusiasm, and
            asked if Janet were beautiful. Omar answered with decorous vagueness that she was a
            ‘moon,’ but declined mentioning her hair, eyes, etc. (it is a liberty to describe a
            woman minutely). I nearly laughed out at hearing Omar relate his manœuvres to make me
            ‘amuse his mind’; it seems I am in no danger of being discharged for being dull. </p>
         <p> The weather has set in so hot that I have shifted my quarters out of my fine room to
            the south-west into one with only three sides looking over a lovely green view to the
            north-east, with a huge sort of solid veranda, as large as the room itself, on the open
            side; thus I live in the open air altogether. The bats and the swallows are quite
            sociable; I hope the serpents and scorpions will be more reserved. ‘_El Khamaseen_’ (the
            fifty) has begun, and the wind is enough to mix up heaven and earth, but it is not
            distressing like the Cape south-easter, and, though hot, not choking like the Khamseen
            in <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> and Alexandria. Mohammed brought me a
            handful of the new wheat just now. Think of harvest in March and April! These winds are
            as good for the crops here as a ‘nice steady rain’ is in England. It is not necessary to
            water so much when the wind blows strong. As I rode through the green fields along the
            dyke, a little boy sang as he turned round on the musically-creaking Sakìah (the
            water-wheel turned by an ox) the one eternal Sakìah tune—the words are _ad libitum_, and
            my little friend chanted ‘Turn oh Sakìah to the right and turn to the left—who will take
            care of me if my father dies? Turn oh Sakìah, etc., pour water for the figs and the
            grass and for the watermelons. Turn oh Sakìah!’ Nothing is so pathetic as that Sakìah
            song. </p>
         <p> I passed the house of the Sheykh-el-Ababdeh, who called out to me to take coffee. The
            moon was splendid and the scene was lovely. The handsome black-brown Sheykh in dark
            robes and white turban, Omar in a graceful white gown and red turban, and the wild
            Ababdeh in all manner of dingy white rags, and with every kind of uncouth weapon,
            spears, matchlocks, etc., in every kind of wild and graceful attitude, with their long
            black ringlets and bare heads, a few little black-brown children quite naked and shaped
            like Cupids. And there we sat and looked so romantic and talked quite like ladies and
            gentlemen about the merits of Sakna and Almás, the two great rival women-singers of
               <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>. I think the Sheykh wished to display his
            experiences of fashionable life. </p>
         <p> The Copts are now fasting and cross. They fast fifty-five days for Lent; no meat, fish,
            eggs, or milk, no exception for Sundays, no food till after twelve at noon, and no
            intercourse with the hareem. The only comfort is lots of arrak, and what a Copt can
            carry decently is an unknown quantity; one seldom sees them drunk, but they imbibe awful
            quantities. They offer me wine and arrak always, and can’t think why I don’t drink it. I
            believe they suspect my Christianity in consequence of my preference for Nile water. As
            to that, though, they scorn all heretics, _i.e._, all Christians but themselves and the
            Abyssinians, more than they do the Muslims, and dislike them more; the procession of the
            Holy Ghost question divides us with the Gulf of Jehannum. The gardener of this house is
            a Copt, such a nice fellow, and he and Omar chaff one another about religion with the
            utmost good humour; indeed they are seldom touchy with the Moslems. There is a pretty
            little man called Michaïl, a Copt, vakeel to M. Mounier. I wish I could draw him to show
            a perfect specimen of the ancient Egyptian race; his blood must be quite unmixed. He
            came here yesterday to speak to Ali Bey, the Moudir of Keneh, who was visiting me (a
            splendid handsome Turk he is); so little Michaïl crept in to mention his business under
            my protection, and a few more followed, till Ali Bey got tired of holding a durbar in my
            divan and went away to his boat. You see the people think the _courbash_ is not quite so
            handy with an English spectator. The other day Mustapha A’gha got Ali Bey to do a little
            job for him—to let the people in the Gezeereh (the island), which is Mustapha’s
            property, work at a canal there instead of at the canal higher up for the Pasha. Very
            well, but down comes the Nazir (the Moudir’s _sub_.), and courbashes the whole Gezeereh,
            not Mustapha, of course, but the poor _fellaheen_ who were doing his corvée instead of
            the Pasha’s by the Moudir’s order. I went to the Gezeereh and thought that Moses was at
            work again and had killed a firstborn in every house by the crying and wailing, when up
            came two fellows and showed me their bloody feet, which their wives were crying over
            like for a death, _Shorghl el Mizr_—things of Egypt—like _Cosas de España_. </p>
         <p> _Wednesday_.—Last night I bored Sheykh Yussuf with Antara and Abou-Zeyd, maintaining
            the greater valour of Antara who slew 10,000 for the love of Ibla; you know Antara.
            Yussuf looks down on such profanities, and replied, ‘What are Antara and Abou-Zeyd
            compared to the combats of our Lord Moses with Og and other infidels of might, and what
            is the love of Antara for Ibla compared to that of our Lord Solomon for Balkees (Queen
            of Sheba), or their beauty and attractiveness to that of our Lord Joseph?’ And then he
            related the combat of _Seyyidna Mousa_ with Og; and I thought, ‘hear O ye Puritans, and
            give ear O ye Methodists, and learn how religion and romance are one to those whose
            manners and ideas are the manners and ideas of the Bible, and how Moses was not at all a
            crop-eared Puritan, but a gallant warrior!’ There is the Homeric element in the religion
            here, the Prophet is a hero like Achilles, and like him directed by God—Allah instead of
            Athene. He fights, prays, teaches, makes love, and is truly a _man_, not an abstraction;
            and as to wonderful events, instead of telling one to ‘gulp them down without looking’
            (as children are told with a nasty dose, and as we are told about Genesis, etc.) they
            believe them and delight in them, and tell them to amuse people. Such a piece of
            deep-disguised scepticism as _Credo quia impossibile_ would find no favour here; ‘What
            is impossible to God?’ settles everything. In short, Mohammed has somehow left the stamp
            of romance on the religion, or else it is in the blood of the people, though the Koran
            is prosy and ‘common-sensical’ compared to the Old Testament. I used to think Arabs
            intensely prosaic till I could understand a little of their language, but now I can
            trace the genealogy of Don Quixote straight up to some Sheykh-el-Arab. </p>
         <p> A fine, handsome woman with a lovely baby came to me the other day. I played with the
            baby, and gave it a cotton handkerchief for its head. The woman came again yesterday to
            bring me a little milk and some salad as a present, and to tell my fortune with date
            stones. I laughed, and so she contented herself with telling Omar about his family,
            which he believed implicitly. She is a clever woman evidently, and a great sibyl here.
            No doubt she has faith in her own predictions. She told Mme. Mounier (who is a
            Levantine) that she would never have a child, and was forbidden the house accordingly,
            and the prophecy has ‘come true.’ Superstition is wonderfully infectious here. The fact
            is that the Arabs are so intensely impressionable, and so cowardly about inspiring any
            ill-will, that if a man looks askance at them it is enough to make them ill, and as
            calamities are not infrequent, there is always some mishap ready to be laid to the
            charge of somebody’s ‘eye.’ Omar would fain have had me say nothing about the theft of
            my purse, for fear the Karnac people should hate me and give me the eye. A part of the
            boasting about property, etc., is politeness, so that one may not be supposed to be
            envious of one’s neighbours’ nice things. My Sakka (water carrier) admired my bracelet
            yesterday, as he was watering the verandah floor, and instantly told me of all the gold
            necklaces and earrings he had bought for his wife and daughters, that I might not be
            uneasy and fear his envious eye. He is such a good fellow. For two shillings a month he
            brings up eight or ten huge skins of water from the river a day, and never begs or
            complains, always merry and civil. I shall enlarge his backsheesh. There are a lot of
            camels who sleep in the yard under my verandah; they are pretty and smell nice, but they
            growl and swear at night abominably. I wish I could draw you an Egyptian farm-yard, men,
            women and cattle; but what no one can draw is the amber light, so brilliant and so soft,
            not like the Cape diamond sunshine at all, but equally beautiful, hotter and less
            dazzling. There is no glare in Egypt like in the South of France, and, I suppose, in
            Italy. </p>
         <p> _Thursday_.—I went yesterday afternoon to the island again to see the crops, and show
            Sally my friend farmer Omar’s house and Mustapha’s village. Of course we had to eat, and
            did not come home till the moon had long risen. Mustapha’s brother Abdurachman walked
            about with us, such a noble-looking man, tall, spare, dignified and active, grey-bearded
            and hard-featured, but as lithe and bright-eyed as a boy, scorning any conveyance but
            his own feet, and quite dry while we ‘ran down.’ He was like Boaz, the wealthy gentleman
            peasant—nothing except the Biblical characters gave any idea of the rich _fellah_. We
            sat and drank new milk in a ‘lodge in a garden of cucumbers’ (the ‘lodge’ is a neat hut
            of palm branches), and saw the moon rise over the mountains and light up everything like
            a softer sun. Here you see all colours as well by moonlight as by day; hence it does not
            look as brilliant as the Cape moon, or even as I have seen in Paris, where it throws
            sharp black shadows and white light. The night here is a tender, subdued, dreamy sort of
            enchanted-looking day. My Turkish acquaintance from Karnac has just been here; he
            boasted of his house in Damascus, and invited me to go with him after the harvest here,
            also of his beautiful wife in Syria, and then begged me not to mention her to his wives
            here. </p>
         <p> It is very hot now; what will it be in June? It is now 86° in my shady room at noon; it
            will be hotter at two or three. But the mornings and evenings are delicious. I am
            shedding my clothes by degrees; stockings are unbearable. Meanwhile my cough is almost
            gone, and the pain is quite gone. I feel much stronger, too; the horrible feeling of
            exhaustion has left me; I suppose I must have salamander blood in my body to be made
            lively by such heat. Sally is quite well; she does not seem at all the worse at present. </p>
         <p> _Saturday_.—This will go to-morrow by some travellers, the last winter swallows. We
            went together yesterday to the Tombs of the Kings on the opposite bank. The mountains
            were red-hot, and the sun went down into Amenti all on fire. We met Mr. Dümmichen, the
            German, who is living in the temple of Dayr el-Bahree, translating inscriptions, and
            went down Belzoni’s tomb. Mr. Dümmichen translated a great many things for us which were
            very curious, and I think I was more struck with the beauty of the drawing of the
            figures than last year. The face of the Goddess of the Western shore, Amenti, Athor, or
            Hecate, is ravishing as she welcomes the King to her regions; death was never painted so
            lovely. The road is a long and most wild one—truly through the valley of the shadow of
            death—not an insect nor a bird. Our moonlight ride home was beyond belief beautiful. The
            Arabs who followed us were immensely amused at hearing me interpret between German and
            English, and at my speaking Arabic; they asked if I was dragoman of all the languages in
            the world. One of them had droll theories about ‘Amellica’ (America), as they pronounce
            it always. Was the King very powerful that the country was called ‘_Al Melekeh_’ (the
            Kings)? I said, ‘No: all are Kings there: you would be a King like the rest.’ My friend
            disapproved utterly: ‘If all are Kings they must all be taking away every man the
            other’s money’—a delightful idea of the kingly vocation. </p>
         <p> When we landed on the opposite shore, I told little Achmet to go back in the
            ferry-boat, in which he had brought me over my donkey; a quarter of an hour after I saw
            him by my side. The guide asked why he had not gone as I told him. ‘Who would take care
            of the lady?’ the monkey is Rainie’s size. Of course he got tired, and on the way home I
            told him to jump up behind me _en croupe_ after the Fellah fashion. I thought the Arabs
            would never have done laughing and saying _Wallah_ and _Mashallah_. Sheykh Yussuf talked
            about the excavations, and is shocked at the way the mummies are kicked about. One boy
            told him they were not Muslims as an excuse, and he rebuked him severely, and told him
            it was _haraam_ (accursed) to do so to the children of Adam. He says they have learned
            it very much of Mariette Bey, but I suspect it was always so with the fellaheen. To-day
            a tremendous wind is blowing; excellent for the corn. At Mustapha’s farm they are
            preparing for the harvest, baking bread and selecting a young bull to be killed for the
            reapers. It is not hot to-day; only 84° in a cool room. The dust is horrid with this
            high wind; everything is gritty, and it obscures the sun. I am desired to eat a raw
            onion every day during the Khamseen for health and prosperity. This too must be a
            remnant of ancient Egypt. How I do long to see you and the children. Sometimes I feel
            rather down-hearted, but it is no good to say all that. And I am much better and
            stronger. I stood a long ride and some scrambling quite well last evening.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>