<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, ALEXANDRIA, October 19, 1863.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/15">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/361058">Alexandria</settlement>
               <date when="1863-10-19">19 October 1863</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff Gordon</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>We had a wretched voyage, good weather, but such a _pétaudière_ of a ship. I am
            competent to describe the horrors of the middle passage—hunger, suffocation, dirt, and
            such _canaille_, high and low, on board. The only gentleman was a poor Moor going to
            Mecca (who stowed his wife and family in a spare boiler on deck). I saw him washing his
            children in the morning! ‘_Que c’est degoutant_!’ was the cry of the French spectators.
            If an Arab washes he is a _sale cochon_—no wonder! A delicious man who sat near me on
            deck, when the sun came round to our side, growled between his clenched teeth: ‘_Voilà
            un tas d’intrigants a l’ombre tandis que le soleil me grille, moi_,’ a good resume of
            French politics, methinks. Well, on arriving at noon of Friday, I was consoled for all
            by seeing Janet in a boat looking as fresh and bright and merry as ever she could look.
            The heat has evidently not hurt her at all. Omar’s joy was intense. He has had an offer
            of a place as messenger with the mails to Suez and back, £60 a year; and also his
            brother wanted him for Lady Herbert of Lea, who has engaged Hajjee Ali, and Ali promised
            high pay, but Omar said that he could not leave me. ‘I think my God give her to me to
            take care of her, how then I leave her if she not well and not very rich? I can’t speak
            to my God if I do bad things like that.’ I am going to his house to-day to see the baby
            and Hajjee Hannah, who is just come down from <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>.
            Omar is gone to try to get a dahabieh to go up the river, as I hear that the
            half-railway, half-steamer journey is dreadfully inconvenient and fatiguing, and the
            sight of the overflowing Nile is said to be magnificent, it is all over the land and
            eight miles of the railway gone. Omar kisses your hand and is charmed with the knife,
            but far more that my family should know his name and be satisfied with my servant.</p>

         <p>I cannot live in Thayer’s house because the march of civilization has led a party of
            French and Wallachian women into the ground-floor thereof to instruct the ignorant Arabs
            in drinking, card-playing, and other vices. So I will consult Hajjee Hannah to-day; she
            may know of an empty house and would make divan cushions for me. Zeyneb is much grown
            and very active and intelligent, but a little louder and bolder than she was owing to
            the maids here wanting to christianize her, and taking her out unveiled, and letting her
            be among the men. However, she is as affectionate as ever, and delighted at the prospect
            of going with me. I have replaced the veil, and Sally has checked her tongue and scolded
            her sister Ellen for want of decorum, to the amazement of the latter. Janet has a
            darling Nubian boy. Oh dear! what an elegant person Omar seemed after the French
            ‘gentleman,’ and how noble was old Hamees’s (Janet’s doorkeeper) paternal but
            reverential blessing! It is a real comfort to live in a nation of truly well-bred people
            and to encounter kindness after the savage incivility of France.</p>

         <p>Tuesday, October 20.</p>

         <p>Omar has got a boat for £13, which is not more than the railway would cost now that half
            must be done by steamer and a bit on donkeys or on foot. Poor Hajjee Hannah was quite
            knocked up by the journey down; I shall take her up in my boat. Two and a half hours to
            sit grilling at noonday on the banks, and two miles to walk carrying one’s own baggage
            is hard lines for a fat old woman. Everything is almost double in price owing to the
            cattle murrain and the high Nile. Such an inundation as this year was never known
            before. Does the blue God resent Speke’s intrusion on his privacy? It will be a glorious
            sight, but the damage to crops, and even to the last year’s stacks of grain and beans,
            is frightful. One sails among the palm-trees and over the submerged cotton-fields.
            Ismail Pasha has been very active, but, alas! his ‘eye is bad,’ and there have been as
            many calamities as under Pharaoh in his short reign. The cattle murrain is fearful, and
            is now beginning in <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> and Upper Egypt. Ross
            reckons the loss at twelve millions sterling in cattle. The gazelles in the desert have
            it too, but not horses, asses or goats.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>