<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Mrs. Austin, MASR EL-KAHIRA, CAIRO, May 21, 1863.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/13">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/360630">Cairo</settlement>
               <date when="1863-05-21">21 May 1863</date>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/59830344">Sarah Austin</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST MUTTER,</p>

         <p>I came here on Saturday night. To-day is Wednesday, and I am already much better. I have
            attached an excellent donkey and his master, a delightful youth called Hassan, to my
            household for fifteen piastres (under two shillings) a day. They live at the door, and
            Hassan cleans the stairs and goes errands during the heat of the day, and I ride out
            very early, at six or seven, and again at five. The air is delicious now. It is very hot
            for a few hours, but not stifling, and the breeze does not chill one as it does at
            Alexandria. I live all day and all night with open windows, and plenty of fresh warm air
            is the best of remedies. I can do no better than stay here till the heat becomes too
            great. I left little Zeyneb at Alexandria with Janet’s maid Ellen who quite loves her,
            and begged to keep her ‘for company,’ and also to help in their removal to the new
            house. She clung about me and made me promise to come back to her, but was content to
            stop with Ellen, whose affection she of course returns. It was pleasant to see her so
            happy, and how she relished being ‘put to bed’ with a kiss by Ellen or Sally. Her
            Turkish master, whom she pronounces to have been _batal_ (bad), called her Salaam
            es-Sidi (the Peace of her Master); but she said that in her own village she used to be
            Zeyneb, and so we call her. She has grown fatter and, if possible, blacker. Mahbrooka
            (Good Fortune), the elder wife of Hegab, the confectioner, was much interested in her,
            as her fate had been the same. She was bought by an Italian who lived with her till his
            death, when she married Hegab. She is a pious Muslimeh, and invoked the intercession of
            Seyidna Mohammad for me when I told her I had no intention of baptizing Zeyneb by force,
            as had been done to her.</p>

         <p>The fault of my lodging here is the noise. We are on the road from the railway and there
            is no quiet except in the few hot hours, when nothing is heard but the cool tinkle of
            the Sakka’s brass cup as he sells water in the street, or perchance _erksoos_
            (liquorice-water), or caroub or raisin sherbet. The _erksoos_ is rather bitter and very
            good. I drink it a good deal, for drink one must; a gulleh of water is soon gone. A
            gulleh is a wide-mouthed porous jar, and Nile water drunk out of it without the
            intervention of a glass is delicious. Omar goes to market every morning with a donkey—I
            went too, and was much amused—and cooks, and in the evening goes out with me if I want
            him. I told him I had recommended him highly, and hoped he would get good employment;
            but he declares that he will go with no one else so long as I come to Egypt, whatever
            the difference of wages may be. ‘The bread I eat with you is sweet’—a pretty little
            unconscious antithesis to Dante. I have been advising his brother Hajjee Ali to start a
            hotel at Thebes for invalids, and he has already set about getting a house there; there
            is _one_. Next winter there will be steamers twice a week—to Assouan! Juvenal’s distant
            Syene, where he died in banishment. My old washerwoman sent me a fervent entreaty
            through Omar that I would dine with her one day, since I had made <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> delightful with my presence. If one will only devour these
            people’s food, they are enchanted; they like that much better than a present. So I will
            honour her house some day. Good old Hannah, she is divorced for being too fat and old,
            and replaced by a young Turk whose family sponge on Hajjee Ali and are condescending. If
            I could afford it, I would have a sketch of a beloved old mosque of mine, falling to
            decay, and with three palm-trees growing in the middle of it. Indeed, I would have a
            book full, for all is exquisite, and alas, all is going. The old Copt quarter is
            _entamé_, and hideous, shabby French houses, like the one I live in, are being run up;
            and in this weather how much better would be the Arab courtyard, with its mastabah and
            fountain!</p>

         <p> There is a quarrel now in the street; how they talk and gesticulate, and everybody puts
            in a word; a boy has upset a cake-seller’s tray, ‘_Naal Abu’k_!’ (Curses on your father)
            he claims six piastres damages, and everyone gives an opinion _pour ou contre_. We all
            look out of the window; my opposite neighbour, the pretty Armenian woman, leans out, and
            her diamond head-ornaments and earrings glitter as she laughs like a child. The
            Christian dyer is also very active in the row, which, like all Arab rows, ends in
            nothing; it evaporates in fine theatrical gestures and lots of talk. Curious! In the
            street they are so noisy, but get the same men in a coffee-shop or anywhere, and they
            are the quietest of mankind. Only one man speaks at a time, the rest listen, and never
            interrupt; twenty men don’t make the noise of three Europeans.</p>

         <p>Hekekian Bey is my near neighbour, and he comes in and we _fronder_ the Government. His
            heart is sore with disinterested grief for the sufferings of the people. ‘Don’t they
            deserve to be decently governed, to be allowed a little happiness and prosperity? They
            are so docile, so contented; are they not a good people?’ Those were his words as he was
            recounting some new iniquity. Of course half these acts are done under pretext of
            improving and civilizing, and the Europeans applaud and say, ‘Oh, but nothing could be
            done without forced labour,’ and the poor Fellaheen are marched off in gangs like
            convicts, and their families starve, and (who’d have thought it) the population keeps
            diminishing. No wonder the cry is, ‘Let the English Queen come and take us.’ You see, I
            don’t see things quite as Ross does, but mine is another _standpunkt_, and my heart is
            with the Arabs. I care less about opening up the trade with the Soudan and all the new
            railways, and I should like to see person and property safe, which no one’s is here
            (Europeans, of course, excepted). Ismail Pasha got the Sultan to allow him to take
            90,000 feddans of uncultivated land for himself as private property, very well, but the
            late Viceroy Said granted eight years ago certain uncultivated lands to a good many
            Turks, his _employés_, in hopes of founding a landed aristocracy and inducing them to
            spend their capital in cultivation. They did so, and now Ismail Pasha takes their
            improved land and gives them feddan for feddan of his new land, which will take five
            years to bring into cultivation, instead. He forces them to sign a _voluntary_ deed of
            exchange, or they go off to Fazogloo, a hot Siberia whence none return. The Sultan also
            left a large sum of money for religious institutions and charities—Muslim, Jew, and
            Christian. None have received a foddah. It is true the Sultan and his suite plundered
            the Pasha and the people here; but from all I hear the Sultan really wishes to do good.
            What is wanted here is hands to till the ground, and wages are very high; food, of
            course, gets dearer, and the forced labour inflicts more suffering than before, and the
            population will decrease yet faster. This appears to me to be a state of things in which
            it is no use to say that public works must be made at any cost. The wealth will perhaps
            be increased, if meanwhile the people are not exterminated. Then, every new Pasha builds
            a huge new palace while those of his predecessors fall to ruin. Mehemet Ali’s sons even
            cut down the trees of his beautiful botanical garden and planted beans there; so money
            is constantly wasted more than if it were thrown into the Nile, for then the Fellaheen
            would not have to spend their time, so much wanted for agriculture, in building hideous
            barrack-like so-called palaces. What chokes me is to hear English people talk of the
            stick being ‘the only way to manage Arabs’ as if anyone could doubt that it is the
            easiest way to manage any people where it can be used with impunity.</p>

         <p>_Sunday_.—I went to a large unfinished new Coptic church this morning. Omar went with me
            up to the women’s gallery, and was discreetly going back when he saw me in the right
            place, but the Coptic women began to talk to him and asked questions about me all the
            time I was looking down on the strange scene below. I believe they celebrate the ancient
            mysteries still. The clashing of cymbals, the chanting, a humming unlike any sound I
            ever heard, the strange yellow copes covered with stranger devices—it was _wunderlich_.
            At the end everyone went away, and I went down and took off my shoes to go and look at
            the church. While I was doing so a side-door opened and a procession entered. A priest
            dressed in the usual black robe and turban of all Copts carrying a trident-shaped sort
            of candlestick, another with cymbals, a lot of little boys, and two young ecclesiastics
            of some sort in the yellow satin copes (contrasting queerly with the familiar tarboosh
            of common life on their heads), these carried little babies and huge wax tapers, each a
            baby and a taper. They marched round and round three times, the cymbals going furiously,
            and chanting a jig tune. The dear little tiny boys marched just in front of the priest
            with such a pretty little solemn, consequential air. Then they all stopped in front of
            the sanctuary, and the priest untied a sort of broad-coloured tape which was round each
            of the babies, reciting something in Coptic all the time, and finally touched their
            foreheads and hands with water. This is a ceremony subsequent to baptism after I don’t
            know how many days, but the priest ties and then unties the bands. Of what is this
            symbolical? _Je m’y perds_. Then an old man gave a little round cake of bread, with a
            cabalistic-looking pattern on it, both to Omar and to me, which was certainly baked for
            Isis. A lot of closely-veiled women stood on one side in the aisle, and among them the
            mothers of the babies who received them from the men in yellow copes at the end of the
            ceremony. One of these young men was very handsome, and as he stood looking down and
            smiling on the baby he held, with the light of the torch sharpening the lines of his
            features, would have made a lovely picture. The expression was sweeter than St. Vincent
            de Paul, because his smile told that he could have played with the baby as well as have
            prayed for it. In this country one gets to see how much more beautiful a perfectly
            natural expression is than any degree of the mystical expression of the best painters,
            and it is so refreshing that no one tries to look pious. The Muslim looks serious, and
            often warlike, as he stands at prayer. The Christian just keeps his everyday face. When
            the Muslim gets into a state of devotional frenzy he does not think of making a face,
            and it is quite tremendous. I don’t think the Copt has any such ardours, but the scene
            this morning was all the more touching that no one was ‘behaving him or herself’ at all.
            A little acolyte peeped into the sacramental cup and swigged off the drops left in it
            with the most innocent air, and no one rebuked him, and the quite little children ran
            about in the sanctuary—up to seven they are privileged—and only they and the priests
            enter it. It is a pretty commentary on the words ‘Suffer the little children,’ etc.</p>

         <p>I am more and more annoyed at not being able to ask questions for myself, as I don’t
            like to ask through a Muslim and no Copts speak any foreign language, or very very few.
            Omar and Hassan had been at five this morning to the tomb of Sittina Zeyneb, one of the
            daughters of the Prophet, to ‘see her’ (Sunday is her day of reception), and say the
            Fathah at her tomb. Next Friday the great Bairam begins and every Muslim eats a bit of
            meat at his richer neighbour’s expense. It is the day on which the pilgrims go up the
            sacred mount near Mecca, to hear the sermon which terminates the Haj. Yesterday I went
            to call on pretty Mrs. Wilkinson, she is an Armenian of the Greek faith, and was gone to
            pray at the convent of Mar Girgis (St. George) to cure the pains a bad rheumatic fever
            has left in her hands. Evidently Mar Girgis is simply Ammon Ra, the God of the Sun and
            great serpent-slayer, who is still revered in Egypt by all sects, and Seyd el-Bedawee is
            as certainly one form of Osiris. His festivals, held twice a year at Tanta, still
            display the symbol of the Creator of all things. All is thus here—the women wail the
            dead, as on the old sculptures, all the ceremonies are pagan, and would shock an Indian
            Mussulman as much as his objection to eat with a Christian shocks an Arab. This country
            is a palimpsest, in which the Bible is written over Herodotus, and the Koran over that.
            In the towns the Koran is most visible, in the country Herodotus. I fancy it is most
            marked and most curious among the Copts, whose churches are shaped like the ancient
            temples, but they are so much less accessible than the Arabs that I know less of their
            customs.</p>

         <p>Now I have filled such a long letter I hardly know if it is worth sending, and whether
            you will be amused by my commonplaces of Eastern life. I kill a sheep next Friday, and
            Omar will cook a stupendous dish for the poor Fellaheen who are lying about the
            railway-station, waiting to be taken to work somewhere. That is to be my Bairam, and
            Omar hopes for great benefit for me from the process.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>