<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>May 15, 1864: Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, LUXOR, May 15, 1864, Day before
               Eed-el-Kebir (Bairam).</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK, </p>
         <p> We returned to Luxor the evening before last just after dark. The salute which Omar
            fired with your old horse-pistols brought down a lot of people, and there was a chorus
            of _Alhamdulilah Salaameh ya Sitt_, and such a kissing of hands, and ‘Welcome home to
            your place’ and ‘We have tasted your absence and found it bitter,’ etc., etc. Mustapha
            came with letters for me, and Yussuf beaming with smiles, and Mahommed with new bread
            made of new wheat, and Suleyman with flowers, and little Achmet rushing in wildly to
            kiss hands. When the welcome had subsided, Yussuf, who stayed to tea, told me all the
            cattle were dead. Mustapha lost thirty-four, and has three left; and poor farmer Omar
            lost all—forty head. The distress in Upper Egypt will now be fearful. Within six weeks
            _all_ our cattle are dead. They are threshing the corn with donkeys, and men are turning
            the sakiahs (water-wheels) and drawing the ploughs, and dying by scores of overwork and
            want of food in many places. The whole agriculture depended on the oxen, and they are
            all dead. At El-Moutaneh and the nine villages round Halim Pasha’s estate 24,000 head
            have died; four beasts were left when we were there three days ago. </p>
         <p> We spent two days and nights at Philæ and _Wallahy_! it was hot. The basalt rocks which
            enclose the river all round the island were burning. Sally and I slept in the Osiris
            chamber, on the roof of the temple, on our air-beds. Omar lay across the doorway to
            guard us, and Arthur and his Copt, with the well-bred sailor Ramadan, were sent to
            bivouac on the Pylon. Ramadan took the hareem under his special and most respectful
            charge, and waited on us devotedly, but never raised his eyes to our faces, or spoke
            till spoken to. Philæ is six or seven miles from Assouan, and we went on donkeys through
            the beautiful Shellaleeh (the village of the cataract), and the noble place of tombs of
            Assouan. Great was the amazement of everyone at seeing Europeans so out of season; we
            were like swallows in January to them. I could not sleep for the heat in the room, and
            threw on an _abbayeh_ (cloak) and went and lay on the parapet of the temple. What a
            night! What a lovely view! The stars gave as much light as the moon in Europe, and all
            but the cataract was still as death and glowing hot, and the palm-trees were more
            graceful and dreamy than ever. Then Omar woke, and came and sat at my feet, and rubbed
            them, and sang a song of a Turkish slave. I said, ‘Do not rub my feet, oh brother—that
            is not fit for thee’ (because it is below the dignity of a free Muslim altogether to
            touch shoes or feet), but he sang in his song, ‘The slave of the Turk may be set free by
            money, but how shall one be ransomed who has been paid for by kind actions and sweet
            words?’ Then the day broke deep crimson, and I went down and bathed in the Nile, and saw
            the girls on the island opposite in their summer fashions, consisting of a leathern
            fringe round their slender hips—divinely graceful—bearing huge saucer-shaped baskets of
            corn on their stately young heads; and I went up and sat at the end of the colonnade
            looking up into Ethiopia, and dreamed dreams of ‘Him who sleeps in Philæ,’ until the
            great Amun Ra kissed my northern face too hotly, and drove me into the temple to
            breakfast, and coffee, and pipes, and _kief_. And in the evening three little naked
            Nubians rowed us about for two or three hours on the glorious river in a boat made of
            thousands of bits of wood, each a foot long; and between whiles they jumped overboard
            and disappeared, and came up on the other side of the boat. Assouan was full of Turkish
            soldiers, who came and took away our donkeys, and stared at our faces most
            irreligiously. I did not go on shore at Kom Ombos or El Kab, only at Edfou, where we
            spent the day in the temple; and at Esneh, where we tried to buy sugar, tobacco, etc.,
            and found nothing at all, though Esneh is a _chef-lieu_, with a Moudir. It is only in
            winter that anything is to be got for the travellers. We had to ask the Nazir in Edfou
            to _order_ a man to sell us charcoal. People do without sugar, and smoke green tobacco,
            and eat beans, etc., etc. Soon we must do likewise, for our stores are nearly exhausted. </p>
         <p> We stopped at El-Moutaneh, and had a good dinner in the Mouniers’ handsome house, and
            they gave me a loaf of sugar. Mme. Mounier described Rachel’s stay with them for three
            months at Luxor, in my house, where they then lived. She hated it so, that on embarking
            to leave she turned back and spat on the ground, and cursed the place inhabited by
            savages, where she had been _ennuyée a mort_. Mme. Mounier fully sympathized with her,
            and thought no _femme aimable_ could live with Arabs, who are not at all _galants_. She
            is Levantine, and, I believe, half Arab herself, but hates the life here, and hates the
            Muslims. As I write this I laugh to think of _galanterie_ and _Arab_ in one sentence,
            and glance at ‘my brother’ Yussuf, who is sleeping on a mat, quite overcome with the
            Simoom (which is blowing) and the fast which he is keeping to-day, as the eve of the
            _Eed-el-Kebir_ (great festival). This is the coolest place in the village. The glass is
            only 95½° now (eleven a.m.) in the darkened divan. The Kádee, and the Maōhn, and Yussuf
            came together to visit me, and when the others left he lay down to sleep. Omar is
            sleeping in the passage, and Sally in her room. I alone don’t sleep—but the Simoom is
            terrible. Arthur runs about all day, sight-seeing and drawing, and does not suffer at
            all from the heat. I can’t walk now, as the sand blisters my feet. </p>
         <p> _Tuesday_, _May_ 17.—Yesterday the Simoom was awful, and last night I slept on the
            terrace, and was very hot. To-day the north wind sprang up at noon and revived us,
            though it is still 102° in my divan. My old ‘great-grandfather’ has come in for a pipe
            and coffee; he was Belzoni’s guide, and his eldest child was born seven days before the
            French under Bonaparte marched into Luxor. He is superbly handsome and erect, and very
            talkative, but only remembers old times, and takes me for Mme. Belzoni. He is
            grandfather to Mahommed, the guard of this house, and great-grandfather to my little
            Achmet. His grandsons have married him to a tidy old woman to take care of him; he calls
            me ‘My lady grand-daughter,’ and Omar he calls ‘Mustapha,’ and we salute him as
            ‘grandfather.’ I wish I could paint him; he is so grand to look at. Old Mustapha had a
            son born yesterday—his tenth child. I must go and wish him joy, after which I will go to
            Arthur’s boat and have a bathe; the sailors rig me out a capital awning. We had a good
            boat, and a capital crew; one man Mahommed, called Alatee (the singer), sang
            beautifully, to my great delight, and all were excellent fellows, quiet and obliging;
            only his servant was a lazy beast, dirty and conceited—a Copt, spoiled by an Italian
            education and Greek associates, thinking himself very grand because he was a Christian.
            I wondered at the patience and good-nature with which Omar did all his work and endured
            all his insolence. There was one stupendous row at Assouan, however. The men had rigged
            out a sort of tent for me to bathe in over the side of the boat, and Ramadan caught the
            Copt trying to peep in, and half strangled him. Omar called him ‘dog,’ and asked him if
            he was an infidel, and Macarius told him I was a Christian woman, and not _his Hareem_.
            Omar lost his temper, and appealed to the old reis and all the sailors, ‘O Muslims,
            ought not I to cut his throat if he had defiled the noble person of the lady with his
            pig’s eyes? God forgive me for mentioning her in such a manner.’ Then they all cursed
            him for a pig and an infidel, and threatened to put him ashore and leave him for his
            vile conduct towards noble _Hareem_. Omar sobbed with passion, saying that I was to him
            like the ‘back of his mother,’ and how ‘dare Macarius take my name in his dirty mouth,’
            etc. The Copt tried to complain of being beaten afterwards, but I signified to him that
            he had better hold his tongue, for that I understood Arabic, upon which he sneaked
            off.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>