<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>May 12, 1863: To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, ALEXANDRIA, May 12, 1863.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK,</p>

         <p>I only got your letter an hour ago, and the mail goes out at four. I enclose to you the
            letter I had written to my mother, so I need not repeat about my plans. Continue to
            write here, a letter comes as soon and safer. My general health is so much stronger and
            better—especially before I had this last severe attack—that I still hope, though it is a
            severe trial of patience not to throw it up and come home for good. It would be
            delightful to have you at <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> now I have pots and
            pans and all needful for a house, but a carpet and a few mattresses, if you could camp
            with me _à l’Arabe_.</p>

         <p>How you would revel in old Masr el-Kahira, peep up at lattice windows, gape like a
            _gasheem_ (green one) in the bazaar, go wild over the mosques, laugh at portly Turks and
            dignified Sheykhs on their white donkeys, drink sherbet in the streets, ride wildly
            about on a donkey, peer under black veils at beautiful eyes and feel generally
            intoxicated! I am quite a good cicerone now of the glorious old city. Omar is in
            raptures at the idea that the Sidi el Kebir (the Great Master) might come, and still
            more if he brought the ‘little master.’ He plans meeting you on the steamboat and
            bringing you to me, that I may kiss your hand first of all. Mashallah! How our hearts
            would be dilated!</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>