<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>April 6, 1864: To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, LUXOR, April 6, 1864.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK, </p>
         <p> I received yours of March 10 two days ago; also one from Hekekian Bey, much advising me
            to stay here the summer and get my disease ‘evaporated.’ Since I last wrote the great
            heat abated, and we now have 76° to 80°, with strong north breezes up the river—glorious
            weather—neither too hot nor chilly at any time. Last evening I went out to the
            threshing-floor to see the stately oxen treading out the corn, and supped there with
            Abdurachman on roasted corn, sour cream, and eggs, and saw the reapers take their wages,
            each a bundle of wheat according to the work he had done—the most lovely sight. The
            graceful, half-naked, brown figures loaded with sheaves; some had earned so much that
            their mothers or wives had to help to carry it, and little fawn-like, stark-naked boys
            trudged off, so proud of their little bundles of wheat or of _hummuz_ (a sort of vetch
            much eaten both green and roasted). The _sakka_ (water-carrier), who has brought water
            for the men, gets a handful from each, and drives home his donkey with empty waterskins
            and a heavy load of wheat, and the barber who has shaved all these brown heads on credit
            this year past gets his pay, and everyone is cheerful and happy in their gentle, quiet
            way; here is no beer to make men sweaty and noisy and vulgar; the harvest is the most
            exquisite pastoral you can conceive. The men work seven hours in the day (_i.e._, eight,
            with half-hours to rest and eat), and seven more during the night; they go home at
            sunset to dinner, and sleep a bit, and then to work again—these ‘lazy Arabs’! The man
            who drives the oxen on the threshing-floor gets a measure and a half for his day and
            night’s work, of threshed corn, I mean. As soon as the wheat, barley, _addas_ (lentils)
            and _hummuz_ are cut, we shall sow _dourrah_ of two kinds, common maize and Egyptian,
            and plant sugar-cane, and later cotton. The people work very hard, but here they eat
            well, and being paid in corn they get the advantage of the high price of corn this year. </p>
         <p> I told you how my purse had been stolen and the proceedings thereanent. Well, Mustapha
            asked me several times what I wished to be done with the thief, who spent twenty-one
            days here in irons. With my absurd English ideas of justice I refused to interfere at
            all, and Omar and I had quite a tiff because he wished me to say, ‘Oh, poor man, let him
            go; I leave the affair to God.’ I thought Omar absurd, but it was I who was wrong. The
            authorities concluded that it would oblige me very much if the poor devil were punished
            with a ‘rigour beyond the law,’ and had not Sheykh Yussuf come and explained the nature
            of the proceedings, the man would have been sent up to the mines in Fazogloo _for life_,
            out of civility to me, by the Moudir of Keneh, Ali Bey. There was no alternative between
            my ‘forgiving him for the love of God’ or sending him to a certain death by a climate
            insupportable to these people. Mustapha and Co. tried hard to prevent Sheykh Yussuf from
            speaking to me, for fear I should be angry and complain at <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>, if my vengeance were not wreaked on the thief, but he said he
            knew me better, and brought the _procès verbal_ to show me. Fancy my dismay! I went to
            Seleem Effendi and to the Kádee with Sheykh Yussuf, and begged the man might be let go,
            and not sent to Keneh at all. Having settled this, I said that I had thought it right
            that the people of Karnac should pay the money I had lost, as a fine for their bad
            conduct to strangers, but that I did not require it for the sake of the money, which I
            would accordingly give to the poor of Luxor in the mosque and in the church (great
            applause from the crowd). I asked how many were Muslimeen and how many Nazranee, in
            order to divide the three napoleons and a half, according to the numbers. Sheykh Yussuf
            awarded one napoleon to the church, two to the mosque, and the half to the
            water-drinking place—the _Sebeel_—which was also applauded. I then said, ‘Shall we send
            the money to the bishop?’ but a respectable elderly Copt said, ‘_Malcysh_! (never mind)
            better give it all to Sheykh Yussuf; he will send the bread to the church.’ Then the
            Cadi made me a fine speech, and said I had behaved like a great _Emeereh_, and one that
            feared God; and Sheykh Yussuf said he knew the English had mercy in their stomachs, and
            that I especially had Mussulman feelings (as we say, Christian charity). Did you ever
            hear of such a state of administration of justice. Of course, sympathy here, as in
            Ireland, is mostly with the ‘poor man’ in prison—‘in trouble,’ as we say. I find that
            accordingly a vast number of disputes are settled by private arbitration, and Yussuf is
            constantly sent for to decide between contending parties, who abide by his decision
            rather than go to law; or else five or six respectable men are called upon to form a
            sort of amateur jury, and to settle the matter. In criminal cases, if the prosecutor is
            powerful, he has it all his own way; if the prisoner can bribe high, he is apt to get
            off. All the appealing to my compassion was quite _en règle_. Another trait of Egypt. </p>
         <p> The other day we found all our water-jars empty and our house unsprinkled. On enquiry
            it turned out that the _sakkas_ had all run away, carrying with them their families and
            goods, and were gone no one knew whither, in consequence of some ‘persons having
            authority,’ one, a Turkish _cawass_ (policeman), having forced them to fetch water for
            building purposes at so low a price that they could not bear it. My poor _sakka_ is gone
            without a whole month’s pay—two shillings!—the highest pay by far given in Luxor. I am
            interested in another story. I hear that a plucky woman here has been to Keneh, and
            threatened the Moudir that she will go to <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> and
            complain to Effendina himself of the unfair drafting for soldiers—her only son taken,
            while others have bribed off. She’ll walk in this heat all the way, unless she succeeds
            in frightening the Moudir, which, as she is of the more spirited sex in this country,
            she may possibly do. You see these Saeedes are a bit less patient than Lower Egyptians.
            The _sakkas_ can strike, and a woman can face a Moudir. </p>
         <p> You would be amused at the bazaar here. There is a barber, and on Tuesdays some beads,
            calico, and tobacco are sold. The only artizan is—a jeweller! We spin and weave our own
            brown woollen garments, and have no other wants, but gold necklaces and nose and
            earrings are indispensable. It is the safest way of hoarding, and happily combines
            saving with ostentation. Can you imagine a house without beds, chairs, tables, cups,
            glasses, knives—in short, with nothing but an oven, a few pipkins and water-jars, and a
            couple of wooden spoons, and some mats to sleep on? And yet people are happy and quite
            civilized who live so. An Arab cook, with his fingers and one cooking-pot, will serve
            you an excellent dinner quite miraculously. The simplification of life possible in such
            a climate is not conceivable unless one has seen it. The Turkish ladies whom I visit at
            Karnac have very little more. They are very fond of me, and always want me to stay and
            sleep, but how could I sleep in my clothes on a mat-divan, poor spoiled European that I
            am? But they pity and wonder far more at the absence of my ‘master.’ I made a bad slip
            of the tongue and said ‘my husband’ before Abdul Rafiah, the master of the house. The
            ladies laughed and blushed tremendously, and I felt very awkward, but they turned the
            tables on me in a few minutes by some questions they asked quite coolly. </p>
         <p> I hardly know what I shall have to do. If the heat does not turn out overpowering, I
            shall stay here; if I cannot bear it, I must go down the river. I asked Omar if he could
            bear a summer here, so dull for a young man fond of a little coffee-shop and gossip, for
            that, if he could not, he might go down for a time and join me again, as I could manage
            with some man here. He absolutely cried, kissed my hands, and declared he was never so
            happy as with me, and he could not rest if he thought I had not all I wanted. ‘I am your
            _memlook_, not your servant—your _memlook_.’ I really believe that these people
            sometimes love their English masters better than their own people. Omar certainly has
            shown the greatest fondness for me on all occasions.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>