<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>October 26, 183: To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, ALEXANDRIA, October 26,
               1863.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK,</p>

         <p>I went to two hareems the other day with a little boy of Mustapha Aga’s, and was much
            pleased. A very pleasant Turkish lady put out all her splendid bedding and dresses for
            me, and was most amiable. At another a superb Arab with most _grande dame_ manners,
            dressed in white cotton and with unpainted face, received me statelily. Her house would
            drive you wild, such antique enamelled tiles covering the panels of the walls, all
            divided by carved woods, and such carved screens and galleries, all very old and rather
            dilapidated, but superb, and the lady worthy of the house. A bold-eyed slave girl with a
            baby put herself forward for admiration, and was ordered to bring coffee with such cool
            though polite imperiousness. One of our great ladies can’t half crush a rival in
            comparison, she does it too coarsely. The quiet scorn of the pale-faced, black-haired
            Arab was beyond any English powers. Then it was fun to open the lattice and make me look
            out on the square, and to wonder what the neighbours would say at the sight of my face
            and European hat. She asked about my children and blessed them repeatedly, and took my
            hand very kindly in doing so, for fear I should think her envious and fear her eye—she
            had none.</p>

         <p>_Tuesday_.—The post goes out to-morrow, and I have such a cold I must stay in bed and
            cannot write much. I go on Thursday and shall go to Briggs’ house. Pray write to me at
               <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>. Sally and I are both unwell and anxious to
            get up the river. I can’t write more. </p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>