<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>August 13, 1864: To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, LUXOR, August 13, 1864.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK, </p>
         <p> For the last month we have had a purgatory of hot wind and dust, such as I never
            saw—impossible to stir out of the house. So in despair I have just engaged a return
            boat—a _Gelegenheit_—and am off to <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> in a day or
            two, where I shall stop till _Inshallah_! you come to me. Can’t you get leave to come at
            the beginning of November? Do try, that is the pleasant time in <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>. </p>
         <p> I am a ‘stupid, lazy Arab’ now, as Omar says, having lain on a mat in a dark stone
            passage for six weeks or so, but my chest is no worse—better I think, and my health has
            not suffered at all—only I am stupid and lazy. I had a pleasant visit lately from a
            great doctor from Mecca—a man so learned that he can read the Koran in seven different
            ways, he is also a physician of European _Hekmeh_ (learning). Fancy my wonder when a
            great Alim in gorgeous Hegazee dress walked in and said: ‘_Madame, tout ce qu’on m’a dit
            de vous fait tellement l’éloge de votre cœur et de votre esprit que je me suis arreté
            pour tacher de me procurer le plaisir de votre connaissance_!’ A lot of Luxor people
            came in to pay their respects to the great man, and he said to me that he hoped I had
            not been molested on account of religion, and if I had I must forgive it, as the people
            here were so very ignorant, and _barbarians were bigots everywhere_. I said, ‘_Wallahy_,
            the people of Luxor are my brothers!’ and the Maōhn said, ‘True, the fellaheen are like
            oxen, but not such swine as to insult the religion of a lady who has served God among
            them like this one. She risked her life every day.’ ‘And if she _had_ died,’ said the
            great theologian, ‘her place was made ready among the martyrs of God, because she showed
            more love to her brothers than to herself!’ </p>
         <p> Now if this was humbug it was said in Arabic before eight or ten people, by a man of
            great religious authority. </p>
         <p> Omar was _aux anges_ to hear his Sitt spoken of ‘in such a grand way for the religion.’
            I believe that a great change is taking place among the Ulema, that Islam is ceasing to
            be a mere party flag, just as occurred with Christianity, and that all the moral part is
            being more and more dwelt on. My great Alim also said I had practised the precepts of
            the Koran, and then laughed and added, ‘I suppose I ought to say the Gospel, but what
            matters it, _el Hakh_ (the truth) is one, whether spoken by Our Lord Jesus or by Our
            Lord Mahommed!’ He asked me to go with him to Mecca next winter for my health, as it was
            so hot and dry there. I found he had fallen in with El-Bedrawee and the Khartoum
            merchant at Assouan. The little boy was well again, and I had been outrageously extolled
            by them. We are now sending off all the corn. I sat the other evening on Mustapha’s
            doorstep and saw the Greeks piously and zealously attending to the divine command to
            spoil the Egyptians. Eight months ago a Greek bought up corn at 60 piastres the ardeb
            (he follows the Coptic tax-gatherer like a vulture after a crow), now wheat is at 170
            piastres the ardeb here, and the fellah has paid 3½ _per cent. a month_ besides. Reckon
            the profit! Two men I know are quite ruined, and have sold all they had. The cattle
            disease forced them to borrow at these ruinous rates, and now alas, the Nile is sadly
            lingering in its rise, and people are very anxious. Poor Egypt! or rather, poor
            Egyptians! Of course, I need not say that there is great improvidence in those who can
            be fleeced as they are fleeced. Mustapha’s household is a pattern of muddling
            hospitality, and Mustapha is generous and mean by turns; but what chance have people
            like these, so utterly uncivilized and so isolated, against Europeans of unscrupulous
            characters. </p>
         <p> I can’t write more in the wind and dust. You shall hear again from <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>