<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>May 12, 1863: To Mrs. Austin, ALEXANDRIA, May 12, 1863.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST MUTTER,</p>

         <p>I have been here a fortnight, but the climate disagrees so much with me that I am going
            back to <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> at once by the advice of the doctor of
            the Suez Canal. I cannot shake off my cough here. Mr. Thayer kindly lends me his nice
            little bachelor house, and I take Omar back again for the job. It is very hot here, but
            with a sea-breeze which strikes me like ice; strong people enjoy it, but it gives even
            Janet cold in the head. She is very well, I think, and seems very happy. She is _Times_
            correspondent and does it very well.</p>

         <p>I am terribly disappointed at not being as materially better as I had hoped I should be
            while in Upper Egypt. I cannot express the longing I have for home and my children, and
            how much I feel the sort of suspense it all causes to you and to Alick, and my desire to
            be with you.</p>

         <p>One must come to the East to understand absolute equality. As there is no education and
            no reason why the donkey-boy who runs behind me may not become a great man, and as all
            Muslims are _ipso facto_ equal; money and rank are looked on as mere accidents, and my
            _savoir vivre_ was highly thought of because I sat down with Fellaheen and treated
            everyone as they treat each other. In Alexandria all that is changed. The European ideas
            and customs have extinguished the Arab altogether, and those who remain are not improved
            by the contact. Only the _Bedaween_ preserve their haughty _nonchalance_. I found the
            Mograbee bazaar full of them when I went to buy a white cloak, and was amused at the way
            in which one splendid bronze figure, who lay on the shop-front, moved one leg to let me
            sit down. They got interested in my purchase, and assisted in making the bargain and
            wrapping the cloak round me Bedawee fashion, and they too complimented me on having ‘the
            face of the Arab,’ which means Bedaween. I wanted a little Arab dress for Rainie, but
            could not find one, as at her age none are worn in the desert.</p>

         <p>I dined one day with Omar, or rather I ate at his house, for he would not eat with me.
            His sister-in-law cooked a most admirable dinner, and everyone was delighted. It was an
            interesting family circle. A very respectable elder brother a confectioner, whose elder
            wife was a black woman, a really remarkable person, who speaks Italian perfectly, and
            gave me a great deal of information and asked such intelligent questions. She ruled the
            house but had no children, so he had married a fair, gentle-looking Arab woman who had
            six children, and all lived in perfect harmony. Omar’s wife is a tall, handsome girl of
            his own age, with very good manners. She had been outside the door of the close little
            court which constituted the house _once_ since her marriage. I now begin to understand
            all about the _wesen_ with the women. There is a good deal of chivalry in some respects,
            and in the respectable lower and middle classes the result is not so bad. I suspect that
            among the rich few are very happy. But I don’t know them, or anything of the Turkish
            ways. I will go and see the black woman again and hear more, her conversation was really
            interesting.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>