<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Mrs. Austin, OFF BOULAK, September 21, 1886.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/85">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <date when="1866-09-21">21 September 1866</date>
               <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/360630">Cairo</settlement>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/59830344">Sarah Austin</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST MUTTER, </p>
         <p> I am a good deal better again; the weather is delightful, and the Nile in full flood,
            which makes the river scenery from the boat very beautiful. Alick made my mouth water
            with his descriptions of his rides with Janet about the dear old Surrey country, having
            her with him seems to have quite set him up. I have seen nothing and nobody but my ‘next
            boat’ neighbour, Goodah Effendi, as Omar has been at work all day in the boat, and I
            felt lazy and disinclined to go out alone. Big Hassan of the donkeys has grown too lazy
            to go about and I don’t care to go alone with a small boy here. However I am out in the
            best of air all day and am very well off. My two little boys are very diverting and
            serve me very well. The news from Europe is to my ignorant ideas _désolant_, a
            _dégringolade back_ into military despotism, which would have excited indignation with
            us in our fathers’ days, I think. I get lots of newspapers from Ross, which afterwards
            go to an Arab grocer, who reads the _Times_ and the _Saturday Review_ in his shop in the
            bazaar! what next? The cargo of books which Alick and you sent will be most acceptable
            for winter consumption. If I were a painter I would take up the Moslem traditions of
            Joseph and Mary. He was not a white-bearded old gentleman at all you must know, but
            young, lovely and pure as Our Lady herself. They were cousins, brought up together; and
            she avoided the light conversation of other girls, and used to go to the well with her
            jar, hand in hand with Joseph carrying his. After the angel Gabriel had announced to her
            the will of God, and blown into her sleeve, whereby she conceived ‘the Spirit of God,’
            Joseph saw her state with dismay, and resolved to kill her, as was his duty as her
            nearest male relation. He followed her, knife in hand, meaning always to kill her at the
            next tree, and each time his heart failed him, until they reached the well and the tree
            under which the Divine messenger stood once more and said, ‘Fear not oh Joseph, the
            daughter of thy uncle bears within her Eesa, the Messiah, the Spirit of God.’ Joseph
            married his cousin without fear. Is it not pretty? the two types of youthful purity and
            piety, standing hand in hand before the angel. I think a painter might make something
            out of the soft-eyed Syrian boy with his jar on his shoulder (hers on the head), and the
            grave, modest maiden who shrank from all profane company. </p>
         <p> I now know all about Sheykh Seleem, and why he sits naked on the river bank; from very
            high authority—a great Sheykh to whom it has been revealed. He was entrusted with the
            care of some of the holy she camels, like that on which the Prophet rode to Jerusalem in
            one night, and which are invisible to all but the elect, and he lost one, and now he is
            God’s prisoner till she is found. </p>
         <p> A letter from aunt Charley all about her own and Rainie’s country life, school feasts
            etc., made me quite cry, and brought before me—oh, how vividly—the difference between
            East and West, not quite _all_ to the advantage of home however, though mostly. What is
            pleasant here is the primitive ways. Three times since I have been here lads of most
            respectable families of Luxor have come to ask hospitality, which consists in a place on
            the deck of the boat, and liberty to dip their bread in the common dish with my slave
            boy and Achmet. The bread they brought with them, ‘bread and shelter’ were not asked, as
            they slept _sub dio_. In England I must have refused the hospitality, on account of
            _gêne_ and expense. The chief object to the lads was the respectability of being under
            my eye while away from their fathers, as a satisfaction to their families; and while
            they ate and slept like beggars, as we should say, they read their books and chatted
            with me, when I was out on the deck, on perfectly equal terms, only paying the respect
            proper to my age. I thought of the ‘orphanages and institutions’ and all the countless
            difficulties of that sort, and wondered whether something was not to be said for this
            absence of civilization in knives, forks, beds, beer, and first and second tables above
            all. Of course climate has a good deal to do with the facility with which widows and
            orphans are absorbed here. </p>
         <p> Goodbye dearest Mutter: to-day is post day, and Reis Mohammed is about to trudge into
            town in such a dazzling white turban and such a grand black robe. His first wife, whom
            he was going to divorce for want of children, has brought him a son, and we jeer him a
            little about what he may find in Luxor from the second, and wish him a couple of
            dozen.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>