<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>December 23, 1864: Mrs. Austin, ON THE NILE, Friday, December 23, 1864.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST MUTTER, </p>
         <p> Here I am again between Benisouef and Minieh, and already better for the clear air of
            the river and the tranquil boat life; I will send you my Christmas Salaam from Siout.
            While Alick was with me I had as much to do as I was able and could not write for there
            was much to see and talk about. I think he was amused but I fear he felt the Eastern
            life to be very poor and comfortless. I have got so used to having nothing that I had
            quite forgotten how it would seem to a stranger. </p>
         <p> I am quite sorry to find how many of my letters must have been lost from Luxor; in
            future I shall trust the Arab post which certainly is safer than English travellers. I
            send you my long plaits by Alick, for I had my hair cut short as it took to falling out
            by handfuls after my fever, and moreover it is more convenient Turkish hareem fashion. </p>
         <p> Please tell Dean Stanley how his old dragoman Mahommed Gazawee cried with pleasure when
            he told me he had seen Sheykh Stanley’s sister on her way to India, and the ‘little
            ladies’ _knew his name_ and shook hands with him, which evidently was worth far more
            than the backsheesh. I wondered who ‘Sheykh’ Stanley could be, and Mahommed (who is a
            darweesh and very pious) told me he was the _Gassis_ (priest) who was _Imám_ (spiritual
            guide) to the son of our Queen, ‘and in truth,’ said he, ‘he is _really_ a Sheykh and
            one who teaches the excellent things of religion, why he was kind even to his horse! and
            it is of the mercies of God to the English that such a one is the Imám of your Queen and
            Prince.’ I said laughing, ‘How dost thou, a darweesh among Muslims, talk thus of a
            Nazarene priest?’ ‘Truly oh Lady,’ he answered, ‘one who loveth all the creatures of
            God, him God loveth also, there is no doubt of that.’ Is any one bigot enough to deny
            that Stanley has done more for real religion in the mind of that Muslim darweesh than if
            he had baptised a hundred savages out of one fanatical faith into another? </p>
         <p> There is no hope of a good understanding with Orientals until Western Christians can
            bring themselves to recognise the common faith contained in the two religions, the
            _real_ difference consists in all the class of notions and feelings (very important
            ones, no doubt) which we derive—not from the Gospels at all—but from Greece and Rome,
            and which of course are altogether wanting here. </p>
         <p> Alick will tell you how curiously Omar illustrated the patriarchal feelings of the East
            by entirely dethroning me in favour of the ‘Master.’ ‘That _our Master_, we all eat
            bread from his hand, and he work for _us_.’ Omar and I were equal before _our Seedee_.
            He can sit at his ease at my feet, but when the Master comes in he must stand
            reverently, and gave me to understand that I too must be respectful. </p>
         <p> I have got the boat of the American Mission at an outrageous price, £60, but I could
            get nothing under; the consolation is that the sailors profit, poor fellows, and get
            treble wages. My crew are all Nubians. Such a handsome reis and steersman—brothers—and
            there is a black boy, of fourteen or so, with legs and feet so sweetly beautiful as to
            be quite touching—at least I always feel those lovely round young innocent forms to be
            somehow affecting. Our old boat of last summer (Arthur Taylor’s) is sailing in company
            with us, and stately old reis Mubharak hails me every morning with the Blessing of God
            and the Peace of the Prophet. Alee Kuptan, my steamboat captain will announce our advent
            at Thebes; he passed us to-day. This boat is a fine sailer, but iron built and therefore
            noisy, and not convenient. The crew encourage her with ‘Get along, father of three,’
            because she has three sails, whereas two is the usual number. They are active
            good-humoured fellows—my men—but lack the Arab courtesy and _simpatico_ ways, and then I
            don’t understand their language which is pretty and sounds a little like Caffre, rather
            bird-like and sing-song, instead of the clattering guttural Arabic. I now speak pretty
            tolerably for a stranger, _i.e._ I can keep up a conversation, and understand all that
            is said to me much better than I can speak, and follow about half what people say to
            each other. When I see you, _Inshallah_, next summer I shall be a good scholar, I
            hope.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>