<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon. BOAT OFF EMBABEH, November 21, 1862.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

         <p>Dearest Alick,</p>

         <p>We embarked yesterday, and after the fashion of Eastern caravans are abiding to-day at a
            village opposite <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>; it is Friday, and therefore would be improper and unlucky to set
            out on our journey. The scenes on the river are wonderfully diverting and curious, so
            much life and movement. But the boatmen are sophisticated; my crew have all sported new
            white drawers in honour of the Sitti Ingleezee's supposed modesty--of course
            compensation will be expected. Poor fellows! they are very well mannered and quiet in
            their rags and misery, and their queer little humming song is rather pretty, 'Eyah
            Mohammad, eyah Mohammad,' _ad infinitum_, except when an energetic man cries
            'Yallah!'--_i.e_., 'O God!'--which means 'go it' in everyday life. Omar is gone to fetch
            one or two more 'unconsidered trifles,' and I have been explaining the defects to be
            remedied in the cabin door, broken window, etc., to my Reis with the help of six words
            of Arabic and dumb show, which they understand and answer with wonderful quickness.</p>

         <p>The air on the river is certainly quite celestial--totally unlike the damp, chilly
            feeling of the hotel and Frank quarter of <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>. The Isbekeeyeh, or public garden, where
            all the Franks live, was a lake, I believe, and is still very damp.</p>

         <p>I shall go up to the second Cataract as fast as possible, and return back at leisure.
            Hekekian Bey came to take leave yesterday, and lent me several books; pray tell Senior
            what a kindness his introduction was. It would have been rather dismal in <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>--if one
            could be dismal there--without a soul to speak to. I was sorry to know no Turks or
            Arabs, and have no opportunity of seeing any but the tradesman of whom I bought my
            stores but that was very amusing. The young man of whom I bought my _finjaans_ was so
            handsome, elegant and melancholy that I know he was the lover of the Sultan's favourite
            slave. How I wish you were here to enjoy all this, so new, so beautiful, and yet so
            familiar, life--and you would like the people, poor things! they are complete children,
            but amiable children.</p>

         <p>I went into the village here, where I was a curiosity, and some women took me into their
            houses and showed me their sleeping-place, cookery, poultry, etc.; and a man followed me
            to keep off the children, but no backsheesh was asked for, which showed that Europeans
            were rare there. The utter destitution is terrible to see, though in this climate of
            course it matters less, but the much-talked-of dirt is simply utter poverty. The poor
            souls are as clean as Nile mud and water will make their bodies, and they have not a
            second shirt, or any bed but dried mud.</p>

         <p>Give my love to my darlings, and don't be uneasy if you don't get letters. My cough has
            been better now for five days without a bad return of it, so I hope it is really better;
            it is the first reprieve for so long. The sun is so hot, a regular broil, November 21,
            and all doors and windows open in the cabin--a delicious breeze.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>