<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, THEBES, From December 25, 1865, to
               January 3, 1866.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/66">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <date when="1865-12-25">25 December 1865</date>
               <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/347342">Thebes</settlement>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff Gordon</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK, </p>
         <p> I wish you all, ‘may the year be good to thee’ as we say here—and now for my history.
            We left <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> on the 5th Decr. I was not well. No
            wind as usual, and we were a week getting to Benisonef where the Stamboolee Greek lady
            who was so kind to me last summer in my illness came on board with a very well-bred Arab
            lady. I was in bed, and only stayed a few hours. On to Minieh another five or six
            days—walked about and saw the preparations for the Pasha’s arrival. Nothing so flat as
            these affairs here. Not a creature went near the landing-place but his own servants,
            soldiers, and officials. I thought of the arrival of the smallest of German princes,
            which makes ten times the noise. Next on to Siout. Ill again, and did not land or see
            anyone. On to Girgeh, where we only stayed long enough to deliver money and presents
            which I had been begged to take for some old sailors of mine to their mothers and wives
            there. </p>
         <p> Between Siout and Girgeh an Abyssinian slave lad came and wanted me to steal him; he
            said his master was a Copt and ill-used him, and the lady beat him. But Omar sagely
            observed to the sailors, who were very anxious to take him, that a bad master did not
            give his slave such good clothes and even a pair of shoes—_quel luxe_!—and that he made
            too much of his master being a Copt; no doubt he was a lazy fellow, and perhaps had run
            away with other property besides himself. Soon after I was sitting on the pointed prow
            of the boat with the Reis, who was sounding with his painted pole (_vide_ antique
            sculptures and paintings), and the men towing, when suddenly something rose to the
            surface close to us: the men cried out _Beni Adam_! and the Reis prayed for the dead. It
            was a woman: the silver bracelets glittered on the arms raised and stiffened in the
            agony of death, the knees up and the beautiful Egyptian breasts floated above the water.
            I shall never forget the horrid sight. ‘God have mercy on her,’ prayed my men, and the
            Reis added to me, ‘let us also pray for her father, poor man: you see, no robber has
            done this (on account of the bracelets). We are in the Saeed now, and most likely she
            has blackened her father’s face, and he has been forced to strangle her, poor man.’ I
            said ‘Alas!’ and the Reis continued, ‘ah, yes, it is a heavy thing, but a man must
            whiten his face, poor man, poor man. God have mercy on him.’ Such is Saeedee _point
            d’honneur_. However, it turned out she was drowned bathing. </p>
         <p> Above Girgeh we stopped awhile at Dishné, a large village. I strolled up alone, _les
            mains dans les poches_, ‘_sicut meus est mos_:’ and was soon accosted with an invitation
            to coffee and pipes in the strangers’ place, a sort of room open on one side with a
            column in the middle, like two arches of a cloister, and which in all the villages is
            close to the mosque: two or three cloaks were pulled off and spread on the ground for me
            to sit on, and the milk which I asked for, instead of the village coffee, brought. In a
            minute a dozen men came and sat round, and asked as usual, ‘Whence comest thou, and
            whither goest thou?’ and my gloves, watch, rings, etc. were handed round and examined;
            the gloves always call forth many _Mashallah’s_. I said, ‘I come from the Frank country,
            and am going to my place near Abu’l Hajjaj.’ Hereupon everyone touched my hand and said,
            ‘Praise be to God that we have seen thee. Don’t go on: stay here and take 100 feddans of
            land and remain here.’ I laughed and asked, ‘Should I wear the _zaboot_ (brown shirt)
            and the _libdeh_, and work in the field, seeing there is no man with me?’ There was much
            laughing, and then several stories of women who had farmed large properties well and
            successfully. Such undertakings on the part of women seem quite as common here as in
            Europe, and more common than in England. </p>
         <p> I took leave of my new friends who had given me the first welcome home to the Saeed,
            and we went on to Keneh, which we reached early in the morning, and I found my
            well-known donkey-boys putting my saddle on. The father of one, and the two brothers of
            the other, were gone to work on the railway for sixty days’ forced labour, taking their
            own bread, and the poor little fellows were left alone to take care of the Hareem. As
            soon as we reached the town, a couple of tall young soldiers in the Nizam uniform rushed
            after me, and greeted me in English; they were Luxor lads serving their time. Of course
            they attached themselves to us for the rest of the day. We then bought water jars (the
            _specialité_ of Keneh); _gullehs_ and _zees_—and I went on to the Kadee’s house to leave
            a little string of beads, just to show that I had not forgotten the worthy Kadee’s
            courtesy in bringing his little daughter to sit beside me at dinner when I went down the
            river last summer. I saw the Kadee giving audience to several people, so I sent in the
            beads and my salaam; but the jolly Kadee sallied forth into the street and ‘fell upon my
            neck’ with such ardour that my Frankish hat was sent rolling by contact with the turban
            of Islam. The Kadee of Keneh is the real original Kadee of our early days; sleek,
            rubicund, polite—a puisne judge and a dean rolled into one, combining the amenities of
            the law and the church—with an orthodox stomach and an orthodox turban, both round and
            stately. I was taken into the hareem, welcomed and regaled, and invited to the festival
            of Seyd Abd er-Racheem, the great saint of Keneh. I hesitated, and said there were great
            crowds, and some might be offended at my presence; but the Kadee declared ‘by Him who
            separated us’ that if any such ignorant persons were present it was high time they
            learnt better, and said that it was by no means unlawful for virtuous Christians, and
            such as neither hated nor scorned the Muslimeen, to profit by, or share in their
            prayers, and that I should sit before the Sheykh’s tomb with him and the Mufti; and that
            _du reste_, they wished to give thanks for my safe arrival. Such a demonstration of
            tolerance was not to be resisted. So after going back to rest, and dine in the boat, I
            returned at nightfall into the town and went to the burial-place. The whole way was
            lighted up and thronged with the most motley crowd, and the usual mixture of holy and
            profane, which we know at the Catholic _fêtes_ also; but more _prononcé_ here. Dancing
            girls, glittering with gold brocade and coins, swaggered about among the brown-shirted
            fellaheen, and the profane singing of the _Alateeyeh_ mingled with the songs in honour
            of the Arab prophet chanted by the Moonsheeds and the deep tones of the ‘Allah, Allah’
            of the Zikeers. Rockets whizzed about and made the women screech, and a merry-go-round
            was in full swing. And now fancy me clinging to the skirts of the Cadi ul Islam (who did
            not wear a spencer, as the Methodist parson threatened his congregation he would do at
            the Day of Judgement) and pushing into the tomb of the Seyd Abd er-Racheem, through such
            a throng. No one seemed offended or even surprised. I suppose my face is so well known
            at Keneh. When my party had said a _Fattah_ for me and another for my family, we retired
            to another _kubbeh_, where there was no tomb, and where we found the Mufti, and sat
            there all the evening over coffee and pipes and talk. I was questioned about English
            administration of justice, and made to describe the process of trial by jury. The Mufti
            is a very dignified gentlemanly man, and extremely kind and civil. The Kadee pressed me
            to stay next day and dine with him and the Mufti, but I said I had a lantern for Luxor,
            and I wanted to arrive before the _moolid_ was over, and only three days remained. So
            the Kadee accompanied me back to the boat, looked at my maps, which pleased him very
            much, traced out the line of the railway as he had heard it, and had tea. </p>
         <p> Next morning we had the first good wind, and bowled up to Luxor in one day, arriving
            just after sunset. Instantly the boat was filled. Of course Omar and the Reis at once
            organized a procession to take me and my lantern to the tomb of Abu-l-Hajjaj—it was the
            last night but one of his moolid. The lantern was borne on a pole between two of my
            sailors, and the rest, reinforced by men from a steamer which was there with a Prussian
            prince, sung and thumped the tarabookeh, and we all marched up after I had undergone
            every variety of salutation, from Sheykh Yussuf’s embrace to the little boys’ kissing of
            hands. The first thing I heard was the hearty voice of the old Shereef, who praised God
            that ‘our darling’ was safe back again, and then we all sat down for a talk; then more
            _Fattahs_ were said for me, and for you, and for the children; and I went back to bed in
            my own boat. I found the guard of the French house had been taken off to Keneh to the
            works, after lying eight days in chains and wooden handcuffs for resisting, and claiming
            his rights as a French _protégé_. So we waited for his return, and for the keys which he
            had taken with him, in hopes that the Keneh authorities would not care to keep me out of
            the house. I wrote to the French Consular agent at Keneh, and to the Consul at
            Alexandria, and got him back the third day. What would you think in Europe to see me
            welcome with enthusiasm a servant just out of chains and handcuffs? At the very moment,
            too, that Mohammed and I were talking, a boat passed up the river with musick and
            singing on board. It was a Sheykh-el-Beled, of a place above Esneb, who had lain in
            prison three years in <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>, and whose friends were
            making all the fantasia they could to celebrate the end of his misfortune, of disgrace,
            _il n’en est pas question_; and why should it? So many honest men go to prison that it
            is no presumption at all against a man. </p>
         <p> The day after my arrival was the great and last day. The crowd was but little and not
            lively—times are too hard. But the riding was beautiful. Two young men from Hegaz
            performed wonderful feats. </p>
         <p> I dined with the Maōhn, whose wife cooked me the best dinner I ever ate in this
            country, or almost anywhere. Marie, who was invited, rejoiced the kind old lady’s heart
            by her Belgian appreciation of the excellent cookery. ‘Eat, my daughter, eat,’ and even
            I managed to give satisfaction. Such Bakloweh I never tasted. We removed to the house
            yesterday, and I have had company ever since. </p>
         <p> One Sheykh Alee—a very agreeable man from beyond Khartoom, offers to take me up to
            Khartoom and back with a Takhterawan (camel litter) in company with Mustapha A’gha,
            Sheykh Yussuf and a troop of his own Abab’deh. It is a terrible temptation—but it would
            cost £50—so I refused. Sheykh Alee is so clever and well-bred that I should enjoy it
            much, and the climate at this season is delightful. He has been in the Denka country
            where the men are a cubit taller than Sheykh Hassan whom you know, and who enquires
            tenderly after you. </p>
         <p> Now let me describe the state of things. From the Moudeeriat of Keneh only, 25,000 men
            are taken to work for sixty days without food or pay; each man must take his own basket,
            and each third man a hoe, not a basket. If you want to pay a substitute for a beloved or
            delicate son, it costs 1,000 piastres—600 at the lowest; and about 300 to 400 for his
            food. From Luxor only, 220 men are gone; of whom a third will very likely die of
            exposure to the cold and misery (the weather is unusually cold). That is to say that
            this little village, of at most 2,000 souls male and female (we don’t usually count
            women, from decorum), will pay in labour at least £1,320 in sixty days. We have also
            already had eleven camels seized to go up to the Soudan; a camel is worth from £18 to
            £40. </p>
         <p> Last year Mariette Bey made excavations at Gourneh forcing the people to work but
            promising payment at the rate of—Well, when he was gone the four Sheykhs of the village
            at Gourneh came to Mustapha and begged him to advance the money due from Government, for
            the people were starving. Mustapha agrees and gives above 300 purses—about £1,000 in
            _current_ piastres on the understanding that he is to get the money from Government in
            _tariff_—and to keep the difference as his profit. If he cannot get it at all the
            fellaheen are to pay him back without interest. Of course at the rate at which money is
            here, his profit would be but small interest on the money unless he could get the money
            directly, and he has now waited six months in vain. </p>
         <p> Abdallah the son of el-Habbeshee of Damankoor went up the river in chains to Fazoghlou
            a fortnight ago and Osman Bey ditto last week—El-Bedrawee is dead there, of course. </p>
         <p> Shall I tell you what became of the hundred prisoners who were sent away after the Gau
            business? As they marched through the desert the Greek memlook looked at his list each
            morning, and said, ‘Hoseyn, Achmet, Foolan (like the Spanish Don Fulano, Mr. so and so),
            you are free; take off his chains.’ Well, the three or four men drop behind, where some
            arnouts strangle them out of sight. This is banishment to Fazoghlou. Do you remember _le
            citoyen est élargi_ of the September massacres of Paris? Curious coincidence, is it not?
            Everyone is exasperated—the very Hareem talk of the government. It is in the air. I had
            not been five minutes in Keneh before I knew all this and much more. Of the end of
            Hajjee Sultan I will not speak till I have absolute certainty, but, I believe the
            proceeding was as I have described—set free in the desert and murdered by the way. I
            wish you to publish these facts, it is no secret to any but to those Europeans whose
            interests keep their eyes tightly shut, and they will soon have them opened. The blind
            rapacity of the present ruler will make him astonish the Franks some day, I think. </p>
         <p> Wheat is now 400 piastres the ardeb up here; the little loaf, not quite so big as our
            penny roll, costs a piastre—about three-half-pence—and all in proportion. I need not say
            what the misery is. Remember that this is the second levy of 220 men within six months,
            each for sixty days, as well as the second seizure of camels; besides the conscription,
            which serves the same purpose, as the soldiers work on the Pasha’s works. But in
               <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> they are paid—and well paid. </p>
         <p> It is curious how news travels here. The Luxor people knew the day I left Alexandria,
            and the day I left <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>, long before I came. They
            say here that Abu-l-Hajjaj gave me his hand from Keneh, because he would not finish his
            moolid without me. I am supposed to be specially protected by him, as is proved by my
            health being so far better here than anywhere else. </p>
         <p> By the bye, Sheykh Alee Abab’deh told me that all the villages _close_ on the Nile
            escaped the cholera almost completely, whilst those who were half or a quarter of a mile
            inland were ravaged. At Keneh 250 a day died; at Luxor one child was supposed to have
            died of it, but I know he had diseased liver for a year or more. In the desert the
            Bishareen and Abab’deh suffered more than the people at <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>, and you know the desert is usually the place of perfect health;
            but fresh Nile water seems to be _the_ antidote. Sheykh Yussuf laid the mortality at
            Keneh to the canal water, which the poor people drink there. I believe the fact is as
            Sheykh Alee told me. </p>
         <p> Now I will say good-bye, for I am tired, and will write anon to the rest. Let Mutter
            have this. I was very poorly till I got above Siout, and then gradually mended—constant
            blood spitting and great weakness and I am very thin, but, by the protection of
            Abu-l-Hajjaj I suppose I am already much better, and begin to eat again. I have not been
            out yet since the first day, having much to do in the house to get to rights. I felt
            very dreary on Christmas-day away from you all, and Omar’s plum-pudding did not cheer me
            at all, as he hoped it would. He begs me to kiss your hand for him, and every one sends
            you salaam, and all lament that you are not the new Consul at <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>. </p>
         <p> Kiss my chicks, and love to you all. Janet, I hope is in Egypt ere this.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>