<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>October 25, 1866: Mrs. Austin, OFF BOULAK, October 25, 1866.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST MUTTER, </p>
         <p> I have got all ready, and shall sail on Saturday. My men have baked the bread, and
            received their wages to go to Luxor and bring the boat back to let. It is turning cold,
            but I feel none the worse for it, though I shall be glad to go. I’ve had a dreary,
            worrying time here, and am tired of hearing of all the meannesses and wickedness which
            constitute the _on dits_ here. Not that I hear much, but there is nothing else. I shall
            be best at Luxor now the winter has set in so early. You would laugh at such winter when
            one sits out all day under an awning in English summer clothes, and wants only two
            blankets at night; but all is comparative _ici bas_, and I call it cold, and Mabrook
            ceases to consider his clothes such a grievance as they were to him at first, and takes
            kindly to a rough _capote_ for the night. I have just been interrupted by my Reis and
            one of my men, who came in to display the gorgeous printed calico they have bought; one
            for his Luxor wife and the other for his betrothed up near Assouan. (The latter is about
            eight years old, and Hosein has dressed her and paid her expenses these five years, as
            is the custom up in that district.) The Reis has bought a silk head-kerchief for nine
            shillings, but that was in the marriage contract. So I must see, admire and wish good
            luck to the finery, and to the girls who are to wear it. Then we had a little talk about
            the prospects of letting the boat, and, Inshallah, making some money for _el gamma_,
            _i.e._, ‘all our company,’ or ‘all of us together.’ The Reis hopes that the _Howagat_
            will not be too outrageous in their ways or given to use the stick, as the solution of
            every difficulty. </p>
         <p> The young Shurafa of Abu-l-Hajjaj came from Gama’l Azhar to-day to bid me goodbye and
            bring their letters for Luxor. I asked them about the rumours that the Ulema are
            preaching against the Franks (which is always being said), but they had heard nothing of
            the sort, and said they had not heard of anything the Franks had done lately which would
            signify to the Muslims at all. It is not the Franks who press so many soldiers, or levy
            such heavy taxes three months in advance! I will soon write again. I feel rather like
            the wandering Jew and long for home and rest, without being dissatisfied with what I
            have and enjoy, God knows. If I _could_ get better and come home next summer.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>