<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>March 1, 1864: To Mrs. Austin, LUXOR, March_ 1, 1864.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST MUTTER, </p>
         <p> I think I shall have an opportunity of sending letters in a few days by a fast steamer,
            so I will begin one on the chance and send it by post if the steamer is delayed long.
            The glory of the climate now is beyond description, and I feel better every day. I go
            out early—at seven or eight o’clock—on my tiny black donkey, and come in to breakfast
            about ten, and go out again at four. </p>
         <p> I want to photograph Yussuf for you. The feelings and prejudices and ideas of a
            cultivated Arab, as I get at them little by little, are curious beyond compare. It won’t
            do to generalize from one man, of course, but even one gives some very new ideas. The
            most striking thing is the sweetness and delicacy of feeling—the horror of hurting
            anyone (this must be individual, of course: it is too good to be general). I apologized
            to him two days ago for inadvertently answering the _Salaam aleykoum_, which he, of
            course, said to Omar on coming in. Yesterday evening he walked in and startled me by a
            _Salaam aleykee_ addressed to me; he had evidently been thinking it over whether he
            ought to say it to me, and come to the conclusion that it was not wrong. ‘Surely it is
            well for all the creatures of God to speak peace (_Salaam_) to each other,’ said he.
            Now, no uneducated Muslim would have arrived at such a conclusion. Omar would pray,
            work, lie, do anything for me—sacrifice money even; but I doubt whether he _could_ utter
            _Salaam aleykoum_ to any but a Muslim. I answered as I felt: ‘Peace, oh my brother, and
            God bless thee!’ It was almost as if a Catholic priest had felt impelled by charity to
            offer the communion to a heretic. I observed that the story of the barber was new to
            him, and asked if he did not know the ‘Thousand and One Nights.’ No; he studied only
            things of religion, no light amusements were proper for an Alim (elder of religion);
            _we_ Europeans did not know that, of course, as _our_ religion was to enjoy ourselves;
            but _he_ must not make merry with diversions, or music, or droll stories. (See the
            mutual ignorance of all ascetics!) He has a little girl of six or seven, and teaches her
            to write and read; no one else, he believes, thinks of such a thing out of <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>; there many of the daughters of the Alim learn—those
            who desire it. His wife died two years ago, and six months ago he married again a wife
            of twelve years old! (Sheykh Yussuf is thirty he tells me; he looks twenty-two or
            twenty-three.) What a stepmother and what a wife! He can repeat the whole Koran without
            a book, it takes twelve hours to do it. Has read the Towrát (old Testament) and the
            el-Aangeel (Gospels), of course, every Alim reads them. ‘The words of Seyyidna Eesa are
            the true faith, but Christians have altered and corrupted their meaning. So we Muslims
            believe. We are all the children of God.’ I ask if Muslims call themselves so, or only
            the slaves of God. ‘’Tis all one, children or slaves. Does not a good man care for both
            tenderly alike?’ (Pray observe the Oriental feeling here. _Slave_ is a term of
            affection, not contempt; and remember the Centurion’s ‘_servant_ (slave) whom he
            loved.’) He had heard from Fodl Pasha how a cow was cured of the prevailing disease in
            Lower Egypt by water weighed against a _Mushaf_ (copy of the Koran), and had no doubt it
            was true, Fodl Pasha had tried it. Yet he thinks the Arab doctors no use at all who use
            verses of the Koran. </p>
         <p> M. de Rougé, the great _Egyptologue_, came here one evening; he speaks Arabic
            perfectly, and delighted Sheykh Yussuf, who was much interested in the translations of
            the hieroglyphics and anxious to know if he had found anything about _Moussa_ (Moses) or
            _Yussuf_ (Joseph). He looked pleased and grateful to be treated like a ‘gentleman and
            scholar’ by such an Alim as M. de Rougé and such a Sheykhah as myself. As he acts as
            clerk to Mustapha, our consular agent, and wears a shabby old brown shirt, or gown, and
            speaks no English, I dare say he not seldom encounters great slights (from sheer
            ignorance). He produced a bit of old Cufic MS. and consulted M. de R. as to its
            meaning—a pretty little bit of flattery in an Arab Alim to a Frenchman, to which the
            latter was not insensible, I saw. In answer to the invariable questions about all my
            family I once told him my father had been a great Alim of the Law, and that my mother
            had got ready his written books and put some lectures in order to be printed. He was
            amazed—first that I had a mother, as he told me he thought I was fifty or sixty, and
            immensely delighted at the idea. ‘God has favoured your family with understanding and
            knowledge; I wish I could kiss the _Sheykhah_ your mother’s hand. May God favour her!’
            Maurice’s portrait (as usual) he admired fervently, and said one saw his good qualities
            in his face—a compliment I could have fully returned, as he sat looking at the picture
            with affectionate eyes and praying, _sotto voce_, for _el gedda_, _el gemeel_ (the
            youth, the beautiful), in the words of the _Fathah_, ‘O give him guidance and let him
            not stray into the paths of the rejected!’ Altogether, something in Sheykh Yussuf
            reminds me of Worsley: there is the same look of _Seelen reinheit_, with far less
            thought and intelligence; indeed little thought, of course, and an additional childlike
            innocence. I suppose some medieval monks may have had the same look, but no Catholic I
            have ever seen looks so peaceful or so unpretending. I see in him, like in all people
            who don’t know what doubt means, that easy familiarity with religion. I hear him joke
            with Omar about Ramadan, and even about Omar’s assiduous prayers, and he is a frequent
            and hearty laugher. I wonder whether this gives you any idea of a character new to you.
            It is so impossible to describe _manner_, which gives so much of the impression of
            novelty. My conclusion is the heretical one: that to dream of converting here is absurd,
            and, I will add, wrong. All that is wanted is general knowledge and education, and the
            religion will clear and develop itself. The elements are identical with those of
            Christianity, encumbered, as that has been, with asceticism and intolerance. On the
            other hand, the creed is simple and there are no priests, a decided advantage. I think
            the faith has remained wonderfully rational considering the extreme ignorance of those
            who hold it. I will add Sally’s practical remark, that ‘The prayers are a fine thing for
            lazy people; they must wash first, and the prayer is a capital drill.’ </p>
         <p> You would be amused to hear Sally when Omar does not wake in time to wash, pray, and
            eat before daybreak now in Ramadán. She knocks at his door and acts as Muezzin. ‘Come,
            Omar, get up and pray and have your dinner’ (the evening meal is ‘breakfast,’ the early
            morning one ‘dinner’). Being a light sleeper she hears the Muezzin, which Omar often
            does not, and passes on the ‘Prayers is better than sleep’ in a prose version. Ramadán
            is a dreadful business; everybody is cross and lazy—no wonder! The camel-men quarrelled
            all day under my window yesterday, and I asked what it was all about. ‘All about
            nothing; it is Ramadán with them,’ said Omar laughing. ‘I want to quarrel with someone
            myself; it is hot to-day, and thirsty weather.’ Moreover, I think it injures the health
            of numbers permanently, but of course it is the thing of most importance in the eyes of
            the people; there are many who never pray at ordinary times, but few fail to keep
            Ramadán. It answers to the Scotch Sabbath, a comparison also borrowed from Sally. </p>
         <p> _Friday_.—My friend Seleem Effendi has just been here talking about his own affairs and
            a good deal of theology. He is an immense talker, and I just put _eywas_ (yes) and _là_
            (no) and _sahé_ (very true), and learn manners and customs. He tells me he has just
            bought two black slave women, mother and daughter, from a Copt for about £35 the two.
            The mother is a good cook, and the daughter is ‘for his bed,’ as his wife does not like
            to leave <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> and her boys at school there. It does
            give one a sort of start to hear a most respectable magistrate tell one such a domestic
            arrangement. He added that it would not interfere with the _Sittel Kebeer_ (the great
            lady), the black girl being only a slave, and these people never think they have
            children enough. Moreover, he said he could not get on with his small pay without women
            to keep house, which is quite true here, and women are not respectable in a man’s house
            on other terms. Seleem has a high reputation, and is said not to ‘eat the people.’ He is
            a hot Mussulman, and held forth very much as a very superficial Unitarian might do,
            evidently feeling considerable contempt for the absurdities, as he thinks them, of the
            Copts (he was too civil to say Christians), but no hatred (and he is known to show no
            partiality), only he ‘can’t understand how people can believe such nonsense.’ He is a
            good specimen of the good, honest, steady-going man-of-the-world Muslim, a strong
            contrast to the tender piety of dear Sheykh Yussuf, who has all the feelings which we
            call Christian charity in the highest degree, and whose face is like that of ‘the
            beloved disciple,’ but who has no inclination for doctrinal harangues like worthy
            Seleem. There is a very general idea among the Arabs that Christians hate the Muslims;
            they attribute to us the old Crusading spirit. It is only lately that Omar has let us
            see him at prayer, for fear of being ridiculed, but now he is sure that is not so, I
            often find him praying in the room where Sally sits at work, which is a clean, quiet
            place. Yussuf went and joined him there yesterday evening, and prayed with him, and gave
            him some religious instruction quite undisturbed by Sally and her needlework, and I am
            continually complimented on _not hating_ the Muslims. Yussuf promises me letters to some
            Alim in <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> when I go there again, that I may be
            shown the Azhar (the great college). Omar had told him that I refused to go with a
            janissary from the Consul for fear of giving offence to any very strict Muslims, which
            astonished him much. He says his friends shall dress me in their women’s clothes and
            take me in. I asked whether as a concealment of my religion, and he said no, only there
            were ‘thousands’ of young men, and it would be ‘more delicate’ that they should not
            stare and talk about my face. </p>
         <p> Seleem told me a very pretty grammatical quibble about ‘son’ and ‘prophet’ (apropos of
            Christ) on a verse in the Gospel, depending on the reduplicative sign [Arabic sign for
            sheddeh] (_sheddeh_) over one letter; he was just as put out when I reminded him that it
            was written in Greek, as our amateur theologians are if you say the Bible was not
            originally composed in English. However, I told him that many Christians in England,
            Germany, and America did not believe that Seyyidna Eesa was God, but only the greatest
            of prophets and teachers, and that I was myself of that opinion. He at once declared
            that that was sufficient, that all such had ‘received guidance,’ and were not ‘among the
            rejected’; how could they be, since such Christians only believed the teaching of Eesa,
            which was true, and not the falsifications of the priests and bishops (the bishops
            always ‘catch it,’ as schoolboys say). I was curious to hear whether on the strength of
            this he would let out any further intolerance against the Copts, but he said far less
            and far less bitterly than I have heard from Unitarians, and debited the usual most
            commonplace, common-sense kind of arguments on the subject. I fancy it would not be very
            palatable to many Unitarians, to be claimed _mir nichts dir nichts_ as followers of
            _el-Islam_; but if people really wish to convert in the sense of improving, that door is
            open, and no other. </p>
         <p> _Monday_, 7_th_.—The steamer is come down already and will, I suppose, go on to-morrow,
            so I must finish this letter to go by it. I have not received any letter for some time,
            and am anxiously expecting the post. We have now settled into quite warm weather ways,
            no more going out at mid-day. It is now broiling, and I have been watching eight tall
            fine blacks swimming and capering about, their skins shining like otters’ fur when wet.
            They belong to a _gelláab_—a slave-dealer’s boat. The beautiful thing is to see the men
            and boys at work among the green corn, the men half naked and the boys wholly so; in the
            sun their brown skins look just like dark clouded amber—semi-transparent, so fine are
            they. </p>
         <p> I rejoice to say that on Wednesday is Bairam, and to-morrow Ramadan ‘dies.’ Omar is
            very thin and yellow and headachy, and everyone is cross. How I wish I were going,
            instead of my letter, to see you all, but it is evident that this heat is the thing that
            does me good, if anything will.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>