<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>April 14, 1864: To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, LUXOR, April 14, 1864.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK,</p>
         <p>I have but this moment received your letter of the 18th March, which went after Janet,
            who was hunting at Tel-el-Kebir. We have had a tremendous Khamseen wind, and now a
            strong north wind quite fresh and cool. The thermometer was 92° during the Khamseen, but
            it did me no harm. Luckily I am very well for I am worked hard, as a strange epidemic
            has broken out, and I am the _Hakeemeh_ (doctress) of Luxor. The _Hakeem_ Pasha from
               <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> came up and frightened the people, telling
            them it was catching, and Yussuf forgot his religion so far as to beg me not to be all
            day in the people’s huts; but Omar and I despised the danger, I feeling sure it was not
            infectious, and Omar saying _Min Allah_. The people get stoppage of the bowels and die
            in eight days unless they are physicked; all who have sent for me in time have
            recovered. _Alhamdulillah_, that I can help the poor souls. It is harvest, and the hard
            work, and the spell of intense heat, and the green corn, beans, etc., which they eat,
            brings on the sickness. Then the Copts are fasting from all animal food, and full of
            green beans and salad, and green corn. Mustapha tried to persuade me not to give
            physick, for fear those who died should pass for being poisoned, but both Omar and I are
            sure it is only to excuse his own selfishness. Omar is an excellent assistant. The
            bishop tried to make money by hinting that if I forbade my patients to fast, I might pay
            for their indulgence. One poor, peevish little man refused the chicken-broth, and told
            me that we Europeans had _our_ heaven in _this_ world; Omar let out _kelb_ (dog), but I
            stopped him, and said, ‘Oh, my brother, God has made the Christians of England unlike
            those of Egypt, and surely will condemn neither of us on that account; mayest thou find
            a better heaven hereafter than I now enjoy here.’ Omar threw his arms round me and said,
            ‘Oh, thou good one, surely our Lord will reward thee for acting thus with the meekness
            of a Muslimeh, and kissing the hand of him who strikes thy face.’ (See how each religion
            claims humility.) Suleyman was not pleased at his fellow-christian’s display of charity.
            It does seem strange that the Copts of the lower class will not give us the blessing, or
            thank God for our health like the Muslimeen. Most of my patients are Christians, and
            some are very nice people indeed. The people here have named me Sittee (Lady)
            _Noor-ala-Noor_. A poor woman whose only child, a young man, I was happy enough to cure
            when dreadfully ill, kissed my feet and asked by what name to pray for me. I told her my
            name meant _Noor_ (light—_lux_), but as that was one of the names of God I could not use
            it. ‘Thy name is _Noor-ala-Noor_,’ said a man who was in the room. That means something
            like ‘God is upon thy mind,’ or ‘light from the light,’ and _Noor-ala-Noor_ it remains;
            a combination of one of the names of God is quite proper, like Abdallah, Abdurachman,
            etc. I begged some medicines from a Countess Braniscki, who went down the other day;
            when all is gone I don’t know what I shall do. I am going to try to make castor oil; I
            don’t know how, but I shall try, and Omar fancies he can manage it. The cattle disease
            has also broken out desperately up in Esneh, and we see the dead beasts float down all
            day. Of course we shall soon have it here.</p>
         <p>_Sunday_, _April_ 17.—The epidemic seems to be over, but there is still a great deal of
            gastric fever, etc., about. The _hakeem_ from Keneh has just been here—such a pleasing,
            clever young man, speaking Italian perfectly, and French extremely well. He is the son
            of some fellah of Lower Egypt, sent to study at Pisa, and has not lost the Arab
            gentility and elegance by a _Frenghi_ education. We fraternized greatly, and the young
            _hakeem_ was delighted at my love for his people, and my high opinion of their
            intelligence. He is now gone to inspect the sick, and is to see me again and give me
            directions. He was very unhappy that he could not supply me with medicines; none are to
            be bought above <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>, except from the hospital
            doctors, who sell the medicines of the Government, as the Italian at Siout did. But Ali
            Effendi is too honest for that. The old bishop paid me a visit of three and a half hours
            yesterday, and _pour me tirer une carotte_ he sent me a loaf of sugar, so I must send a
            present ‘for the church’ to be consumed in raki. The old party was not very sober, and
            asked for wine. I coolly told him it was _haraam_ (forbidden) to us to drink during the
            day—only with our dinner. I never will give the Christians drink here, and now they have
            left off pressing me to drink spirits at their houses. The bishop offered to alter the
            hour of prayer for me, and to let me into the _Heykel_ (where women must not go) on Good
            Friday, which will be eighteen days hence. All of which I refused, and said I would go
            on the roof of the church and look down through the window with the other _Hareemat_.
            Omar kissed the bishop’s hand, and I said: ‘What! do _you_ kiss his hand like a Copt?’
            ‘Oh yes, he is an old man, and a servant of my God, but dreadful dirty,’ added Omar; and
            it was too true. His presence diffused a fearful monastic odour of sanctity. A Bishop
            must be a monk, as priests are married.</p>
         <p>_Monday_.—To-day Ali Effendi-_el-Hakeem_ came to tell me how he had been to try to see
            my patients and failed; all the families declared they were well and would not let him
            in. Such is the deep distrust of everything to do with the Government. They all waited
            till he was gone away, and then came again to me with their ailments. I scolded, and
            they all said, ‘_Wallah, ya Sitt, ya Emeereh_; that is the _Hakeem_ Pasha, and he would
            send us off to hospital at Keneh, and then they would poison us; by thy eyes do not be
            angry with us, or leave off from having compassion on us on this account.’ I said, ‘Ali
            Effendi is an Arab and a Muslim and an _Emeer_ (gentleman), and he gave me good advice,
            and would have given more,’ etc. No use at all. He is the Government doctor, and they
            had rather die, and will swallow anything from _el-Sittee Noor-ala-Noor_. Here is a
            pretty state of things.</p>
         <p>I gave Sheykh Yussuf £4 for three months’ daily lessons last night, and had quite a
            contest to force it upon him. ‘It is not for money, oh Lady;’ and he coloured crimson.
            He had been about with Ali Effendi, but could not get the people to see him. The Copts,
            I find, _have_ a religious prejudice against him, and, indeed, against all heretics.
            They consider themselves and the Abyssinians as the only true believers. If they
            acknowledge _us_ as brethren, it is for money. I speak only of the low class, and of the
            priests; of course the educated merchants are very different. I had two priests and two
            deacons, and the mother of one, here to-day for physic for the woman. She was very
            pretty and pleasing; miserably reduced and weak from the long fast. I told her she must
            eat meat and drink a little wine, and take cold baths, and gave her quinine. She will
            take the wine and the quinine, but neither eat nor wash. The Bishop tells them they will
            die if they break the fast, and half the Christians are ill from it. One of the priests
            spoke a little English; he fabricates false antiques very cleverly, and is tolerably
            sharp; but, Oh _mon Dieu_, it is enough to make one turn Muslim to compare these greasy
            rogues with such high-minded charitable _shurafa_ (noblemen) as Abd-el-Waris and Sheykh
            Yussuf. A sweet little Copt boy who is very ill will be killed by the stupid bigotry
            about the fast. My friend Suleyman is much put out, and backs my exhortations to the
            sick to break it. He is a capital fellow, and very intelligent, and he and Omar are like
            brothers; it is the priests who do all they can to keep alive religious prejudice.
            _Alhamdulillah_, they are only partially successful. Mohammed has just heard that
            seventy-five head of cattle are dead at El-Moutaneh. Here only a few have died as yet,
            and Ali Effendi thinks the disease less virulent than in Lower Egypt. I hope he is
            right; but dead beasts float down the river all day long.</p>
         <p>To turn to something more amusing—but please don’t tell it—such a joke against my gray
            hairs. I have had a proposal, or at least an attempt at one. A very handsome
            Sheykh-el-Arab (_Bedawee_) was here for a bit, and asked Omar whether I were a widow or
            divorced, as in either case he would send a _dellaleh_ (marriage brokeress) to me. Omar
            told him that would never do. I had a husband in England; besides, I was not young, had
            a married daughter, my hair was gray, etc. The Sheykh swore he didn’t care; I could dye
            my hair and get a divorce; that I was not like stupid modern women, but like an ancient
            Arab _Emeereh_, and worthy of Antar or Abou Zeyd—a woman for whom men killed each other
            or themselves—and he would pay all he could afford as my dowry. Omar came in in fits of
            laughter at the idea, and the difficulty he had had in stopping the _dellaleh’s_ visit.
            He told the Sheykh I should certainly beat her I should be so offended. The disregard of
            differences of age here on marriage is very strange. My adorer was not more than thirty,
            I am sure. Don’t tell people, my dear Alick; it is so very absurd; I should be ‘ashamed
            before the people.’</p>
         <p>_Saturday_, _April_ 23.—_Alhamdulillah_! the sickness is going off. I have just heard
            Suleyman’s report as follows: Hassan Abou-Achmet kisses the Emeereh’s feet, and the
            bullets have cleaned his stomach six times, and he has said the _Fathah_ for the Lady.
            The two little girls who had diarrhœa are well. The Christian dyer has vomited his
            powder and wants another. The mother of the Christian cook who married the priest’s
            sister has got dysentery. The hareem of Mustapha Abou-Abeyd has two children with bad
            eyes. The Bishop had a quarrel, and scolded and fell down, and cannot speak or move; I
            must go to him. The young-deacon’s jaundice is better. The slave girl of Kursheed A’gha
            is sick, and Kursheed is sitting at her head in tears; the women say I must go to her,
            too. Kursheed is a fine young Turk, and very good to his _Hareemat_. That is all;
            Suleyman has nothing on earth to do, and brings me a daily report; he likes the gossip
            and the importance.</p>
         <p>The reis of a cargo-boat brought me up your Lafontaine, and some papers and books from
            Hekekian Bey. Sheykh Yussuf is going down to <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>,
            to try to get back some of the lands which Mahommed Ali took away from the mosques and
            the Ulema without compensation. He asked me whether Ross would speak for him to
            Effendina! What are the Muslimeen coming to? As soon as I can read enough he offers to
            read in the Koran with me—a most unusual proceeding, as the ‘noble Koran’ is not
            generally put into the hands of heretics; but my ‘charity to the people in sickness’ is
            looked upon by Abd-el-Waris the Imam, and by Yussuf, as a proof that I have ‘received
            direction,’ and am of those Christians of whom _Seyyidna_ Mohammed (upon whose name be
            peace) has said ‘that they have no pride, that they rival each other in good works, and
            that God will increase their reward.’ There is no _arrière pensée_ of conversion that
            they think hopeless, but charity covers all sins with Muslimeen. Next Friday is the
            _Djuma el-Kebeer_ (Good Friday) with the Copts, and the prayers are in the daytime, so I
            shall go to the church. Next moon is the great Bairam, _el-Eed el-Kebeer_ (the great
            festival), with the Muslimeen—the commemoration of the sacrifice of Isaac or Ishmael
            (commentators are uncertain which)—and Omar will kill a sheep for the poor for the
            benefit of his baby, according to custom. I have at length compassed the destruction of
            mine enemy, though he has not written a book. A fanatical Christian dog (quadruped),
            belonging to the Coptic family who live on the opposite side of the yard, hated me with
            such virulent intensity that, not content with barking at me all day, he howled at me
            all night, even after I had put out the lantern and he could not see me in bed. Sentence
            of death has been recorded against him, as he could not be beaten into toleration.
            Michaïl, his master’s son, has just come down from El-Moutaneh, where he is _vakeel_ to
            M. Mounier. He gives a fearful account of the sickness there among men and cattle—eight
            and ten deaths a day; here we have had only four a day, at the worst, in a population of
            (I guess) some 2,000. The Mouniers have put themselves in quarantine, and allow no one
            to approach their house, as Mustapha wanted me to do. One hundred and fifty head of
            cattle have died at El-Moutaneh; here only a few calves are dead, but as yet no
            full-grown beasts, and the people are healthy again. I really think I did some service
            by not showing any fear, and Omar behaved manfully. By-the-by, will you find out whether
            a _passaporto_, as they call it, a paper granting British protection, can be granted in
            England. It is the object of Omar’s highest ambition to belong as much as possible to
            the English, and feel safe from being forced to serve a Turk. If it can be done by any
            coaxing and jobbing, pray do it, for Omar deserves any service I can render him in
            return for all his devotion and fidelity. Someone tried to put it into his head that it
            was _haraam_ to be too fond of us heretics and be faithful, but he consulted Sheykh
            Yussuf, who promised him a reward hereafter for good conduct to me, and who told me of
            it as a good joke, adding that he was _raghil ameen_, the highest praise for fidelity,
            the sobriquet of the Prophet. Do not be surprised at my lack of conscience in desiring
            to benefit my own follower _in qualunque modo_; justice is not of Eastern growth, and
            _Europeo_ is ‘your only wear,’ and here it is only base not to stick by one’s friends.
            Omar kisses the hands of the _Sidi-el-Kebeer_ (the great master), and desires his best
            salaam to the little master and the little lady, whose servant he is. He asks if I, too,
            do not kiss Iskender Bey’s hand in my letter, as I ought to do as his Hareem, or whether
            ‘I make myself big before my master,’ like some French ladies he has seen? I tell him I
            will do so if Iskender Bey will get him his _warak_ (paper), whereupon he picks up the
            hem of my gown and kisses that, and I civilly expostulate on such condescension to a
            woman. Yussuf is quite puzzled about European women, and a little shocked at the want of
            respect to their husbands they display. I told him that the outward respect shown to us
            by our men was _our veil_, and explained how superficial the difference was. He fancied
            that the law gave us the upper hand. Omar reports yesterday’s sermon ‘on toleration,’ it
            appears. Yussuf took the text of ‘Thou shalt love thy brother as thyself, and never act
            towards him but as thou wouldest he should act towards thee.’ I forget chapter and
            verse; but it seems he took the bull by the horns and declared _all men_ to be brothers,
            not Muslimeen only, and desired his congregation to look at the good deeds of others and
            not at their erroneous faith, for God is all-knowing (_i.e._, He only knows the heart),
            and if they saw aught amiss to remember that the best man need say _Astafer Allah_ (I
            beg pardon of God) seven times a day.</p> I<p> wish the English could know how
            unpleasant and mischievous their manner of talking to their servants about religion is.
            Omar confided to me how bad it felt to be questioned, and then to see the Englishman
            laugh or put up his lip and say nothing. ‘I don’t want to talk about his religion at
            all, but if he talks about mine he ought to speak of his own, too. You, my Lady, say,
            when I tell you things, that is the same with us, or that is different, or good, or not
            good in your mind, and that is the proper way, not to look like thinking “all
            nonsense.”’</p>
         <p>ESNEH, _Saturday_, _April_ 30.</p>
         <p>On Thursday evening as I was dreamily sitting on my divan, who should walk in but Arthur
            Taylor, on his way, all alone in a big dahabieh, to Edfou. So I offered to go too,
            whereupon he said he would go on to Assouan and see Philæ as he had company, and we went
            off to Mustapha to make a bargain with his Reis for it; thus then here we are at Esneh.
            I embarked on Wednesday evening, and we have been two days _en route_. Yesterday we had
            the thermometer at 110; I was the only person awake all day in the boat. Omar, after
            cooking, lay panting at my feet on the deck. Arthur went fairly to bed in the cabin;
            ditto Sally. All the crew slept on the deck. Omar cooked amphibiously, bathing between
            every meal. The silence of noon with the _white heat_ glowing on the river which flowed
            like liquid tin, and the silent Nubian rough boats floating down without a ripple, was
            magnificent and really awful. Not a breath of wind as we lay under the lofty bank. The
            Nile is not quite so low, and I see a very different scene from last year. People think
            us crazy to go up to Assouan in May, but I do enjoy it, and I really wanted to forget
            all the sickness and sorrow in which I have taken part. When I went to Mustapha’s he
            said Sheykh Yussuf was ill, and I said ‘Then I won’t go.’ But Yussuf came in with a sick
            headache only. Mustapha repeated my words to him, and never did I see such a lovely
            expression in a human face as that with which Yussuf said _Eh, ya Sitt_! Mustapha
            laughed, and told him to thank me, and Yussuf turned to me and said, in a low voice, ‘my
            sister does not need thanks, save from God.’ Fancy a Shereef, one of the Ulema, calling
            a _Frengeeyeh_ ‘sister’! His pretty little girl came in and played with me, and he
            offered her to me for Maurice. I cured Kursheed’s Abyssinian slave-girl. You would have
            laughed to see him obeying my directions, and wiping his eyes on his gold-embroidered
            sleeve. And then the Coptic priest came for me for his wife who was ill. He was in a
            great quandary, because, if she died, he, as a priest, could never marry again, as he
            loudly lamented before her; but he was truly grieved, and I was very happy to leave her
            convalescent.</p>
         <p>Verily we are sorely visited. The dead cattle float down by thousands. M. Mounier buried
            a thousand at El-Moutaneh alone, and lost forty men. I would not have left Luxor, but
            there were no new cases for four days before, and the worst had been over for full ten
            days. Two or three poor people brought me new bread and vegetables to the boat when they
            saw me going, and Yussuf came down and sat with us all the evening, and looked quite
            sad. Omar asked him why, and he said it made him think how it would seem when
            ‘_Inshallah_ should be well and should leave my place empty at Luxor and go back with
            the blessing of God to my own place and to my own people.’ Whereupon Omar grew quite
            sentimental too, and nearly cried. I don’t know how Arthur would have managed without
            us, for he had come with two Frenchmen who had proper servants and who left the boat at
            Girgeh, and he has a wretched little dirty idiotic Coptic tailor as a servant, who can’t
            even sew on a button. It is becoming quite a calamity about servants here. Arthur tells
            me that men, not fit to light Omar’s pipe, asked him £10 a month in <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> and would not take less, and he gives his Copt £4. I
            really feel as if I were cheating Omar to let him stay on for £3; but if I say anything
            he kisses my hand and tells me ‘not to be cross.’</p>
         <p>I have letters from Yussuf to people at Assouan. If I want anything I am to call on the
            Kadee. We have a very excellent boat and a good crew, and are very comfortable. When the
            Luxor folk heard the ‘son of my uncle’ was come, they thought it must be my husband. I
            was diverted at Omar’s propriety. He pointed out to Mustapha and Yussuf how _he_ was to
            sleep in the cabin between Arthur’s and mine, which was considered quite satisfactory
            apparently, and it was looked upon as very proper of Omar to have arranged it so, as he
            had been sent to put the boat in order. Arthur has been all along the Suez Canal, and
            seen a great many curious things. The Delta must be very unlike Upper Egypt from all he
            tells me. The little troop of pilgrims for Mecca left Luxor about ten days ago. It was a
            pretty and touching sight. Three camels, five donkeys, and about thirty men and women,
            several with babies on their shoulders, all uttering the _zaghareet_ (cry of joy). They
            were to walk to Koseir (eight days’ journey with good camels), babies and all. It is the
            happiest day of their lives, they say, when they have scraped together money enough to
            make the _hajj_.</p>
         <p>This minute a poor man is weeping beside our boat over a pretty heifer decked with many
            _hegabs_ (amulets), which have not availed against the sickness. It is heart-rending to
            see the poor beasts and their unfortunate owners. Some dancing girls came to the boat
            just now for cigars which Arthur had promised them, and to ask after their friend el
            Maghribeeyeh, the good dancer at Luxor, whom they said was very ill. Omar did not know
            at all about her, and the girls seemed much distressed. They were both very pretty, one
            an Abyssinian. I must leave off to send this to the post; it will cost a fortune, but
            you won’t grudge it.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>