<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>February 26, 1864: To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, LUXOR, February 26,
               1864.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK, </p>
         <p> I have just received your letter of the 3rd inst., and am glad to get such good
            tidings. You would be amused to see Omar bring me a letter and sit down on the floor
            till I tell him the family news, and then _Alhamdulillah_, we are so pleased, and he
            goes off to his pots and pans again. Lord and Lady Spencer are here, and his sister, in
            two boats. The English ‘Milord,’ extinct on the Continent, has revived in Egypt, and is
            greatly reverenced and usually much liked. ‘These high English have mercy in their
            stomachs,’ said one of my last year’s sailors who came to kiss my hand—a pleasing fact
            in natural history! _Fee wahed Lord_, was little ragged Achmet’s announcement of Lord
            Spencer—‘Here’s a Lord.’ They are very pleasant people. I heard from Janet to-day of
            _ice_ at <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> and at Shoubra, and famine prices. I
            cannot attempt <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> with meat at 1s. 3d. a pound,
            and will e’en stay here and grill at Thebes. Marry-come-up with your Thebes and
            savagery! What if we _do_ wear ragged brown shirts? ‘’Tis manners makyth man,’ and we
            defy you to show better breeding. </p>
         <p> We are now in the full enjoyment of summer weather; there has been no cold for fully a
            fortnight, and I am getting better every day now. My cough has quite subsided, and the
            pain in the chest much diminished; if the heat does not overpower me I feel sure it will
            be very healing to my lungs. I sit out on my glorious balcony and drink the air from
            early morning till noon, when the sun comes upon it and drives me under cover. The
            thermometer has stood at 64° for a fortnight or three weeks, rising sometimes to 67°,
            but people in the boats tell me it is still cold at night on the river. Up here, only a
            stone’s-throw from it, it is warm all night. I fear the loss of cattle has suspended
            irrigation to a fearful extent, and that the harvests of Lower Egypt of all kinds will
            be sadly scanty. The disease has not spread above Minieh, or very slightly; but, of
            course, cattle will rise in price here also. Already food is getting dearer here; meat
            is 4½ piastres—7d.—the _rötl_ (a fraction less than a pound), and bread has risen
            considerably—I should say corn, for no bakers exist here. I pay a woman to grind and
            bake my wheat which I buy, and delicious bread it is. It is impossible to say how
            exactly like the early parts of the Bible every act of life is here, and how totally new
            it seems when one reads it here. Old Jacob’s speech to Pharaoh really made me laugh
            (don’t be shocked), because it is so exactly what a fellah says to a Pasha: ‘Few and
            evil have been the days,’ etc. (Jacob being a most prosperous man); but it is manners to
            say all that, and I feel quite kindly to Jacob, whom I used to think ungrateful and
            discontented; and when I go to Sidi Omar’s farm, does he not say, ‘Take now fine meal
            and bake cakes quickly,’ and wants to kill a kid? _Fateereh_ with plenty of butter is
            what the ‘three men’ who came to Abraham ate; and the way that Abraham’s chief memlook,
            acting as Vakeel, manages Isaac’s marriage with Rebekah! All the vulgarized associations
            with Puritanism and abominable little ‘Scripture tales and pictures’ peel off here, and
            the inimitably truthful representation of life and character—not a flattering one
            certainly—comes out, and it feels like Homer. Joseph’s tears and his love for the
            brother born of the _same mother_ is so perfect. Only one sees what a bad inferior race
            the Beni Israel were compared to the Beni Ishmael or to the Egyptians. Leviticus and
            Deuteronomy are so very heathenish compared to the law of the Koran, or to the early
            days of Abraham. Verily the ancient Jews were a foul nation, judging by the police
            regulations needful for them. Please don’t make these remarks public, or I shall be
            burnt with Stanley and Colenso (unless I suffer Sheykh Yussuf to propose me El-Islam).
            He and M. de Rougé were here last evening, and we had an Arabic _soirée_. M. de Rougé
            speaks admirably, quite like an Alim, and it was charming to see Sheykh Yussuf’s pretty
            look of grateful pleasure at finding himself treated like a gentleman and a scholar by
            two such eminent Europeans; for I (as a woman) am quite as surprising as even M. de
            Rougé’s knowledge of hieroglyphics and Arabic _Fosseeha_. It is very interesting to see
            something of Arabs who have read and have the ‘gentleman’ ideas. His brother, the Imam,
            has lost his wife; he was married twenty-two years, and won’t hear of taking another. I
            was struck with the sympathy he expressed with the English Sultana, as all the
            uneducated people say, ‘Why doesn’t she marry again?’ It is curious how refinement
            brings out the same feelings under all ‘dispensations.’ I apologized to Yussuf for
            inadvertently returning the _Salaam aleykoum_ (Peace be with thee), which he said to
            Omar, and which I, as an unbeliever, could not accept. He coloured crimson, touched my
            hand and kissed his own, quite distressed lest the distinction might wound me. When I
            think of a young parsonic prig at home I shudder at the difference. But Yussuf is
            superstitious; he told me how someone down the river cured his cattle with water poured
            over a _Mushaf_ (a copy of the Koran), and has hinted at writing out a chapter for me to
            wear as a _hegab_ (an amulet for my health). He is interested in the antiquities and in
            M. de Rougé’s work, and is quite up to the connection between Ancient Egypt and the
            books of Moses, exaggerating the importance of _Seyidna Moussa_, of course. </p>
         <p> If I go down to <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> again I will get letters to
            some of the Alim there from Abd-el-Waris, the Imam here, and I shall see what no
            European but Lane has seen. I think things have altered since his day, and that men of
            that class would be less inaccessible than they were then; and then a woman who is old
            (Yussuf guessed me at sixty) and educated does not shock, and does interest them. All
            the Europeans here are traders, and only speak the vulgarest language, and don’t care to
            know Arab gentlemen; if they see anything above their servants it is only Turks, or Arab
            merchants at times. Don’t fancy that I can speak at all decently yet, but I understand a
            good deal, and stammer out a little.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>