<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Mrs. Austin, LUXOR, January 14, 1867.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/93">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <date when="1867-01-14">14 January 1867</date>
               <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/360630">Cairo</settlement>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/59830344">Sarah Austin</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST MUTTER, </p>
         <p> We have had a very cold winter and I have been constantly ailing, luckily the cough has
            transferred itself from the night to the day, and I get some good sleep. The last two
            days have been much warmer and I hope matters will mend. I am beginning to take
            cod-liver oil, as we can’t find a milch camel anywhere. </p>
         <p> My boat has been well let in <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> and is expected
            here every day. The gentlemen shoot, and tell the crew not to row, and in short take it
            easy, and give them £2 in every place. Imagine what luxury for my crew. I shall have to
            dismiss the lot, they will be so spoilt. The English Consul-General came up in a steamer
            with Dr. Patterson and Mr. Francis. I dined with them one day; I wish you could have
            seen me carried in my armchair high up on the shoulders of four men, like a successful
            candidate, or more like one of the Pharaohs in an ancient bas-relief, preceded by torch
            bearers and other attendants and followers, my procession was quite regal. I wish I
            could show you a new friend of mine, Osman Ibraheem, who studied medicine five years in
            Paris. My heart warmed to him directly, because like most high-bred Arabs, he is so like
            Don Quixote—only Don Quixote quite in his senses. The sort of innocent sententiousness,
            and perfectly natural love of fine language and fine sentiments is unattainable to any
            European, except, I suppose, a Spaniard. It is quite unlike Italian fustian or French
            _sentiment_. I suppose to most Europeans it is ridiculous, but I used to cry when the
            carriers beat the most noble of all knights, when I was a little girl and read Don
            Quixote; and now I felt as it were like Sancho, when I listened to Osman reciting bits
            of heroic poetry, or uttering ‘wise saws’ and ‘modern instances,’ with the peculiar
            mixture of strong sense of ‘exultation’ which stamps the great Don. I may not repeat all
            I heard from him of the state of things here, and the insults he had to endure—a Shereef
            and an educated man—from coarse Turkish Pashas; it was the carriers over again. He told
            me he had often cried like a woman, at night in his own room, at the miseries he was
            forced to witness and could do nothing to relieve; all the men I have particularly liked
            I find are more or less pupils of the Sheykh el-Bagooree now dead, who seems to have had
            a gift of inspiring honourable feeling. Our good Maōhn is one; he is no conjuror, but
            the honesty and goodness are heroic which lead a man to starve on £15 a month, when he
            is expected to grow rich on plunder. </p>
         <p> The war in Crete saddens many a household here. Sheykh Yussuf’s brother, Sheykh Yooris,
            is serving there, and many more. People are actually beginning to say ‘We hope the
            English and French won’t fight for the Sultan if the Moscovites want to eat him—there
            will be no good for us till the Turks are driven out.’ All the old religious devotion to
            the Sultan seems quite gone. </p>
         <p> Poor Mustapha has been very unwell and I stopped his Ramadan, gave him some physic and
            ordered him not to fast, for which I think he is rather grateful. The Imaam and Mufti
            always endorse my prohibitions of fasting to my patients. Old Ismaeen is dead, aged over
            a hundred; he served Belzoni, and when he grew doting was always wanting me to go with
            him to join Belzoni at Abu Simbel. He was not at all ill—he only went out like a candle.
            His grandson brought me a bit of the meat cooked at his funeral, and begged me to eat
            it, that I might live to be very old, according to the superstition here. When they
            killed the buffalo for the Sheykh Abu-l-Hajjaj, the man who had a right to the feet
            kindly gave them to Omar, who wanted to make calves’ foot jelly for me. I had a sort of
            profane feeling, as if I were eating a descendant of the bull Apis. </p>
         <p> I am reading Mme. du Deffand’s letters. What a repulsive picture of a woman. I don’t
            know which I dislike most, Horace Walpole or herself: the conflict of selfishness,
            vanity and _ennui_ disguised as sentiment is quite hateful: to her Turgot was _un sot
            animal_,—so much for her great gifts. </p>
         <p> Remember me kindly to William and tell him how much I wish I could see his
            ‘improvements,’ Omar also desires his salaam to him, having a sort of fellow feeling for
            your faithful henchman. I need not say he kisses your hand most dutifully.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>