<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>February 8, 1864: February 8, 1864, LUXOR, Tuesday, February 8, 1864.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST CHILD, </p>
         <p> I got your letter No. 3 about a week ago, and two others before it. I have been very
            lazy in writing, for it has been very cold (for Thebes), and I have been very seedy—no
            severe attack, but no strength at all. The last three or four days the weather has been
            warm, and I am beginning to feel better. I send this to <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> by a clever, pleasant Mme. de Beaulaincourt, a daughter of
            Maréchal Castellane, who is here in one of the Pasha’s steamers. She will call on you
            when she goes to Alexandria. I have been learning to write Arabic, and know my
            letters—no trifle, I assure you. My Sheykh is a perfect darling—the most graceful,
            high-bred young creature, and a Seyyid. These Saeedees are much nicer than the Lower
            Egypt people. They have good Arab blood in their veins, keep pedigrees, and are more
            manly and independent, and more liberal in religion. </p>
         <p> Sheykh Yussuf took me into the tomb of his ancestor, Sheykh Abul Hajjaj, the great
            saint here, and all the company said a Fathah for my health. It was on the night of
            Friday, and during the moolid of the Sheykh. Omar was surprised at the proceeding, and a
            little afraid the dead Sheykh might be offended. My great friend is the Maōhn (police
            magistrate) here—a very kind, good man, much liked, I hear, by all except the Kadee, who
            was displeased at his giving the stick to a Mussulman for some wrong to a Copt. I am
            beginning to stammer out a little Arabic, but find it horribly difficult. The plurals
            are bewildering and the verbs quite heart-breaking. I have no books, which makes
            learning very slow work. I have written to Hekekian Bey to buy me a dictionary. </p>
         <p> The house here is delightful—rather cold now, but will be perfect in hot weather—so
            airy and cheerful. I think I shall stay on here all the time the expense is nil, and it
            is very comfortable. I have a friend in a farm in a neighbouring village, and am much
            amused at seeing country life. It cannot be rougher, as regards material comforts, in
            New Zealand or Central Africa, but there is no barbarism or lack of refinement in the
            manners of the people. M. Mounier has invited me to go and stay with them at
            El-Moutaneh, and offers to send his dahabieh for me. When it gets really hot I shall
            like the trip very much. </p>
         <p> Pray, when you see Mme. Tastu, say civil things for me, and tell her how much I like
            the house. I think it wonderful that Omar cooked the dinner without being cross. I am
            sure I should swear if I had to cook for a heretic in Ramadan.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>