<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>May 25, 1863: Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, CAIRO, May 25, 1863.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK,</p>

         <p>I have spun such a yarn to my mother that I shall make it serve for both. It may amuse
            you to see what impression <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> makes. I ride along
            on my valiant donkey led by the stalwart Hassan and attended by Omar, and constantly
            say, ‘Oh, if our master were here, how pleased he would be’—husband is not a correct
            word.</p>

         <p>I went out to the tombs yesterday. Fancy that Omar witnessed the destruction of some
            sixty-eight or so of the most exquisite buildings—the tombs and mosques of the Arab
            Khaleefehs, which Said Pasha used to divert himself with bombarding for practice for his
            artillery. Omar was then in the boy corps of camel artillery, now disbanded. Thus the
            Pasha added the piquancy of sacrilege to barbarity.</p>

         <p>The street and the neighbours would divert you. Opposite lives a Christian dyer who must
            be a seventh brother of the admirable barber. The same impertinence, loquacity, and love
            of meddling in everybody’s business. I long to see him thrashed, though he is a constant
            comedy. My delightful servant, Omar Abou-el-Halláweh (the father of sweets)—his family
            are pastrycooks—is the type of all the amiable _jeune premiers_ of the stories. I am
            privately of opinion that he is Bedr-ed-Deen Hassan, the more that he can make cream
            tarts and there is no pepper in them. Cream tarts are not very good, but lamb stuffed
            with pistachio nuts fulfils all one’s dreams of excellence. The Arabs next door and the
            Levantines opposite are quiet enough, but how _do_ they eat all the cucumbers they buy
            of the man who cries them every morning as ‘fruit gathered by sweet girls in the garden
            with the early dew.’</p>

         <p>The more I see of the back-slums of <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>, the more
            in love I am with it. The oldest European towns are tame and regular in comparison, and
            the people are so pleasant. If you smile at anything that amuses you, you get the
            kindest, brightest smiles in return; they give hospitality with their faces, and if one
            brings out a few words, ‘Mashallah! what Arabic the Sitt Ingleez speaks.’ The Arabs are
            clever enough to understand the amusement of a stranger and to enter into it, and are
            amused in turn, and they are wonderfully unprejudiced. When Omar explains to me their
            views on various matters, he adds: ‘The Arab people think so—I know not if right;’ and
            the way in which the Arab merchants worked the electric telegraph, and the eagerness of
            the Fellaheen for steam-ploughs, are quite extraordinary. They are extremely clever and
            nice children, easily amused, easily roused into a fury which lasts five minutes and
            leaves no malice, and half the lying and cheating of which they are accused comes from
            misunderstanding and ignorance. When I first took Omar he was by way of ‘ten pounds,
            twenty pounds,’ being nothing for my dignity. But as soon as I told him that ‘my master
            was a Bey who got £100 a month and no backsheesh,’ he was as careful as if for himself.
            They see us come here and do what only their greatest Pashas do, hire a boat to
            ourselves, and, of course, think our wealth is boundless. The lying is mostly from
            fright. They dare not suggest a difference of opinion to a European, and lie to get out
            of scrapes which blind obedience has often got them into. As to the charges of
            shopkeepers, that is the custom, and the haggling a ceremony you must submit to. It is
            for the purchaser or employer to offer a price and fix wages—the reverse of Europe—and
            if you ask the price they ask something fabulous at random.</p>

         <p>I hope to go home next month, as soon as it gets too hot here and is likely to be warm
            enough in England. I do so long to see the children again.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>