<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>February 7, 1865: Mrs. Ross, LUXOR, February 7, 1865.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST JANET, </p>
         <p> It is quite heartrending about my letters. I have ‘got the eye’ evidently. The black
            slave of the poor dragoman who died in my house is here still, and like a dog that has
            lost his master has devoted himself to me. It seems nobody’s business to take him
            away—as the Kadee did the money and the goods—and so it looks as if I should quietly
            inherit poor ugly Khayr. He is of a degree of ugliness quite transcendent, with teeth
            filed sharp ‘in order to eat people’ as he says, but the most good-humoured creature and
            a very fair laundry-maid. It is evidently no concern of mine to send him to be sold in
               <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>, so I wait the event. If nobody ever claims
            him I shall keep him at whatever wages may seem fit, and he will subside into liberty.
            _Du reste_, the Maōhn here says he is legally entitled to his freedom. If the new French
            Consul-General will let me stay on here I will leave my furniture and come down straight
            to your hospitable roof in Alexandria _en route_ for Europe. I fear my plan of a
            dahabieh of my own would be too expensive, the wages of common boatmen now are three
            napoleons a month. M. Prévost Paradol, whose company has been a real _bonne fortune_ to
            me, will speak to the Consul-General. I know all Thebes would sign a round-robin in my
            favour if they only knew how, for I am very popular here, and the only _Hakeen_. I have
            effected some brilliant cures, and get lots of presents. Eggs, turkeys, etc., etc., it
            is quite a pleasure to see how the poor people instead of trying to sponge on one are
            anxious to make a return for kindness. I give nothing whatever but my physick. These
            country people are very good. A nice young Circassian Cawass sat up with a stranger, a
            dying Englishman, all night because I had doctored his wife. I have also a pupil,
            Mustapha’s youngest boy, a sweet intelligent lad who is pining for an education. I wish
            he could go to England. He speaks English very well and reads and writes indifferently,
            but I never saw a boy so wild to learn. Is it difficult to get a boy into the Abbassieh
            college? as it is gratuitous I suppose it is. I quite grieve over little Ach met forced
            to dawdle away his time and his faculties here.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>