<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>March 30, 1865: Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, LUXOR, March 30, 1865.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK, </p>
         <p> I have just received your letter of March 3 with one from Janet, which shows of how
            little moment the extermination of four villages is in this country, for she does not
            allude to our revolt and evidently has not heard of it. </p>
         <p> In my last letter to Mutter I told how one Achmet et Tayib, a mad darweesh had raised a
            riot at Gau below Keneh and how a boat had been robbed and how we were all rather
            looking out for a _razzia_ and determined to fight Achmet et Tayib and his followers.
            Then we called them _harámee_ (wicked ones) and were rather blood-thirstily disposed
            towards them and resolved to keep order and protect our property. But now we say _nas
            messakeen_ (poor people) and whisper to each other that God will not forget what the
            Pasha has done. The truth of course we shall never know. But I do know that one Pasha
            said he had hanged five hundred, and another that he had sent three hundred to Fazoghlou
            (_comme qui dirait Cayenne_) and all for the robbery of one Greek boat in which only the
            steersman was killed. I cannot make out that anything was done by the ‘insurgents’
            beyond going out into the desert to listen to the darweesh’s nonsense, and ‘see a reed
            shaken by the wind;’ the party that robbed the boat was, I am told, about forty strong.
            But the most horrid stories are current among the people of the atrocities committed on
            the wretched villagers by the soldiers. Not many were shot, they say, and they attempted
            no resistance, but the women and girls were outraged and murdered and the men hanged and
            the steamers loaded with plunder. The worst is that every one believes that the
            Europeans aid and abet, and all declare that the Copts were spared to please the
            _Frangees_. Mind I am not telling you _facts_ only what the people are saying—in order
            to show you their feelings. One most respectable young man sat before me on the floor
            the other day and told me what he had heard from those who had come up the river.
            Horrible tales of the stench of the bodies which are left unburied by the Pasha’s
            order—of women big with child ripped open, etc., etc. ‘Thou knowest oh! our Lady, that
            we are people of peace in this place, and behold now if one madman should come and a few
            idle fellows go out to the mountain (desert) with him, Effendina will send his soldiers
            to destroy the place and spoil our poor little girls and hang us—is that right, oh Lady
            and Achmet el-Berberi saw Europeans with hats in the steamer with Effendina and the
            soldiers. Truly in all the world none are miserable like us Arabs. The Turks beat us,
            and the Europeans hate us and say _quite right_. By God, we had better lay down our
            heads in the dust (die) and let the strangers take our land and grow cotton for
            themselves. As for me I am tired of this miserable life and of fearing for my poor
            little girls.’ </p>
         <p> Mahommed was really eloquent, and when he threw his _melayeh_ over his face and sobbed,
            I am not ashamed to say that I cried too. I know very well that Mahommed was not quite
            wrong in what he says of the Europeans. I know the cruel old platitudes about governing
            Orientals by fear which the English pick up like mocking birds from the Turks. I know
            all about ‘the stick’ and ‘vigour’ and all that—but—‘I sit among the people’ and I know
            too that Mohammed feels just as John Smith or Tom Brown would feel in his place, and
            that men who were very savage against the rioters in the beginning, are now almost in a
            humour to rise against the Turks themselves just exactly as free-born Britons might be.
            There are even men of the class who have something to lose who express their disgust
            very freely. </p>
         <p> I saw the steamer pass up to Fazoghlou but the prisoners were all below. The Sheykh of
            the Abab’deh here has had to send a party of his men to guard them through the desert.
            Altogether this year is miserable in Egypt. I have not once heard the _zaghareet_. Every
            one is anxious and depressed, and I fear hungry, the land is parched from the low Nile,
            the heat has set in six weeks earlier than usual, the animals are scarecrows for want of
            food, and now these horrid stories of bloodshed and cruelty and robbery (for the Pasha
            takes the lands of these villages for his own) have saddened every face. I think Hajjee
            Ali is right and that there will be more disturbances. If there are they will be caused
            by the cruelty and oppression at Gau and the three neighbouring villages. From Salamieh,
            two miles above Luxor, every man woman and child in any degree kin to Achmet et-Tayib
            has been taken in chains to Keneh and no one here expects to see one of them return
            alive. Some are remarkably good men, I hear, and I have heard men say ‘if Hajjee Sultan
            is killed and all his family we will never do a good action any more, for we see it is
            of no use.’ </p>
         <p> There was a talk among the three or four Europeans here at the beginning of the rumours
            of a revolt of organizing a defence among Christians only. Conceive what a silly and
            gratuitous provocation! There was no religion in the business at all and of course the
            proper person to organize defence was the Maōhn, and he and Mustapha and others had
            planned using my house as a castle and defending that in case of a visit from the
            rioters. I have no doubt the true cause of the row is the usual one—hunger—the high
            price of food. It was like our Swing, or bread riots, nothing more and a very feeble
            affair too. It is curious to see the travellers’ gay dahabiehs just as usual and the
            Europeans as far removed from all care or knowledge of the distresses as if they were at
            home. When I go and sit with the English I feel almost as if they were foreigners to me
            too, so completely am I now _Dint el-Beled_ (daughter of the country) here. </p>
         <p> I dined three days running with the Kevenbrincks and one day after dinner we sent for a
            lot of Arab Sheykhs to come for coffee—the two Abab’deh and a relation of theirs from
            Khartoum, the Sheykh of Karnac, one Mohammed a rich fellah, and we were joined by the
            A’gha of Halim Pasha’s Hareem, and an ugly beast he is. The little Baroness won all
            hearts. She is a regular _vif argent_ or as we say _Efreeteh_ and to see the dark faces
            glittering with merry smiles as they watched her was very droll. I never saw a human
            being so thoroughly amused as the black Sheykh from the Soudan. Next day we dined at the
            Austrian agent’s and the Baroness at last made the Maōhn dance a polka with her while
            the agent played the guitar. There were a lot of Copts about who nearly died of laughing
            and indeed so did I. Next day we had a capital dinner at Mustapha’s, and the two
            Abab’deh Sheykhs, the Sheykh of Karnac, the Maōhn and Sheykh Yussuf dined with us. The
            Sheykh of Karnac gave a grand performance of eating like a Bedawee. I have heard you
            talk of _tripas elasticas_ in Spain but _Wallahi_! anything like the performance of
            Sheykh Abdallah none but an eyewitness could believe. How he plucked off the lamb’s head
            and handed it to me in token of the highest respect, and how the bones cracked beneath
            his fingers—how huge handfuls of everything were chucked right down his throat all
            scorching hot. I encouraged him of course, quoting the popular song about ‘doing deeds
            that Antar did not’ and we all grew quite uproarious. When Sheykh Abdallah asked for
            drink, I cried ‘bring the _ballaree_ (the big jar the women fetch water in) for the
            Sheykh,’ and Sheykh Yussuf compared him to Samson and to Og, while I more profanely told
            how Antar broke the bones and threw them about. The little Baroness was delighted and
            only expressed herself hurt that no one had crammed anything into her mouth. I told the
            Maōhn her disappointment which caused more laughter as such a custom is unknown here,
            but he of course made no end of sweet speeches to her. After dinner she showed the Arabs
            how ladies curtsey to the Queen in England, and the Abab’deh acted the ceremonial of
            presentation at the court of Darfour, where you have to rub your nose in the dust at the
            King’s feet. Then we went out with lanterns and torches and the Abab’deh did the sword
            dance for us. Two men with round shields and great straight swords do it. One dances a
            _pas seul_ of challenge and defiance with prodigious leaps and pirouettes and Hah! Hahs!
            Then the other comes and a grand fight ensues. When the handsome Sheykh Hassan (whom you
            saw in <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>) bounded out it really was heroic. All
            his attitudes were alike grand and graceful. They all wanted Sheykh Yussuf to play
            _el-Neboot_ (single stick) and said he was the best man here at it, but his sister was
            not long dead and he could not. Hassan looks forward to Maurice’s coming here to teach
            him ‘the fighting of the English.’ How Maurice would pound him! </p>
         <p> On the fourth night I went to tea in Lord Hopetoun’s boat and their sailors gave a
            grand _fantasia_ excessively like a Christmas pantomime. One danced like a woman, and
            there was a regular pantaloon only ‘more so,’ and a sort of clown in sheepskin and a
            pink mask who was duly tumbled about, and who distributed _claques_ freely with a huge
            wooden spoon. It was very good fun indeed, though it was quite as well that the ladies
            did not understand the dialogue, or that part of the dance which made the Maōhn roar
            with laughter. The Hopetouns had two handsome boats and were living like in May Fair. I
            am so used now to our poor shabby life that it makes quite a strange impression on me to
            see all that splendour—splendour which a year or two ago I should not even have
            remarked—and thus out of ‘my inward consciousness’ (as Germans say), many of the
            peculiarities and faults of the people of Egypt are explained to me and accounted for. </p>
         <p> _April_ 2.—It is so dreadfully hot and dusty that I shall rather hasten my departure if
            I can. The winds seem to have begun, and as all the land which last year was green is
            now desert and dry the dust is four times as bad. If I hear that Ross has bought and
            sent up a dahabieh I will wait for that, if not I will go in three weeks if I can.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>