<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>April, 1866: Mrs. Ross, EED EL KEBEER, Wednesday, April, 1866.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST JANET, </p>
         <p> I had not heard a word of Henry’s illness till Mr. Palgrave arrived and told me, and
            also that he was better. Alhamdulillah! I only hope that you are not knocked up, my
            darling. I am not ill, but still feel unaccountably weak and listless. I don’t cough
            much, and have got fatter on my _régime_ of camel’s milk,—so I hope I may get over the
            languor. The box has not made its appearance. What a clever fellow Mr. Palgrave is! I
            never knew such a hand at languages. The folks here are in admiration at his Arabic. I
            hope you will see M. Brune. I am sure you would like him. He is a very accomplished and
            gentlemanly man. </p>
         <p> You have never told me your plans for this year or whether I shall find you when I go
            down. The last three days the great heat has begun and I am accordingly feeling better.
            I have just come home from the Bairam early prayer out in the burial-place, at which
            Palgrave also assisted. He is unwell, and tells me he leaves Luxor to-morrow morning. I
            shall stay on till I am too hot here, as evidently the summer suits me. </p>
         <p> Many thanks for Miss Berry and for the wine, which makes a very pleasant change from
            the rather bad claret I have got. Palgrave’s book I have read through hard, as he wished
            to take it back for you. It is very amusing. </p>
         <p> If you come here next winter Mustapha hopes you will bring a saddle, and ride ‘all his
            horses.’ I think I could get you a very good horse from a certain Sheykh Abdallah here. </p>
         <p> Well, I must say good-bye. _Kulloo sana intee tayib_, love to Henry.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>