<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, BENISOUEF, June 30, 1867.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc ref="http://notes-from-egypt.info/lucie-duff-gordon/letters/103">
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/66577149">Lucie Duff Gordon</persName>
               <date when="1867-06-30">30 June 1867</date>
               <settlement ref="http://www.geonames.org/359173">Banī Suwayf</settlement>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/315623459">Sir Alexander Duff Gordon</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK, </p>
         <p> I write on the chance that this may go safe by post so that you may not think me lost.
            I left Luxor on May 31, got to Siout (half-way) in a week, and have ever since been
            battling with an unceasing furious north and north-east wind. I feel like the much
            travelled Odysseus, and have seen ‘villages and men,’ unlike him, however ‘my
            companions’ have neither grumbled nor deserted, though it is a bad business for them,
            having received their money at the rate of about twenty days’ pay, for which they must
            take me to <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>. They have eaten all, and are now
            obliged to stop and make bread here, but they are as good-humoured as if all were well.
            My fleet consisted of my dahabieh, flag ship; tender, a _kyasseh_ (cargo boat) for my
            horse and sais, wherein were packed two extremely poor shrivelled old widows, going to
               <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> to see their sons, now in garrison there;
            lots of hard bread, wheat, flour, jars of butter, onions and lentils for all the lads of
            ‘my family’ studying at Gama’l Azhar, besides in my box queer little stores of long
            hoarded money for those _megowareen_ (students of Gama’l Azhar). Don’t you wish you
            could provide for Maurice with a sack of bread, a basket of onions and one pound sixteen
            shillings? </p>
         <p> The handsome brown Sheykh el-Arab, Hassan, wanted me to take him, but I knew him to be
            a ‘fast’ man, and asked Yussuf how I could avoid it without breaking the laws of
            hospitality, so my ‘father,’ the old Shereef, told Hassan that he did not choose his
            daughter to travel with a wine-bibber and a frequenter of loose company. Under my convoy
            sailed two or three little boats with family parties. One of these was very pretty,
            whose steersman was a charming little fat girl of five years old. All these hoped to
            escape being caught and worried by the way, by belonging to me, and they dropped off at
            their several villages. I am tolerably well, better than when I started, in spite of the
            wind. </p>
         <p> Poor Reis Mohammed had a very bad attack of ophthalmia, and sat all of a heap, groaning
            all day and night, and protesting ‘I am a Muslim,’ equivalent to ‘God’s will be done.’
            At one place I was known, and had a lot of sick to see, and a civil man killed a sheep
            and regaled us all with meat and _fateereh_. The part of the river in which we were kept
            by the high wind is made cheerful by the custom of the Hareem being just as free to mix
            with men as Europeans, and I quite enjoyed the pretty girls’ faces, and the gossip with
            the women who came to fill their water-jars and peep in at the cabin windows, which, by
            the way, they always ask leave to do. The Sheykh el-Hawara gave me two sheep which are
            in the cargo-boat with four others—all presents—which Omar intends you to eat at
               <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>. The Sheykh is very anxious to give you an
            entertainment at his palace, if you come up the river, with horse-riding, feasting and
            dancing girls. In fact I am charged with many messages to _el-Kebir_ (the great
            master).</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>