<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>October 17, 1867: Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, BOULAK, BOAT MARIE LOUISE, October
               17, 1867.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK, </p>
         <p> You must not be wroth with me because I have not written for a long time—I have been
            ill, but am much better. Omar will go down to Alexandria to meet Maurice on Monday. </p>
         <p> My boat is being painted, but is nearly finished; as soon as it is done I shall move
            back into her. I got out into a little cangia but it swarmed with bugs and wasps, and
            was too dirty, so I moved yesterday into a good boat belonging to a dragoman, and hope
            to be back in my own by Sunday. But oh Lord! I got hold of the Barber himself turned
            painter; and as the little cangia was moored alongside the _Urania_ in order to hold all
            the mattresses, carpets, etc. I was his victim. First, it was a request for ‘three
            pounds to buy paint.’ ‘None but the best of paint is fitting for a noble person like
            thee, and that thou knowest is costly, and I am thy servant and would do thee honour.’
            ‘Very well,’ say I, ‘take the money, and see, oh man, that the paint is of the best, or
            thy backsheesh will be bad also.’ Well, he begins and then rushes in to say: ‘Come oh
            Bey, oh Pasha! and behold the brilliancy of the white paint, like milk, like glass, like
            the full moon.’ I go and say, ‘Mashallah! but now be so good as to work fast, for my son
            will be here in a few days, and nothing is ready.’ Fatal remark. ‘Mashallah! Bismillah!
            may the Lord spare him, may God prolong thy days, let me advise thee how to keep the eye
            from him, for doubtless thy son is beautiful as a memlook of 1,000 purses. Remember to
            spit in his face when he comes on board, and revile him aloud that all the people may
            hear thee, and compel him to wear torn and dirty clothes when he goes out:—and how many
            children hast thou, and our master, thy master, and is he well?’ etc. etc. ‘_Shukr
            Allah_! all is well with us,’ say I; ‘but, by the Prophet, paint, oh _Ma-alim_ (exactly
            the German _Meister_) and do not break my head any more.’ But I was forced to take
            refuge at a distance from Hajj’ Alee’s tongue. Read the story of the Barber, and you
            will know exactly what Ma-alim Hajj’ Alee is. Also just as I got out of my boat and he
            had begun, the painter whom I had last year and with whom I was dissatisfied, went to
            the Sheykh of the painters and persuaded him to put my man in prison for working too
            cheap—that was at daybreak. So I sent up my Reis to the Sheykh to inform him that if my
            man did not return by next day at daybreak, I would send for an European painter and
            force the Sheykh to pay the bill. Of course my man came. </p>
         <p> My steersman Hassan, and a good man, Hoseyn, who can wash and is generally nice and
            pleasant, arrived from el-Bastowee a few days ago, and are waiting here till I want
            them. Poor little ugly black Hassan has had his house burnt down in his village, and
            lost all the clothes which he had bought with his wages; they were very good clothes,
            some of them, and a heavy loss. He is my Reis’s brother, and a good man, clean and
            careful and quiet, better than my Reis even—they are a respectable family. Big stout
            Hazazin owes me 200 piastres which he is to work out, so I have still five men and a boy
            to get. I hope a nice boy, called Hederbee (the lizard), will come. They don’t take pay
            till the day before we sail, except the Reis and Abdul Sadig, who are permanent. But
            Hassan and Hoseyn are working away as merrily as if they were paid. People growl at the
            backsheesh, but they should also remember what a quantity of service one gets for
            nothing here, and for which, oddly enough, no one dreams of asking backsheesh. Once a
            week we shift the anchors, for fear of their silting over, and six or eight men work for
            an hour; then the mast is lowered—twelve or fourteen men work at this—and nobody gets a
            farthing. </p>
         <p> The other day Omar met in the market an ‘agreeable merchant,’ an Abyssinian fresh from
            his own country, which he had left because of the tyranny of Kassa, alias Todoros, the
            Sultan. The merchant had brought his wife and concubines to live here. His account is
            that the mass of the people are delighted to hear that the English are coming to conquer
            them, as they hope, and that everyone hates the King except two or three hundred scamps
            who form his bodyguard. He had seen the English prisoners, who, he says, are not
            ill-treated, but certainly in danger, as the King is with difficulty restrained from
            killing them by the said scamps, who fear the revenge of the English; also that there is
            one woman imprisoned with the native female prisoners. Hassan the donkeyboy, when he was
            a _marmiton_ in <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>, knew the Sultan Todoros, he
            was the only man who could be found to interpret between the then King of Abyssinia and
            Mohammed Ali Pasha, whom Todoros had come to visit. The merchant also expressed a great
            contempt for the Patriarch, and for their _Matraam_ or Metropolitan, whom the English
            papers call the _Abuna_. _Abuna_ is Arabic for ‘our father.’ The man is a Cairene Copt
            and was a hanger-on of two English missionaries (they were really Germans) here, and he
            is more than commonly a rascal and a hypocrite. I know a respectable Jew whom he had
            robbed of all his merchandise, only Ras Alee forced the _Matraam_ to disgorge. Pray what
            was all that nonsense about the Armenian Patriarch of Jerusalem writing to Todoros? what
            could he have to do with it? The Coptic Patriarch, whose place is <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>, could do it if he were forced. </p>
         <p> At last my boat is finished, so to-morrow Omar will clean the windows, and on Saturday
            move in the cushions, etc. and me, and on Sunday go to Alexandria. I hear the dreadful
            voice of Hajj’ Alee, the painter, outside, and will retire before he gets to the cabin
            door, for fear he should want to bore me again. I do hope Maurice will enjoy his
            journey; everyone is anxious to please him. The Sheykh of the Hawara sent his brother to
            remind me to stop at his ‘palace’ near Girgeh, that he might make a fantasia for my son.
            So Maurice will see real Arab riding, and jereed, and sheep roasted whole and all the
            rest of it. The Sheykh is the last of the great Arab chieftains of Egypt, and has
            thousands of fellaheen and a large income. He did it for Lord Spencer and for the Duke
            of Rutland and I shall get as good a fantasia, I have no doubt. Perhaps at Keneh Maurice
            had better not see the dancing, for Zeyneb and Latefeeh are terribly fascinating, they
            are such pleasant jolly girls as well as pretty and graceful, but old Oum ez-Zeyn
            (mother of beauty), so-called on account of his hideousness, will want us to eat his
            good dinner.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>