<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>June 14, 1868: Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, BOULAK, June 14, 1868.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK, </p>
         <p> The climate has been odious for Egypt—to shiver in cold winds of June on the Nile seems
            hard. Maurice inherits my faculty for getting on with ‘d------d niggers’; all the crew
            kissed him on both cheeks and swore to come back again in the winter; and up the country
            he was hand and glove with all the fellaheen, eating a good deal of what he called
            ‘muck’ with great enjoyment, walking arm in arm with a crazy derweesh, fetching home a
            bride at night and swearing lustily by the Prophet. The good manners of the Arab
            _canaille_, have rubbed off the very disagreeable varnish which he got at Brussels. </p>
         <p> Dr. Patterson wants me to go to Beyrout or one of the Greek isles for a change. I am
            very feeble and short of breath—but I will try the experiment. Would you be shocked if a
            nigger taught Maurice? One Hajjee Daboos I know to be a capital Arabic scholar and he
            speaks French like a Parisian, and Italian also, only he is a real nigger and so is the
            best music-master in <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName>. _Que faire_? it’s not
            catching, as Lady Morley said, and I won’t present you with a young mulatto any more
            than with a young _brave Belge_. I may however find someone at Beyrout. <placeName ref="Cairo">Cairo</placeName> is in such a state of beggary that all educated young
            men have fled. Maurice has no sort of idea why a nigger should not be as good as anyone
            else, but thinks perhaps you might not approve. </p>
         <p> You would have stared to see old Achmet Agha Abd el-Sadig, a very good friend of ours
            at Assouan, coaxing and patting the _weled_ (boy) when he dined here the other day, and
            laughing immoderately at Maurice’s nonsense. He is one of the M.P.’s for Assouan, and a
            wealthy and much respected man in the Saeed. The Abyssinian affair is an awful
            disappointment to the Pasha; he had laid his calculations for something altogether
            different, and is furious. The Coptic clergy are ready to murder us. The Arabs are all
            in raptures. ‘God bless the English general, he has frightened our Pasha.’ </p>
         <p> Giafar Pasha backsheeshed me an _abbayeh_ of crimson silk and gold, also a basket of
            coffee. I was obliged to accept them as he sent his son with them, and to refuse would
            have been an insult, and as he is the one Turk I do think highly of I did not wish to
            affront him. It was at Luxor on his way to Khartoum. He also invited Maurice to
            Khartoum, and proposed to send a party to fetch him from Korosko, on the Nile. Giafar is
            Viceroy of the Soudan, and a very quiet man, who does not ‘eat the people.’ </p>
         <p> My best love to Janet, I’ll write soon to her, but I am _lazy_ and Maurice is worse.
            Omar nearly cried when Maurice went to Alexandria for a week. ‘I seem to feel how dull
            we shall be without him when he goes away for good,’ said he, and Darfour expresses his
            intention of going with Maurice. ‘Thou must give me to the young man backsheesh,’ as he
            puts it, ‘because I have plenty of sense and shall tell him what to do.’ That is the
            little rascal’s sauce. Terence’s slaves are true to the life here.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>