<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>June 15, 1869: Sir Alexander Duff Gordon, BOULAK, June 15, 1869.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Text taken from http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/17816</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>DEAREST ALICK, </p>
         <p> Do not think of coming here. Indeed it would be almost too painful to me to part from
            you again; and as it is, I can patiently wait for the end among people who are kind and
            loving enough to be comfortable, without too much feeling of the pain of parting. The
            leaving Luxor was rather a distressing scene, as they did not think to see me again. </p>
         <p> The kindness of all the people was really touching, from the Kadee who made ready my
            tomb among his own family, to the poorest fellaheen. Omar sends you his most heartfelt
            thanks, and begs that the boat may remain registered at the Consulate in your name for
            his use and benefit. The Prince has appointed him his own dragoman. But he is sad
            enough, poor fellow, all his prosperity does not console him for the loss of ‘the mother
            he found in the world.’ Mohammed at Luxor wept bitterly and said, ‘poor I, my poor
            children, poor all the people,’ and kissed my hand passionately, and the people at
            Esneh, asked leave to touch me ‘for a blessing,’ and everyone sent delicate bread, and
            their best butter, and vegetables and lambs. They are kinder than ever now that I can no
            longer be of any use to them. </p>
         <p> If I live till September I will go up to Esneh, where the air is softest and I cough
            less. I would rather die among my own people in the Saeed than here. </p>
         <p> You must forgive this scrawl, dearest. Don’t think please of sending Maurice out again,
            he must begin to work now or he will never be good for anything. </p>
         <p> Can you thank the Prince of Wales for Omar, or shall I write? He was most pleasant and
            kind, and the Princess too. She is the most perfectly simple-mannered girl I ever saw.
            She does not even try to be civil like other great people, but asks blunt questions, and
            looks at one so heartily with her clear, honest eyes, that she must win all hearts. They
            were more considerate than any people I have seen, and the Prince, instead of being
            gracious, was, if I may say so, quite respectful in his manner: he is very well bred and
            pleasant, and has the honest eyes that makes one sure he has a kind heart. </p>
         <p> My sailors were so proud at having the honour of rowing him _in our own boat_, and of
            singing to him. I had a very good singer in the boat. Please send some little present
            for my Reis: he is such a good man; he will be pleased at some little thing from you. He
            is half Turk, and seems like whole one. Maurice will have told you all about us.
            Good-bye for the present, dearest Alick.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>